<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Planes apokalypsis. Popery manifested, or, the Papist incognito made known by way of dialogue betwixt a Papist priest, Protestant gentleman, and Presbyterian divine. In two parts. Intended for the good of those that shall read it by L. B. P.</title>
            <author>Beaulieu, Luke, 1644 or 5-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 244 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1574B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232440</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897991</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897991</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170992</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76286)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170992)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2545:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Planes apokalypsis. Popery manifested, or, the Papist incognito made known by way of dialogue betwixt a Papist priest, Protestant gentleman, and Presbyterian divine. In two parts. Intended for the good of those that shall read it by L. B. P.</title>
                  <author>Beaulieu, Luke, 1644 or 5-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 52, [4], 75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Henry Brome, at the Gun at the west end of S. Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Part 2 has a caption title: Popery manifested, and the Papist incognito made known. With separate pagination and continuous register.</note>
                  <note>The first two words of the title transliterated from the Greek.</note>
                  <note>The words "Papist" to "divine" are connected by a left brace.</note>
                  <note>By Luke Beaulieu.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholics --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170992:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170992:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΠΛΑΝΗΣ ΑΠΟΚΑΛΥΨΙΣ.</p>
            <p>POPERY MANIFESTED, OR, THE Papiſt Incognito made known, By way of DIALOGUE Betwixt A
<list>
                  <item>Papiſt Prieſt,</item>
                  <item>Proteſtant Gentleman, and</item>
                  <item>Presbyterian Divine.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In Two Parts.</p>
            <p>Intended for the good of thoſe that ſhall read it</p>
            <p>By <hi>L. B. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the Gun at the Weſt End of <hi>S. Pauls.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170992:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170992:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Chriſtian, Courteous and Impartial READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Would fain oblige thee in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my Book, becauſe poſſibly the reſt will not pleaſe thee ſo well: Therefore inſtead of a Preface or a ſhort Advertiſement, wherewith uſually the Reader is put off, I give thee an Epiſtle Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory. This I hope will prove ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, in that it is a new device, and alſo becauſe thou mayſt have very cheap the Honour of having had a Book Dedicated to thee. But yet beſides I aſſure thee, that this Book of itſelf is worth thy reading;
<pb facs="tcp:170992:3"/>for it will make thee ſee in their natural ſhape and colours, many things which before appeared only under a diſguiſe: and if thou art a Lover of Truth (as all pretend to be) thou canſt not but rejoice to ſee it come out from under the Cloud, where before it lay hid. And withal, thou mayſt uſe it as an Antidote againſt the Infection of ſome ſugared Poiſons, which many venture to drink of, not knowing their deadly Qualities. Therefore I require thee, that thou wouldeſt not fling away the Book as ſoon as thou findeſt ſome things in it, againſt thy former perſuaſions or thy preſent liking: for often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wholeſom Phyſic is the moſt unpleaſant, and if thou readeſt through, and then repenteſt of thy labour, I give it here under my hand, that I alſo will repent of
<pb facs="tcp:170992:3"/>mine: but if the Book doth work upon thee the good effect I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, all the Requital I expect is this; that as thou art unknown to the Author, ſo thou wouldeſt not enquire after him, becauſe he is unwilling to be known any otherwiſe than by being</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Real Friend and Affectionate Well-wiſher, <hi>L. B. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:170992:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170992:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>MAny Learned Books have been written againſt the Errors of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral worthy Champions of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but uſually they read them moſt that have leaſt need of them, while in the mean time they that have but little of knowledge are left unarmed againſt the Crafts and Subtilties of the Propagators of the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith. I know there is an in-bred Averſion to Popery in the major part of our People, but Popery is now a word of a very dubious ſignification, and means rather what every one diſlikes, than what is ſo indeed: and it is to be ſeen in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of this Book, that they that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd moſt againſt what they pleaſed to call Popery; ran themſelves into the worſt of Popiſh Errors.</p>
            <p>However, 'tis not a brutiſh Hatred or a blind Zeal againſt unknown Errors can ſecure us from them: A man may eaſily embrace
<pb facs="tcp:170992:5"/>his mortal Enemy, if he knows him not, or if he meets him under a diſguiſe. Jeſuites are Traveſty among us, and ſo is their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; they put a ſtrange garb as well upon their Opinions, as upon their Perſons, and I am confident they win more Proſelytes by miſ-repreſenting the Popiſh Religion, than by proving it to be true.</p>
            <p>Therefore, that they might no longer be impoſed upon, that have not the leiſure or the capacity of knowing what the Papiſts do really believe, contrary to that ſound and orthodox Doctrine, which is profeſt in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> I have here ſet down their real Opinions, taken out of their moſt approved Doctors and the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> itſelf, having tranſcrib'd their very words, without any the leaſt alteration, and then Engliſht them as faithfully as their ſenſe did require: And afterwards I have added ſome of thoſe places of Scripture which I thought moſt expreſs againſt thoſe Errors which our Church hath rejected, as being contrary to Gods Word and the Faith of the Primitive Church.</p>
            <p>Now if any man likes thoſe Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as they are really in themſelves, and as they ſtand in oppoſition to the Word of God, let him embrace them,
<pb facs="tcp:170992:5"/>if it ſo pleaſe him: but let none flatter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or be made to believe by others, that the Popiſh Tenets I have mentioned are not ſo bad as I repreſent them, for I have uſed the very Words and Expreſſions of their own Authors, which certainly could not be made either better or worſe by being tranſcrib'd by me.</p>
            <p>Perhaps I ſhall be cenſur'd for having writ my Book Dialogue-wiſe, and not well manag'd the Intrigue; but if they that find fault with this, like the matter, let them not mind the form, if not, I had as lieve they ſhould diſlike both as but one onely. My deſign was not to make a Dramatic Piece, but to make my Actors ſpeak truth. This way of writing is eaſie to the meaneſt capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, and I am minded to imitate at leaſt in the method, that excellent Dialogue, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the F.D. However if I can profit thoſe that ſhall read me, I little care whether I pleaſe them or not.</p>
            <p>And now if it may be lawful for a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſt to moralize a little, give me leave to tell thee, Dear Reader, that what I have written is not to engage thee into Diſputes and Religious Quarrels: I had rather thou ſhouldeſt read <hi>The whole Duty of Man,</hi> and the excellent Diſcourſe which that pious
<pb facs="tcp:170992:6"/>Author hath written againſt Diſputes in his <hi>Decay of Chriſtian Piety,</hi> than this Book of mine. By diſcovering the foul ſtains of thoſe Religions that make ſhew of a fair and ſpecious outſide, my deſign is not to teach thee how to rail at them, or wrangle with their followers: But to make thee love and obey that holy Religion which is taught in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and which promiſeth rewards to her followers, not for hating thoſe that are of different Perſuaſions, but for obeying the Precepts of Chriſt. If thou art an ill liver, no matter what Religion thou art of, thy recompence ſhall be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy Works; if not, thy Creed and a Good Life will do thy ſoul more good than much Knowledge and Activity in what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Differences among Chriſtians in points of Religion. And if thou doſt ask me, why therefore I ſhould meddle with them and not be wholly employed in the performance of good Works? I anſwer ſomewhat like as <hi>Aphraates</hi> did <hi>Valens,</hi> when he came into <hi>Antioch</hi> to oppoſe himſelf to the then prevailing Error of <hi>Arius,</hi> and the Emperor askt him, why he had left his Religious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement to come into the City. <hi>Niceph. l. 11. c. 2.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When the flock of Chriſt is in
<pb facs="tcp:170992:6"/>danger of being ſeduced, it behoves me alſo to do my utmoſt endeavour for its Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And when my heavenly Fathers houſe is ſet on fire, I will by all means endeavour to quench it, and fling water upon it though it were but one drop.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:170992:7"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho. Tomkyns.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ex <hi>Aed. Lambethanis,</hi> 
                  <date>Decemb. 13. 1672.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <div n="1" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170992:7"/>
               <head>Popery Manifeſted, AND THE Papiſt Incognito made known: By way of DIALOGUE between a Papiſt Prieſt, a Proteſtant Gentleman, and a Presbyterian Divine.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Firſt Part.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, your humble ſervant, I come to wait you upon a double account, to give you thanks for the Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities I have heretofore received from you, and to ſpend in the beſt Company I can, that ſhort time I am allow'd to ſtay in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>I proteſt Maſter — it grieves me that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our inclination we ſhould be forc'd to be thus ſevere againſt you for to ſecure the peace of the kingdom: And were it not that your Religion ſtands in oppoſition to the good and peaceable intentions which I believe ſome of you may have, I do proteſt that I my ſelf would heartily intercede for your ſtaying and living quietly with us: However you are very welcome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I know you to be of a very ſweet nature, by a long experience, and I will requite
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170992:8"/>your kindneſs by praying heartily for your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to the true Catholic Faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Maſter — I thank you for your good will, but I believe if your Prayers be heard, I ſhall never be of your Religion, for if it hath the truth, yet therewith ye have mixt ſo many falſe Doctrins particular to your own Church, that it can never be juſtly call'd, The true Catholic Faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, you ſpeak as you have been taught, but did you well underſtand thoſe things as you call falſe Doctrines, I am ſure you would be of another mind.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, we are entred <hi>ab abrupto</hi> upon a Subject that will help us to paſs away the time, therefore I deſire you, my good Friend, for our old acquaintance ſake, to let me know poſitively the truth of what your Church believes in the chiefeſt things we differ from you, as it is taught and recorded by your moſt approved Doctors.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>I will with all my heart, as far as I am able, and that you may not think I diſguiſe any thing or ſpeak my private Opinions, I will bring the very words of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> or <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> or <hi>Stapleton,</hi> as the Authentic Proofs of the truth of what I ſhall ſay, ask you what you have a mind to know.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt, let me enquire of what you believe concerning the Holy Scripture; for we make it the Ground and the Rule of our Faith, being perſuaded that it conteins all things neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>We are much of another mind, for we hold, that <hi>the Scripture doth not expreſly contein
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170992:8"/>all that is neceſſary to be believed or to be done, i.e.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bellar. de <hi>Verbo Dei l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> that its Doctrine is defective in what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns Faith and Morality. <hi>Nos aſſerimus, in Scripturis non contineri expreſſe totam doctrinam neceſſariam, ſive de fide, ſive de moribus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>That's very plain and I believe more than you dare ſay to thoſe you endeavour to make your Proſelytes. —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay Sir, before we proceed I muſt tell you, that I expect you would render me like for like, and cite the words of <hi>Cranmer</hi> or <hi>Calvin,</hi> or whatever Authors they are you have your Doctrine from, that it may be ſeen which of us hath the better Authorities for our ſeveral Opinions; pray who taught you, that all things neceſſary to ſalvation are contein'd in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Bleſſed Saviour, who approved the Jews opinion of believing that by the Scriptures they might have eternal life, and therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to ſearch them. <hi>John</hi> 5.39. <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think ye have eternal life, and they are they which teſtifie of me.</hi> And more expreſly S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who affirms, that <hi>they are able to make us wiſe unto ſalvation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15, &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>being inſpir'd by God.</hi> Theſe two Texts are of more weight with me than the contrary af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmations of twenty Cardinals. And as for the Authors of our Religion, we own none beſides Chriſt and his bleſſed Apoſtles. Thoſe Doctrines of our Church which are poſitive are plainly contein'd in Scripture, and the beſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of the Primitive Church, and are own'd and believ'd by you alſo: and the negatives
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170992:9"/>which are againſt your Innovations, can neither be diſprov'd by Scripture nor the Antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but are generally included in the poſitive. All this is to be ſeen in the learned labours of many of the Reformed Doctors. I will not make our Diſcourſe ſo tedious, as to rehearſe what they have ſaid upon that ſubject, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I deſire you to be contented with a few plain Scriptures, which I will bring to autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize our denying thoſe Articles of your Roman Faith, we have rejected.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, do ſo if you will; but let me tell you, that Scripture is not to be the judge of Differences in Religion; <hi>'Tis the Pope and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil muſt decide all Controverſies and declare the true ſenſe of Scripture.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bellar. de <hi>Verbo Dei</hi> l. 3. c. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Judicem dicimus veri ſenſus Scripturae &amp; omnium Controverſiarum eſſe Eccleſiam,</hi> id eſt, <hi>Pontificem cum Concilio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>I don't believe it, for I find that God ſends his People <hi>to the Law and to the Teſtimony</hi> to examin the Doctrine of the Prophets;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.20.</note> and I hope the Goſpel may as well have the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, that by it we ſhould examin the Doctrin of the Pope. Chriſt tells the Saducees that they <hi>creed becauſe they knew not the Scriptures.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 12.24. Luke 16.29.</note> It is ſaid in the Parable of <hi>Dives, They have Moſes and the Prophets, let them hear them.</hi> And it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded to the praiſe of the people of <hi>Berea,</hi> that <hi>they ſearched the Scriptures daily to ſee whether thoſe things were ſo.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 17.11.</note> In all theſe the Scripture is made Judge of Controverſies, and by it the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf is tried and examined.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>But for all that, <hi>the Scripture is very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and harder to be underſtood than the Notions
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170992:9"/>of Metaphyſic.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bellar. de <hi>Verbo Dei</hi> l. 3. c. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Certe ſi ſcientia Metaphyſicorum dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficilior, —quomodo non obſcuriſſima erit Scriptura quae de rebus longe altioribus agit. And if the People ſhould read it, it would do them more harm than good, for 'twould be an occaſion of their falling into error about thoſe Doctrines that concern Faith and a good Life.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Et ibid. l. 2. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>5.</note> 
                     <hi>Populum non ſolum non eaperet fructum ex Scripturis, ſed etiam caperet detrimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, acciperet enim facillime occaſionem errandi, tum in doctrina fidei, tum in praeceptis vitae &amp; morum.</hi> Therefore all men ought to follow the Deciſions of Popes and Councils, that they may be guided in the truth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I would have the people follow the judgment of the Church they live in, but I would have them to make uſe of their Rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to chuſe the Communion of the pureſt Church, according to the Word of God (and if they have learning enough) according to the four firſt General Councils and the Primitive Chriſtians; and not deny their Reaſon, and the plain meaning of Scripture and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves blind, that they may be led by thoſe that pretend to Infallibility and a ſupreme Authority in things of Faith. As for the Deciſions of your Popes and Councils, it hath been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by learned men of ours, that they are alſo ſubject to miſ-interpretation, and that they have not been able ſo much as to compoſe any one of thoſe Differences that have been and are ſtill amongſt you. And indeed, why ſhould not God ſpeak as plain as the Pope in what is abſolutely neceſſary to be known? Is it becauſe he is not able, or becauſe he is not willing we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170992:10"/>ſhould know the truth? But, Friend, whilſt you tax the Scripture with obſcurity and make the people think 'tis a dangerous Book, ſee whether you do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot give the lie to God himſelf, who ſaith,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 19 7, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aw of the Lord is perfect, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the ſoul: the Teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, making wiſe the ſimple,</hi> (according to <hi>Rome</hi> it ſhould have been, making the ſimple to err) <hi>The Statutes of the Lord are right, rejoycing the heart, the commandment of the Lord is pure, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning the eye,</hi> (not blinding or darkning the eye.)
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119 105.</note> In another place, <hi>Thy word is a lamp unto my feet, and a light unto my path.</hi> Could any thing be more expreſs againſt the charge of obſcurity?
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.3, 4.</note> And ſo, S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>If our Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that periſh, in whom the God of this world hath blinded the minds, — leſt the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the image of God ſhould ſhine unto them.</hi> It ſeems the Goſpel hath a light that ſhines unto men, and the devil endeavours to blind them that they may not ſee it: and whether the Pope be not an uſeful inſtrument to that effect, let them judge that are not yet quite blind. Sure if there was ſo great a danger in reading the Scriptures, God would not have commanded his people ſo abſolutely to ſtudy his Law; Chriſt would not have preached to the multitudes (for his words might be miſinterpreted as well ſpoken as writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) and the Apoſtles ſhould not have directed their Epiſtles to all the people of <hi>Corinth, Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, &amp;c.</hi> We ſhould rather have been forbidden ſearching the Scriptures, and ſent to <hi>his Holineſs</hi> to know what we muſt believe and do.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170992:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, you are tedious in your Reaſons and Proofs, and whereas I cite only one of our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Doctors at a time, and that in few words: you bring me I don't know how many places of Scripture. I had rather you would tell me what <hi>Luther</hi> or the Church of <hi>Geneva</hi> have reſolv'd in theſe Controverſies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>'Twould be to no purpoſe, for we regard not their opinions, nor thoſe of any private men, but as far as they agree with the truth: Our Church is founded upon that Catholic and unchangeable truth which God hath revealed in the <hi>Sacred Books,</hi> and which hath been and is ſtill entertain'd, by all thoſe that own the Fundamentals of Chriſtianity. Therefore as I have told you, 'twill be the ſhorteſt way for me to back thoſe Doctrins of our Church which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any of yours by the authority of Gods Revelations, his moſt Holy Word, which is a ſufficient foundation for us to ground our faith upon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>As far as I can ſee, you are run a great way off from us, for we (as many as own the Pope to be the Head and Monarch of the Church) never mind what the Scripture ſaith, we follow blind-fold the Judgment of our Church, as a moſt infallible guide.
<note place="margin">Bellar. de <hi>Rom. Pont.</hi> l. 4. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>We believe that neither the Pope, nor the particular Church of</hi> Rome <hi>can err in things of Faith. Non ſolum Pontifex Romanus non poteſt errare in fide, ſed ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Romana particularis Eccleſia.</hi> No Sir, take it from <hi>Bellarmin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bellar. de <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. c. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>It is abſolutely impoſſible that the Church ſhould err in any thing, whether it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsary or not. Noſtra eſt ſententia, Eccleſiam ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170992:11"/>non poſſe errare nec in rebus abſolute neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis, nec in aliis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>And you, Sir, take it from experience, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> could and hath greatly erred in many things (if it be an error to make huge additions to the antient Creeds, and to go directly againſt the Word of God) And though it be impoſſible that ever the Univerſal Church ſhould forſake and deny the ſaving truths of Chriſtian Religion, becauſe of the Promiſe of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.18. Yet any one particular Church or Society of Chriſtians, though never ſo great, may err, and that in Fundamentals, as we know of ſome Pſeudo-Councils that have broach'd or confirm'd damnable Hereſies. And accordingly the Scripture ſaith,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Let God be true and every man a liar:</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is not excepted: And doubtleſs if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was infallible, and the only guide that can lead us to heaven: God who hath revealed to us the way to happineſs, would not have omitted ſo eſſential a thing. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a command wholly to rely on the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Pope ſpeaking <hi>ex Cathedra,</hi> we are commanded to <hi>prove all things,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 1 Joh. 4.1.</note> 
                     <hi>and to hold faſt that which is good;</hi> and again <hi>to try the ſpirits whether they be of God; becauſe many falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are come out into the world.</hi> Now, how ſhall we try them, but by the Word of God? and if we find you do not follow it, why ſhould we any longer follow you? Find me as many Texts out of Gods Word, to prove that your great Biſhop is infallible, and that we are all bound to believe every thing he ſaith, as I have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170992:11"/>produc'd already for the Divine Authority of Scripture, and its ſufficiency to bring us unto Salvation, and then we'll weigh them together, and my faith ſhall follow the heavier Scale: But when we prove and demonſtrate that you err and go directly againſt Scripture, for you to come and ſay that it is impoſſible becauſe you are infallible and free from all error, is to my thinking a very odd and unſatisfactory anſwer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, if you talk of Scripture till to morrow, I am ſure ours is the Antient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Church without the which there is no ſalvation: But your Religion is a new up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart, you cannot ſhew me where it was and the Profeſſors of it two hundred years ago.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>As for the Profeſſors, where they were, and that there were many even in the highth of Popery is a long Hiſtorical labour, but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy done to my hand by ſeveral learned men; the Author of <hi>Catalogus teſtium Verit. Abbot, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher, Fox, White, &amp;c.</hi> They were in the Eaſtern and Greec Churches much larger than that of <hi>Rome,</hi> they were amongſt you, ſome declar'd and marty'd for it, ſome for peace ſake living in the Communion of your Church, and ſome conceled for fear of your cruelty, ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſecret for Liberty and Reformation. But you may ſatisfie your ſelf fully in their Books.</p>
                  <p>As for our Religion, It was where it had been above a thouſand years, in the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. And ſuppoſe (what is utterly falſe) that ſoon after its being written all Chriſtian Churches had been ſo corrupted, as to own fifteen hundred years together thoſe Errors
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170992:12"/>which now are amongſt you; yet ſtill the Scripture had been the ſame, as much to be obeyed and followed, as if it had always been ſo.
<note place="margin">2 King. 22.</note> When <hi>Joſiah</hi> had found the Book of the Law, he did not fling it by, becauſe it had been hid and neglected, during the reign of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> and <hi>Amon</hi> his Fathers, but he cauſed it to be read before all the people,
<note place="margin">Ibid. 23.</note> that they might obſerve what was conteined in it. So now we have the Holy Scriptures read and preached to us, we muſt not reject them, to follow the Cuſtoms of ſome of our Fore-Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in whoſe time they were hid and diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, for they are as much the Rule of Faith, as if they had never been diſown'd. But I ſay farther, that our Religion was in thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the Eaſt and South which never own'd Popery; and even amongſt you, our Religion was profeſſed; you believed all along thoſe three Creeds which you and we do ſtill retein, which contein the Articles of our Faith, but not the new additions which are particular to <hi>Rome:</hi> The Popes univerſal Supremacy and his Infallibility, Tranſubſtantiation, Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Images, Purgatory, Indulgences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe are neither in Scripture, nor in the firſt Councils, nor in the Writings of the Antient Fathers, not ſo much as in your Creeds (an evident mark of their novelty) but in the late Councils and Conſtitutions of the Popes.</p>
                  <p>We confeſs indeed that there is an univerſal Church out of which there is no ſalvation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that known ſaying of S. <hi>Cyprian. Deum non poteſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He can be none of Gods
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170992:12"/>children, who is not a ſon of the Church:</hi> But that Church is the Chriſtian not the Roman Church; and to know which is the Chriſtian Church, or which is the pureſt of Chriſtian Churches, (for they are all Chriſtian in ſome meaſure that own Chriſt) we muſt not conſult humane Hiſtories; for they cannot inform us of that, and if they could we muſt not build our faith upon mens report.
<note place="margin">De <hi>Sac a.</hi> l. 2. c. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſaith of humane Hiſtories, <hi>Faciunt tantum humanam fidem cui falſam ſubeſſe poteſt,</hi> that <hi>they only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a human ſaith which may be erroneous.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Controverſie betwixt us, which is the pureſt Church, we muſt not ſearch old Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords and Chronicles, to ſee which was the oldeſt, the moſt viſible or the moſt large and flouriſhing Church (that is not the Queſtion, and if it were, ſtill human Hiſtories cannot be the ground of a Chriſtian Faith) but we muſt examin, which agrees beſt with Holy Scripture (which we all acknowledge to be the Word of God) for no doubt the true Church wherein Salvation may be had, is that which holds that Doctrin which God himſelf hath reveled to Mankind, whatever her condition may have been in times paſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>There may be ſomething conſiderable in what you ſay, but you Hereties have ſtrange cunnings and ſubtilties to juſtifie your Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and yet ſtill for all you have ſaid, you are no better than Rebels againſt your ſpiritual So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, you are Schiſmatics, undutiful Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that have forſaken your Mother the Church. <hi>The true and only Church wherein Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170992:13"/>is to be obtein'd, guided and governed by the Vicar of Chriſt upon earth, our holy Father the Pope. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na eſt tantum Eccleſia — ſub regimine unius Chriſti in terris Vicarii Romani Pontific is.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bellar. de <hi>Eccl.</hi> l 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> But pray do not make ſuch a tedious Diſcourſe as you have juſt now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Good Sir, ſometimes ſhort Queſtions can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be anſwered in few words, I could propoſe one to you much like that as you put to me, which I believe would take a great deal of your time to anſwer, that is, Where your particular Religion, your ſacrificing of the real and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral body and bloud of Chriſt for the ſins of the living and the dead, your Worſhipping Images and Saints, and making them your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſors, your Purgatory, Indulgences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where was all that in the time of Chriſt and his Apoſtles? Whereabout can it be found in Scripture or in the antient Creeds or in the four firſt General Councils or in the three or four firſt Centuries? But I will not put you to ſo long and impoſſible a Task.</p>
                  <p>As for our forſaking the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> we were abſolutely bound, and in a manner forc'd to do it, becauſe of the many errors which had crept and been brought into it by the Ignorance, Pride, Avarice and Ambition of the late Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> and their Partizans; and which were confirm'd by your Church, and defended with that violence, that it was death to any man to ſpeak in the leaſt againſt them: Now you know 'tis a Rule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on of all ſides, that he is not guilty of Schiſm that ſeparates, but he that gives a juſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170992:13"/>cauſe of Separation, wherfore I retort the charge upon you, of being Schiſmatics, except you can prove by the Word of God, thoſe Doctrins of yours we have rejected to be Divine and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, for we have left your Church upon this account, that you had perverted the truth of God, and added many falſe opinions to it, which ye impos'd upon the people as if they had been Articles of Faith. And we find it in Scripture;
<note place="margin">Ro. 16.17</note> 
                     <hi>Mark them which cauſe diviſions and offences contrary to the Doctrin which ye have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and avoid them:</hi> 'tis not ſaid, except it be the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And in another place;
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Though we or an angel from heaven preach unto you beyond or over and above</hi> (in the Grecc <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the vulgar <hi>praeterquam quod) what we have prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, let him be accurſed:</hi> the Pope himſelf you ſee is not excepted. Again, we have left the Communion of your Church becauſe it was Schiſmatic itſelf, in that it had forſaken the Doctrin taught and believed in the Primitive Church: We have come out of <hi>Rome,</hi> to return into the more antient and univerſal Church: We have left the Pope to follow Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and we have forſaken you no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than you had forſaken the truth. The antient Creeds, the firſt Councils, many good and Fundamental Doctrins we hold together, in theſe we hold Communion with you: We reject your Communion only in thoſe new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins which ye have ſuperadded to the antient and divine Faith of Chriſtians. And ſo likewiſe we rebel not againſt the Pope, only we ſet God above him: I'll ſtill acknowledge him to be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170992:14"/>a Biſhop and the Patriarch of the Weſt, and perhaps I had been civil enough never to have diſputed his Infallibility and ſpiritual Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty (though I find nothing for it in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture) had I not found, that he hath really er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that very groſly, whence I infer, that therefore his Infallibility and ſupreme Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are Chimeras, mere devices of his own brain, the which I am in no wiſe bound to obey, being they pervert and oppoſe the plaineſt truths in the New Teſtament: As that Chriſt is now in heaven by his bodily preſence, and not on the Altars; as it is in the Creed, <hi>he is aſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heaven, from whence he ſhall come to judge the quick and the dead,</hi> and in Acts 3.20. <hi>Whom the heavens muſt contain until the reſtitution of all things.</hi> That we are forgiven and cleanſed by the death and merits of Chriſt, not by Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and Indulgences, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. <hi>And the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſins,</hi> ibid. 2.2. <hi>He is the propitiation for our ſins, and not for ours only, but alſo for the ſins of the whole world.</hi> That the offering of himſelf on the Croſs hath fully ſatisfied for ſin, and that his ſacrifice needs not be renewed daily and be offered corporally in the Maſs for the ſins of the living and the dead, as you teach and do, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26. <hi>But now once in the end of the world, he hath appeared to put away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. In thoſe things that are evidently againſt the Word of God we are reſolv'd to follow Scripture rather than the head of your Church, and we'll rather for ever break with him, than to ſuffer him to put out our eyes, that ſo he may guide us at his own pleaſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170992:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, thoſe be the fruits of tranſlating the Bible and performing Divine Service in the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Tongues; every one of you can find fault with the Doctrins and Conſtitutions of the Church, and talk Scripture from morning to night; we ſee among your ſelves what Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders it hath cauſed. If your Clergy had been wiſe enough to have ſtill retein'd the Latin Tongue in all their Miniſtrations, the people could have diſlik'd and cenſur'd nothing, 'twas ſufficient for them to have light enough to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their guides, more ſubmiſſion and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with leſs knowledge had done better.
<note place="margin">Bellar de <hi>Verbo Dei</hi> l. 2. c. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>That hath been the wiſdom of our Church to keep the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and the publick prayers of our Church out of the peoples reach by forbidding them to be read in any vulgar tongue. Catholica Eccleſia prohibet ne in publico &amp; communi uſu Eccleſiae Scripturae legantur vel canentur vulgaribus linguis, ut in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio Tridentino SS.</hi> 22. <hi>Can.</hi> 9. <hi>Sed contenti ſumus tribus illis linguis quas Dominus titulo crucis ſuae honoravit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe ſome men ſtumble and fall at noon-day, muſt the Sun be charged with a fault that proceeds from their heedleſneſs; and would it become one, to ſay, that therefore 'tis ſafer to grope in the dark, becauſe then people tread more warily? Or muſt therefore mens eyes be put out, becauſe then they ſhall be willing to be led and to follow their guides. S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>unſtable and unlearned</hi> in his time <hi>wreſted ſome difficult things written by Saint</hi> Paul, <hi>and other Scriptures to their own deſtruction.</hi> Yet he doth not ſay, therefore let not the common
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170992:15"/>people read them, but rather dedicates his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to all thoſe that were partakers of the Chriſtian Faith, and exhorts them <hi>to grow in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ibid. v. 18. S. <hi>Paul</hi> reckons Idolatry, Hereſies and Schiſms among the fruits of the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20. but doth not any where impute them to the reading of Holy Scripture: and it hath been obſerv'd that the perverſneſs of men of great Learning hath been the cauſe of Hereſies, and not the miſtakes or ignorance of ordinary peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in reading the Bible. However we have a whole Chapter in the New Teſtament againſt the ſpeaking in an unknown tongue as you do in all your Churches:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.11.</note> 
                     <hi>If I know not the meaning of the voice, I ſhall be unto him that ſpeaketh a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barian, and he that ſpeaketh ſhall be a Barbarian unto me:</hi> that's the relation betwixt your Prieſts and your people, they are Barbarians one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, the whole Chapter is to that purpoſe, and would be too long to be tranſcrib'd. But if Scripture had been ſilent in this, one would think that common Reaſon would have kept men from a practice ſo abſurd and ridiculous, that a man ſhould preſent a petition and know not what he asks; and be taught his duty by words he doth not underſtand, is a ſtrange and incredible thing, which Reaſon alone confutes moſt ſtrongly. And yet for all this, I do huge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commend the wiſdom of your Church in this particular, for that hath maintain'd the Popes Religion and Credit for ſome hundreds of years; the underſtanding of Maſs and Scripture hath already prov'd fatal to his authority, and ſhould
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170992:15"/>once the reſt of his flock be able to compare both together, 'tis to be fear'd he that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded many of his friends with the gift of ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tular Biſhopricks, might come to be himſelf a titular Biſhop.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſee you value an univerſal Council as little as you do <hi>Bellarmin</hi> alone, and have as many things to object againſt it; I wonder how you dare in any wiſe oppoſe the authority of ſuch an Aſſembly, and think your Judgment is to be prefer'd to theirs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>And I wonder how you can call the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> univerſal, when there was none in it of the Clergy of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which are almoſt as large and populous here in the Weſt, as thoſe of the Roman Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: But eſpecially, becauſe none of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> nor of thoſe that are ſubject to the Patriarchs of <hi>Antioch</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (whoſe Juriſdiction is of a far larger extent than that of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi>) were preſent at it. Pray did you never hear, that a great Company of <hi>Arrians</hi> met once together and confirmed their Errors and curſed all thoſe that would not embrace it, and call'd themſelves an Univerſal Council: juſt ſo did that Company of Papiſts that met at <hi>Trent.</hi> But had they been twice as many more, you ſhould not wonder how I dare oppoſe them, but rather conſider whether what I ſay be rational or no, and whether what you call my private judgment be not rather the expreſs words of Scripture. But pray proceed and tell me what your Church thinks of Images and Saints, for we are told that you worſhip them.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170992:16"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes,
<note place="margin">Bellar. de <hi>San. beat.</hi> l. 1. c. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>and that very devoutly and to our great advantage by making religious Invocations to them whether they be men or angels. Sancti ſive angeli ſive homines, pie at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> utiliter invocantur.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I wonder too, how you dare do that, for I find that when <hi>Cornelius</hi> would have wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped S. <hi>Peter,</hi> the holy Apoſtle took him up, ſaying,
<note place="margin">Acts 10.26. Rev. 19.10.</note> that he himſelf was a man alſo. And that when S. <hi>John</hi> fell at the Angels feet to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, the Angel hindred him, ſaying, <hi>See thou do it not, I am thy fellow-ſervant, worſhip God.</hi> Who told you 'tis more lawful now? Or that they are not ſtill of the ſame mind (for belike the Worſhip of <hi>Latreia</hi> was not offer'd them) and how can you call on the Saints for help, being you have not yet put them in your Creed? for S.
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>How ſhall they call on him in whom they have not believed?</hi> And more than ſo, he gives us warning againſt the plauſibility of the Doctrin of worſhipping Angels.
<note place="margin">Col. 2.18</note> 
                     <hi>Let no man beguile you of your reward in a voluntary humility and worſhipping of Angels, intruding into thoſe things which he hath not ſeen, vainly puft up by his fleſhly mind.</hi> I take the practice of our Church in worſhipping God alone to be much ſafer, for we are bid by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſo to do.
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> It is ſaid in the Acts,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.21.</note> 
                     <hi>Whoſoever ſhall call on the name of the Lord ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Could you produce as much for the Worſhipping of Saints, we would do it as devoutly as you. But rather to the contrary, we find that when the Apoſtles deſired Chriſt to teach them to pray, not only to pray God,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170992:16"/>but in general to pray: he told them,
<note place="margin">Luc. 11.1.</note> 
                     <hi>When ye pray, ſay, Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. there was not a ſyllable for the Saints. And S. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he had ſaid, <hi>That Chriſt is our High-Prieſt in heaven,
<note place="margin">Heb. 4.16</note> infers, let us therefore come boldly unto the throne of grace, that we may obtein mercy.</hi> He doth not ſay, Let us go to the Saints, that they may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein mercy for us. Nothing is to be found in Scripture but what diſcountenanceth the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of your Church in Praying to Saints: Pray, what reaſons have you for it beſides the command of the Pope.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>There may be many, but I can tell you of two very ſtrong ones: Firſt, <hi>Becauſe they know our neceſſities and the very thoughts of our hearts, and ſo can hear our prayers at all times. Bellarmin</hi> is expreſs in it:
<note place="margin">Bellar. de <hi>San. beat.</hi> l. 1. c. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>Non verum eſt quod aſſumitur Sanctos ignorare quod ab illis petimus; nam etſi dubitatio eſſe poſſit, quemadmodum cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeant, &amp; quae ſolo cordis affectu interdum proferun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, tamen certum eſt eos cognoſcere.</hi> And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                     <hi>Becauſe they are our Mediators and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede with God for us. Ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> eſt cur timeamus nomen mediatoris transferre ad Sanctos, ſicut ad eos tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferimus nomen advocati &amp; interceſſoris.</hi> And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly it was decreed by the Council of <hi>Trent, Mandat ſancta Synodus omnibus Epiſcopis, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Con <hi>Trid.</hi> S. 25. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. de <hi>Inv. Sanct.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>omnes fideles inſtruant de Sanctorum interceſſione, invocatione, reliquiarum honore &amp; legitimo imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num uſu. — Doceant eos bonum at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> utile eſſe eos invocare, ad eorum orationes, opem auxiliumque confugere.— Imagines Chriſti &amp; Sanctorum in templis habendas eiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> debitum honorem &amp; venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem impertiendam. — Quod, per imagines
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170992:17"/>quas oſculamur, &amp; coram quibus caput aperimus, Chriſtum &amp; Sanctos adoremus &amp; veneremur. The people muſt be taught by the Clergy, to pray to Saints, to flee to them for ſuccour and help, and alſo for their interceſſion, to honour their ſhrines and reliques, to have their images in Churches, and give them their due honour and worſhip by kiſſing of them, and by kneeling and being bare to them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I know you do ſo, and burn Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, and go on Pilgrimages to them, and offer gifts to them, and a great deal more than I can think of. But the more ſhame for you, for were your reaſons true, yet they could not juſtifie ſuch doings, but rather what we all grant and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, that the Saints ſhould be mentioned with honour, that the memory of them ſhould be pretious to us, and that we would imitate their virtues, and thank God for all the bleſſings we receive from them. And yet 'tis very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that they ſhould know the thoughts of all men at once, for 'tis a thing that belongs to God only,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.6, &amp; 7.</note> and ſeems to contradict theſe Scriptures: <hi>That the dead know not any thing of what is done under the Sun:</hi> That <hi>God only knows the heart of all the children of men:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Kings 8.39. Rev. 2.23</note> And that <hi>it is he that ſearcheth the reins and the hearts.</hi> And as for your ſecond reaſon, we deny not but that the Saints glorified may pray for the Militant Church; only we ſay that to make them our Mediators and Interceſſors, and to pray by their merits is expreſly againſt theſe Scriptures:
<note place="margin">1 Tim 2.5. 1 John 2.1, 2. Joh. 14.6.</note> 
                     <hi>There is one Mediator between God and men, the man Jeſus Chriſt. I am the way, the truth and the life, no man cometh unto the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170992:17"/>father but by me</hi> (not by the Saints) <hi>If ye ask any thing in my name, that will I do.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. 13, &amp; 14.</note> 
                     <hi>If ye ask any thing in my name, I will do it,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 2.18.</note> (not if ye ask in the name of the Saints.) <hi>Through him we have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs by one ſpirit unto the father:</hi> and laſtly, to conclude and ſhew that the Practice of our Church is well grounded and ſafe. It is ſaid <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>He</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>is able to ſave to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt thoſe that come unto God by him, ſeeing he ever liveth to make interceſſion for them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for your repreſenting God in bodily ſhapes and worſhipping the Images of Saints, 'tis well the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> is ſo expreſs for it,
<note place="margin">Deut. 5.8.</note> for I am ſure the Holy Scripture doth not in the leaſt authorize but rather condemn it. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven image nor the likeneſs of any thing that is in heaven above,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Ib. 4.15.</note> and in another place, <hi>Take ye good heed unto your ſelves for you ſaw no manner of ſimilitude when the Lord ſpake to you in Horeb, — leſt ye corrupt your ſelves and make you a graven image, the ſimilitude of any figure,</hi> &amp;c. And that Images ſhould not be worſhipped in any wiſe,
<note place="margin">Ex. 20.5.</note> what can be more expreſs than the ſecond Commandment? <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow down thy ſelf to them nor ſerve them.</hi> And now who will wonder that you believe Doctrins not contein'd in Scripture, when ye teach and command what is ſo directly againſt it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>You fanſie that we tranſgreſs the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,
<note place="margin">Bellar. de <hi>Juſt.</hi> l. 4. c. 13. De <hi>Monas.</hi> l. 2. c. 7.</note> but we ſay that we can fulfil them all, and that ſome do ſo, and more than is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded too, <hi>There are thoſe amongſt us who are ſo far from committing any ſin, that they can do more than is required of them by God. Poteſt homo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170992:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>facere plus quam Deus praecipit, multo magis poteſt implere praeceptum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Very good, ſo ſay the worſt of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natics, that they are perfect and without ſin: yet I confeſs, you do not fanſie your people to fanſie ſo, that privilege is granted only to ſome choice ones and that long after they are dead, and therein you act with much diſcretion,
<note place="margin">Contr. 3. Quaeſt. 11.</note> as <hi>Stapleton</hi> ſaith, <hi>Summa cum ratione introductum fuit ut Canonizatio per ſolum ſummum Pontificem fiat.</hi> For ſome muſt be more than juſt that the Pope may have works of Supererogation to hoord up, and the people muſt be kept from that Perfection that he may have Chap-men to buy thoſe ſacred Wares. But God's <hi>Amanu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſes,</hi> who had none of them to ſell, teach quite otherwiſe,
<note place="margin">1 Kings 8.46. Pſ. 130.3. Eccl. 7.20.</note> that <hi>There is no man that ſinneth not:</hi> that <hi>If God ſhould mark iniquities, not any man could ſtand:</hi> that <hi>There is not a juſt man upon earth that doth good and ſinneth not.</hi> In all theſe there is not ſo much as one Frier excepted. So the deareſt Apoſtle of our Bleſſed Saviour tells us, <hi>If we ſay that we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.8.</note> 
                     <hi>and the truth is not in us.</hi> God requires the utmoſt of our love, whatever we do out of love is due, and ſure what we do upon other Motives is not meritorious (in that ſenſe as you take it) <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matt. 22.37.</note> 
                     <hi>with all thy ſoul, and with all thy mind.</hi> And our Bleſſed Lord and Redeemer hath taught all Chriſtians even the moſt perfect, to ſay in their daily Offices,
<note place="margin">Luk. 11.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Forgive us our ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>You know how the Fox that had no tail would perſuade others to cut off theirs: I am
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170992:18"/>ſure we are told,
<note place="margin">Beyrling prompt. mor <hi>p.</hi> 37</note> that you live moſt unchriſtian lives, and that ye have an irreconcileable quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel againſt all Good Works: Therefore ye would fain perſuade us that no body can attain to Perfection here, and that Good Works are not meritorious. But for all you can ſay, <hi>We will believe that they are, and that not only of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral bleſſings, but of life eternal it ſelf and of the higheſt degree of glory, by their own dignity.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bellar. de <hi>Juſtif.</hi> l. 5. c. 1. Ibid. c 20.</note> 
                     <hi>Probavimus bona opera juſtorum vere &amp; proprie eſſe merita, &amp; merita non cujuſcunq, praemii ſed ipſius vitae aeternae. Nos exiſtimamus vitam aeternam, tum quoad primum gradum tum quoad caeteros, reddi bonis meritis filiorum Dei.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>We little regard thoſe foul aſperſions you caſt upon us, the firſt and beſt Chriſtians were made as vile by the Heathen as poſſibly you can make us; neither have we any quarrel againſt good Works. We make them abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſalvation, and we teach according to Scripture, that God will reward them with eternal life; but to ſay that they do really and properly merit it <hi>ex condigno, without reſpect to Chriſt and the Promiſe:</hi> We dare not be ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, eſpecially becauſe of theſe Scriptures, <hi>The wages of ſin is death,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.23.</note> 
                     <hi>and the gift of God is eternal life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> It ſhould have been according to your Doctrin, And the wages of works is eternal life.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 143.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Enter not into judgment with thy ſervant for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be juſtified:</hi> How much leſs rewarded with the higheſt degree of eternal glory.
<note place="margin">Lu 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.</note> 
                     <hi>When ye have done all thoſe things that are commanded you, ſay, we are unprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170992:19"/>We have done what was our duty to do.</hi> But I forget that you can do more than all that is commanded you, and belike 'tis that overplus that makes the Merits of Condignity. S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.19, 20. 1 Cor 4 7. Ro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.18.</note> 
                     <hi>That we are not our own, becauſe we have been bought with a price.</hi> And in another place, <hi>What haſt thou that thou didſt not receive?</hi> And laſtly that <hi>the ſufferings of this preſent time are not worthy to be compared with the glory that ſhall he revealed in us.</hi> Let any man weigh theſe Scriptures, and ſee whether they favour more your abſolute Merits, than our Doctrin of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying our own righteouſneſs for to rely on Gods merciful Promiſes in Chriſt for a reward to our ſyncere though imperfect Services and good Works.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, if we had no Merits of our own, yet we are not left deſtitute. Oh, the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe that live in the lap of the Church! that good Mother will let them want for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; if a child of hers is not furniſht with meritoriouſneſs, but hath rather many ſins to anſwer for, as it is the caſe of a great many, yet he ſhall not be left without help. She will make over to him the ſatisfactions of others, who have ſuffered more than their ſins requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
<note place="margin">Bellar. de <hi>Indulg.</hi> l. 1. c. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>In bonis actibus hominum juſtorum duplex valor five pretium aſſignari poteſt; meriti videlicet &amp; ſatisfactionis; — Opus bonum qua parte meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torium eſt non poteſt alii applicari, poteſt tamen qua ſatisfactorium; — Extat in Eccleſia theſaurus ſatisfactionum Chriſti ſuperfluentium ad quem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent etiam paſſiones Beatae Mariae Virginis &amp; omnium aliorum Sanctorum qui plus paſſi ſunt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170992:19"/>quam eorum peccata requirerent. Satisfactiones Chriſto &amp; Sanciis ſupervacaneae applicari poſſunt aliis qui rei ſunt luendae paenae temporalis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> —<hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae paſtoribus auctoritas divinitus conceſſa eſt the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurum ſatisfactionum diſpenſandi, ac per hanc indulgentias concedendi; — Praelati Eccleſiae diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſare poſſunt Chriſti paſſionem tum per Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta tum per Indulgentias, paſſiones vero Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nonniſi per Indulgentias.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray give me leave to Engliſh it, to my thinking the Doctrin is pleaſant; you ſhall ſee how well I reliſh it: that is to ſay, <hi>That the good Works of juſt men have a twofold value, one ſide of them is meritorious and the other ſatisfactory, this laſt may be given to others, but the firſt may not: and that in the Church there is a treaſure of the ſuperfluous ſatisfactions of Chriſt, of the Bleſſed Virgin, and all other Saints, who ſuffered more than in juſtice they ought: Which treaſure is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of by the Paſtors of the Church according to that authority as God hath given them to thoſe who are guilty of temporal pains,</hi> and that with a great deal of Art and Induſtry, <hi>for the Paſſion of Chriſt is given by the Sacraments and Indulgences, but the Paſſions of the Saints by Indulgences only.</hi> I proteſt you are witty folks to deviſe ſuch pretty things as theſe; no wonder if you will not be tied to the written Word, when you are ſo good at inventing. Honeſt <hi>Novator,</hi> were I minded only to point out all the Impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces included in this Doctrin, it would confute itſelf or at leaſt appear moſt ridiculous. I would fain know who told <hi>Bellarmin, Poena aeterna com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutatur in temporalem quando remittitur culpa.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170992:20"/>That when the guilt is forgiven, the eternal pain is changed into a temporal.</hi> I know this was neceſſary to build upon, the Doctrin of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences and Purgatory, but the Scripture that hath no ſuch Doctrins makes no ſuch diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions at all,
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.10.</note> but ſaith in general, <hi>Curſed is every one that continueth not in all things that are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Book of the Law to do them:</hi> No com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation of the eternal into a temporal pain, he that tranſgreſſeth deſerves the curſe of the law.
<note place="margin">Ibid. v 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> But <hi>Chriſt hath redeemed us from that curſe.</hi> Wherefore there remains no more ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory pains to the penitent ſinner. God may indeed viſit him ſtill with Chaſtiſements and temporal Judgments, but who told you that it muſt be to make him ſatisfie for his ſins, and if it were, who gave the Pope power to ſell the ſinner an Indulgence, and ſo take off that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment as he pretends to do? S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that <hi>the wages of ſin is death;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ro. 6.23.</note> but he ſaith in another place, that Chriſt died for us, and that by that means,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.8.</note> 
                     <hi>there remains no more wrath to thoſe that are in Chriſt.</hi> But admit there had been part of the puniſhment due to ſin to be ſuffered here and part hereafter, and that ſo, a twofold ſatisfaction had been required; yet to ſay, that Chriſt could not ſatisfie for the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral pain, would be impious, to ſay that he would not, is to ſpeak without book or rather againſt it;
<note place="margin">Joh. 1.29.</note> for S. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Behold the Lamb of God that taketh away the ſins of the world:</hi> He doth not ſay, that he leaves part of them to be taken away by the ſatisfactions of Saints. S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.6.</note> 
                     <hi>that he gave himſelf a ranſom for all;</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170992:20"/>S. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.24 Rom. 8.1.</note> that <hi>his own ſelf bare our ſins in his own body on the tree;</hi> and laſtly <hi>that there is no condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to thoſe that are in Chriſt.</hi> In all theſe the ſatisfaction of Chriſt is general, and there is not one place in Scripture that reſtrains it to one part of the puniſhment. But to do you right you do not abſolutely deny, that Chriſt hath alſo yielded a ſatisfaction for the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral pain, only you will not have him to give it <hi>gratis,</hi> the Pope muſt ſell it; and you will not have it to be ſufficient of itſelf, but your own and the Saints muſt be added to it. Whereas it is written,
<note place="margin">Act. 4.12.</note> 
                     <hi>That there is no ſalvation in any other,</hi> and <hi>that he bore our griefs and carried our ſorrows,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 53.4, &amp; 5.</note> 
                     <hi>that he was wounded for our tranſgreſſions and bruiſed for our iniquities, and that God laid on him the iniquity of us all.</hi> Nothing like that is ſaid of any man, but of them all it is written,
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.5.</note> That <hi>every one ſhall bear his own burthen,</hi> and that <hi>we ſhall appear before the judgment-ſeat of Chriſt, that every one may receive according to what he hath done,</hi> not according to what S. <hi>Francis</hi> hath ſuffered for him. But pray tell us ſome more of the care of your Church for her neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Children.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, if by their careleſneſs or poverty they have not bought as many Pardons and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences as would ſatisfie for the remaining temporal pains, which the merits and bloud of Chriſt did not take away, there is provided for them a place of Torments called Purgatory, where they are to ſuffer until they have given full ſatisfaction, or ſome of their friends have procur'd them a Releaſe by Maſſes or Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170992:21"/>or ſome other way, and after that they are received into heaven. <hi>Thoſe pains of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory are moſt intolerable and far greater than any upon earth: this Reaſon and Revelations and the Fathers have aſsur'd us of.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bellar. de <hi>Purg.</hi> l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. c. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Poenas purgatorii eſſe atrociſſimas &amp; cum illis nullas poenas hujus vitae comparandas, docent patres, probant revelationes &amp; ratio. And if any one denies Purgatory think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that God hath ſo pardoned him by Chriſt as that there remains no temporal pains whereby he muſt ſatisfie the divine juſtice either in this world or in Purgatory;</hi> Bellarmin <hi>and the Council of</hi> Trent <hi>condemn him to burn for ever in Hell. Conſtanter aſſerimus dogma eſſe fidei Purgatorium,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. l. 1. c. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>adeo ut qui non credit illud ad idem nunquam ſit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturus,
<note place="margin">Concil. Trid. S. 6. Can. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> ſed in gehenna ſempiterno incendio crucian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus. Si quis dixerit culpam ita remitti &amp; reatum aeternae poenae deleri, ut nullus remaneat reatus poenae temporalis exſolvendae, vel in hoc ſeculo vel in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turo Purgatorio, antequam ad regna coelorum aditus patere poſſit, Anathema ſit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Well done Holy Fathers! curſe them ſtoutly, thoſe Heretics that would put out that ſacred fire which warms you and makes your Pot boil. Now the cheat is complete, I ſee your Church-men are reſolv'd to have money by hook or by crook. If people have wit enough as not to be perſuaded to buy Indulgences while they live, at leaſt 'tis hop'd that when they are dying, when their Reaſon is weak and their fears ſtrong, that they ſhall be willing to part with thoſe goods they can keep no longer, to purchaſe a total exemption from, or at leaſt a quicker paſſage through thoſe dreadful Flames,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170992:21"/>which, they are told, will torment them God knows how long. And if that ſhould fail, their ſurviving friends it may chance will have ſome pity upon their ſouls, and buy for them all thoſe aſſiſtances the Church can afford, to help them out of their miſeries; and ſo dead or alive, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y are like to pay for that care your Church takes for their well-being.</p>
                  <p>But I wonder that your Clergy, who have power by their Maſſes and Indulgences to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Souls out of Purgatory as faſt as they pleaſe, ſhould be ſo hard-hearted as to let them lie there, except they or their friends have paid for their deliverance: And I wonder as much at your Peoples folly, that they don't make a ſufficient proviſion of Indulgences while they live, for to carry their Souls ſtraightway to Heaven; being they could get more than enough by ſaying ſome Prayers, or viſiting cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Shrines and Churches which have an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary faculty that way.</p>
                  <p>But what if the Scripture ſaith, That the Souls of the Faithful when they depart out of this life do not go into a place of Torments? muſt we needs be damn'd if we believe it before the Pope? In the Revelations,
<note place="margin">Rev. 14.13.</note> 
                     <hi>Bleſſed are they that die in the Lord, for they reſt from their labours, and their works follow them:</hi> their own works follow them, not the ſatisfactory works or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Fryers; and they reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and therefore are not in a place of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Certainly, St. <hi>John</hi> had been an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick too, but that Purgatory was not found out in his time. <hi>I have a deſire to depart,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 1.23</note> 
                     <hi>and to be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170992:22"/>with Chriſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.8</note> 
                     <hi>We are confident, and willing rather to be abſent from the body, and to be preſent with the Lord.</hi> And our bleſſed Saviour tells the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent Malefactor,
<note place="margin">Luk. 23.43.</note> 
                     <hi>This day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> Though it hath been, and is ſtill queſtioned whether the Souls of the Righteous are admitted into the ſame Manſions of Glory as they ſhall be after the Reſurrection; yet that there is Reſt and Bliſs in their Receptacles, is certainly taught by theſe Scriptures: But there is no mention made of Purgatory in the whole Bible;
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.7 <hi>Ibid.</hi> v. 9.</note> rather we are told, That <hi>the blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin:</hi> That, <hi>If we confeſs our ſins, he is faithful and juſt to forgive us our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſs;</hi> and that,
<note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Chriſt by himſelf hath purged our ſins;</hi> by himſelf, not by the flames of Purgatory.</p>
                  <p>I can't but commend the modeſty of your Clergy, that they have not inſerted their new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deviſed Doctrines in the holy Scripture, but rather hid the Scripture from the People: but I do hugely ſuſpect their honeſty to perſwade men to relie upon ſuch imaginary things as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences and Purgatory, when the beſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove that they can in any wiſe benefit the People, is that they bring great profit to the Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I know you would fain bring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon our Clergy: I ſuppoſe you envy their mighty Power, in that they can do more than all Men and Angels beſides. <hi>They have the Keys of Heaven and Hell;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bel. de poenit. l. 3. c. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>except they abſolve a man, though he be never ſo penitent, yet he muſt be damn'd. Si non eſſent Sacerdotes judices nec vere
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170992:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>peccata remitterent, nemo periret ex eo ſolum qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d Sacerdotem reconciliantem habere non poſſet, ſed, &amp;c.</hi> Moreover, they have the power to deſtroy all the ſeven Sacraments: <hi>Without their intention goes along with their miniſtration, the Sacraments are ineffectual and inſignificant, and they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed that don't believe it.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bell. de Sacram. L. 1. c. 27. Con. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. S. 7. Can. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Sententia Catholico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt requiri intentionem faciendi</hi> quod facit Eccleſia, <hi>ut expreſſe ſacra Synodus Tridentina. His verbis. Si quis dixerit, in Miniſtris dum Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta conficiunt &amp; conferunt, non requiri in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionem faltem faciendi quod facit Eccleſia, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema ſit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed if your tale be true, your Prieſts have a moſt unlimited Power; and except they uſe it aright, the poor people are like to ſmart for it. 'Tis a thing muſt make them very dear and precious to the Laity, that except they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, a penitent ſinner he muſt go to Hell not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his repenting and begging for mercy. But ſure you forget one thing in their commendation, that they are as infallible as the Pope; nay more, that they do as well as God know the hearts of men: for 'twould be a very odd thing if they ſhould abſolve a wicked Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite and ſend him to Heaven, or ſend a true Penitent to Hell by refuſing to abſolve him. What a dreadful thing muſt a Prieſt be amongſt you? and how careful muſt your people be to pleaſe them, when by their only thoughts they can damn them as faſt as they will? If his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention be wanting when he baptizeth a Child, the poor Creature will live and die a Heathen. If when he marries he intends it not, Maſter
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170992:23"/>Bridegroom in ſtead of a Wife hath got none but a Concubine. In the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, he may chance to make the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple worſhip nothing but a Wafer, if he doth not intentionally conſecrate. And who knows but that intention might be wanting in the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Prieſt, of the Pope himſelf, or of ſome of their Predeceſſors? and then how great are the miſchiefs that follow thereupon? Are not thoſe very pious Doctrines? and don't they well deſerve the Councils curſe that will not believe them? Your Clergy-mens Power is indeed much to be admired, that they can get credit to ſuch ſtuff as this, and impoſe ſo groſly upon the people.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>No wonder if you are injurious to our Miniſters, when you are ſo to the Sacraments themſelves; making them to be but ſigns to put us in mind of what they ſignifie. We differ as much from you in this, as in the precedent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle: for we are taught by the holy Council, <hi>That Sacraments confer Grace to the Receivers,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cone. Trident. S. 7. Can. 8. Bel. de effectu Sacram. l. 2. c. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>opere operato, by their own immediate vertue and efficacy. As the fire burns by its ſelf,</hi> (ſaith Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine) <hi>not by the dryneſs of the wood; ſo the Sacraments give Grace by their own ſelves without any diſpoſition or qualification be required of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, and not as Hereticks ſay by exciting faith, &amp;c. Catholici probant Sacramentorum efficaciam non pendere ab ulla qualitate ſuſcipientis. — Nam ut ignis urit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Et c. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c. Et— ibid. Titulus Capitis tertii, quod Sacramenta ex opere operato conferant gratiam— Non ut concio excitando fidem, ut dicunt haeretici.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170992:23"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>By Mr. <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s good leave, we dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate nothing from the Ordination or the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of Clergy-men, much leſs from the two Sacraments which Chriſt inſtituted; they all really give and exhibit what they ſignifie: by them God conveys his Grace really and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, at all times, and to all Receivers <hi>non ponentibus obicem,</hi> that do not hinder their effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy by their indiſpoſition and perverſeneſs. But 'tis very ſtrange that you make ſpiritual Graces to be inherent in things material, as if they were their natural properties; and make thoſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to work upon our ſouls by themſelves more powerfully, than that very matter that is perſonally united to them. And 'tis likely to prove a great hindrance to Devotion and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to tell the people, that whatſoever their preparations or the condition of their Souls be, they ſhall certainly receive the Grace offered in the Sacraments: ſo that if a dying wicked man can but make the Prieſt to believe that he hath attrition or contrition enough to be in a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of having the Sacrament adminiſtred to him, then the Abſolution and Extream Uncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will conjure him up to Heaven by their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſe and powerful vertue: And then who would be at the trouble of living ſoberly, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, and godly, as the Goſpel requires, when one may be ſaved without it? I might bring Sacriptures againſt this opinion, but it confutes it ſelf; and I believe the Owners of it will rather miſ-repreſent, than defend it. But ſure the Fathers of <hi>Trent</hi> were got in an ill mood, when they did curſe thoſe that would
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170992:24"/>not believe, that under the Goſpel there is ſeven Sacraments inſtituted by Chriſt, as they did in the Canons of their ſeventh Seſſion: for one might look long enough before he could find any ſuch thing in the New Teſtament, and they were not pleaſed to ſay when nor where two or three of them were inſtituted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Can't you take it upon their credit? and don't you think that as they had more, ſo they had better eyes than you? Sure you put a great deal of confidence in your capacity, and in your ſenſes! That's the reaſon I believe that you will not be perſwaded, <hi>that in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper the ſubſtance of Bread and Wine is really changed into the very ſubſtance of the Body and Bloud of Chriſt: ſo that not only under either kind of the Elements, but alſo under each the leaſt crum or drop of them Chriſt is wholly and ſubſtantially contained, his Body and Bloud, with his Soul and Divine Nature.</hi> This the ſame Fathers have taught us, and it ſhall not be the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your eyes ſhall ſave you from the <hi>Anathema</hi> they have pronounc'd againſt all thoſe that will not believe it.
<note place="margin">Concil. Trid. c. 4. S. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>Sacra Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus declarat per conſecrationem panis &amp; vini converſionem fieri totius ſubſtantiae panis in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiam corporis Domini, &amp; totius ſubſtantiae vini in ſubſtantiam ſanguinis ejus.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">S. 13. Can. 3.</note> Et alibi. <hi>Si quis negaverit in vencrabili ſacramento ſub una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaque ſpecie &amp; ſub ſingulis cujuſcunque ſpeciei partibus ſeparatione facta totum Chriſtum contineri, Anathema ſit. Si quis negaverit in Sacramento contineri vere,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">S. 13. Can 1.</note> 
                     <hi>realiter, &amp; ſubſtantialiter, corpus &amp; ſanguinem una cum anima &amp; divinitate Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170992:24"/>— ac proinde totum Chriſtum, Anathema ſit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Should they put out my very eyes with their fulminations, I cannot believe the Gloſs as they have made upon the Text of the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of that Sacrament. I believe what Chriſt ſaid, <hi>That the Bread and Wine are his Body and Bloud:</hi> after what manner he beſt knows; I am ſure his words are true and real, though myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious beyond the reach of our reaſon. A little modeſty had better becom'd your holy Fathers than thus peremptorily to define things which they themſelves confeſs to be abſtruſe; and by their Definitions heap abſurdities one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, make a thin Wafer, and every crum of it diſtinctly to become a whole and entire Body, ſo that you receive at a time as many Bodies of Chriſt as there is little parcels in the Bread you take. And what becomes of all thoſe entire Bodies and Souls in your Stomachs, who knows? And how Chriſt came by ſuch an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite multitude of Bodies, when we read but of one that was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt in the holy Virgin, and now ſits at the right hand of God, as we ſay in our Creed? And what will become of them all? whether they ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to nothing, or glorified alſo, after they have been a certain time in the Stomachs of the Receivers? Theſe and many more Queſtions, ſome whereof very impious, have been and are ſtill diſputed amongſt your School-Divines. Why was a Myſtery, which ſhould be the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our faith and reverence, made a perplexed Riddle, by making the object of our ſenſe groſs
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170992:25"/>and material?
<note place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> The Scripture ſaith, <hi>That Chriſt dwells in our hearts by faith,</hi> not by a corporal preſence which requires no faith: as to that manner of preſence,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.11.</note> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The poor ye have always with you, but me ye have not alway:</hi> And St.
<note place="margin">Col. 3.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Paul, Seek ye the things which are above, where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God.</hi> It is written,
<note place="margin">Heb. 2.17</note> 
                     <hi>That in all things he was made like unto his Brethren:</hi> therefore his Body is but in one place at once; and where it is, is the object of ſenſe as ours be, and as we read his was after his Reſurrection, when he told his Diſciples, <hi>Handle me and ſee,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 24.39.</note> 
                     <hi>for a Spirit hath not fleſh and bones as ye ſee me have.</hi> And the Angels ſaid when he went up into Heaven,
<note place="margin">Act. 1.11.</note> 
                     <hi>This ſame Jeſus which is taken up from you into Heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner as ye have ſeen him go into Heaven.</hi> Theſe Scriptures are plain and eaſie, there is no myſtery in them as there is in the words of the Inſtitution of the Sacrament: therefore he that believes both according as they are reveal'd, doth certainly better than he that expounds a myſterious Text, ſo, as thereby to contradict many clear and plain ones.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>But then how could Chriſt be really ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed in the Sacrament, if his Body and Bloud was not there? for we <hi>firmly believe that in the Maſs the very ſame Chriſt who once yielded himſelf a bloudy ſacrifice upon the Croſs, is bodily ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed without bloud-ſhedding: and therein, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Apoſtolical Tradition, is truly and really offered a ſacrifice, not only for the ſins, pains, ſatisfactions, and other neceſſities of the faithful alive, but alſo for thoſe that are dead in the Lord,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170992:25"/>and are not yet throughly purged.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Conc. Trident. S. 22. Cap. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Quoniam in divino illo ſacrificio quod in Miſſa peragitur idem ille Chriſtus continetur &amp; incruenter immolatur, qui in ara crucis ſemel ſeipſum cruente obtulit, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet ſancta Synodus ſacrificium iſtud vere propitiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium eſſe, — quare non ſolum pro fidelium viro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum peccatis, poenis, ſatisfactionibus &amp; aliis neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitatibus, ſed &amp; pro defunctis in Chriſto, nondum ad plenum purgatis, rite juxta Apoſtolorum tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem offertur.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>We don't read when Chriſt inſtituted the Sacrament, that he offered a bodily Sacrifice for the ſins of the living and the dead, or inſtituted ſuch an one, (though we believe that bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament really to be a commemorative Sacrifice of that which Chriſt offered upon the Croſs, and which was typified as now it is remembred by real Sacrifices) we don't read of any adoration given by the Apoſtles to the Sacrament, but you teach that it muſt be worſhipped with that high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt kind of worſhip which is proper to God alone. <hi>Latriae cultu.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Conc. Trident. S. 13. Cap. 5.</note> We find the ſame example and command for the receiving the Wine as the Bread; but you have wholly taken away the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Wine from all but the Miniſters, and withal pronounc'd a curſe to thoſe that ſhould dare to ſay that ye have not well done:
<note place="margin">Conc. Trident. S. 21. Can. 2.</note> as alſo <hi>to thoſe that ſhould find fault with your not ſpeaking in a vulgar Tongue, or with your ſpeaking very low part of the Canon, and the words of Conſecration, or with your mixing Water with the Wine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Concil. Trident. S. 22. Can. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>or with your celebrating Maſſes in honour of the Saints, and to obtain their interceſſion. Si impoſturam eſſe Miſſas celebrare in honorem ſanctorum &amp; pro illorum inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſione
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170992:26"/>apud Deum obtinenda, Anathema ſit. Si quis dixerit Eccleſia Romana ritum quo ſubmiſſa voce par canonis &amp; verba conſecrationis proferuntur, damnandum eſſe, aut lingua tantum vulgari Miſſam celebrari debere,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> Can. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>aut aquam non Miſcendam eſſe vino in Calice eo quod ſit contra Chriſti inſtitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, Anathema ſit.</hi> In a word, let any one read the Inſtitution of that bleſſed Sacrament in the three Goſpels, and compare it to what is now done and taught among you, and if he will but believe his own eyes, he muſt needs confeſs that you have moſt wretchedly corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and deform'd it. But againſt your pretended ſacrificing of Chriſt for the ſins of the living and the dead,
<note place="margin">Heb 7.26, &amp; 27.</note> I'll oppoſe theſe Scriptures: <hi>Such an high Prieſt became us— who needeth not daily as thoſe high Prieſts to offer up ſacrifice firſt for his own ſins, and then for the peoples: for this he did once when he offered up himſelf.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb 9.12</note> 
                     <hi>By his own bloud he entred once into the holy places, having obtained eternal redemption for us.</hi> What need then he be ſacrificed any more for ſin and ſatisfaction, as you reach? At the 26 verſe, <hi>Once in the end of the world he appeared, once to put away ſins by the ſacrifice of himſelf:</hi> the whole Chapter is againſt Chriſt being ſacrificed again. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that the New Covenant which Chriſt made with us in his Bloud is this, <hi>Their ſins and iniquities will I remember no more:</hi> and then infers, <hi>Now where remiſſion of theſe is, there is no more offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſin.</hi> And at the 14 verſe, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid, <hi>That he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified.</hi> And then what need thoſe daily Sacrifices or Offerings for ſin that are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170992:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>amongſt you? Now let your Church boaſt no more of her infallibility, except ſhe can firſt prove that thoſe many clear and expreſs Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures which ſpeak againſt her new Doctrines are miſtaken, or elſe that God meant by them quite another thing than what he expreſt, and that men are not to believe any thing of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, though never ſo plain, until the Pope hath determined how far and in what ſenſe: until that be done, we will, together with the primitive Concils and Fathers, make the Word of God the Rule of our Faith, and adhere to the three ancient Creeds, and then laugh at your wilful and confident Aſſertions, as we do at that which is call'd a Womans reaſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>You may laugh as long as you will, you can never ſcorn us ſo much as we do you: and for all you are ſo ſtout here at home, if you were in thoſe Countries where there is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, they'll make you talk after another rate, and feel that ſuch perverſe Hereticks as you are deſerve to be uſed as bad as the worſt of Infidels; <hi>and that faith is no more to be kept with you, than with Tirants and publick Robbers. Praeſens Sancta Synodus ex quovis ſalvo conductu per Imperatorem, Reges &amp; alios ſaeculi principes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Concil. Conſtant. S. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>haereticis vel de haereſi diffamatis putantes eoſdem ſic à ſuis erroribus revocare, quocunque vinculo ſe aſtrixerint, Conceſſo: nullum fidei Catholicae vel juriſdictioni Eccleſiaſticae praejudicium generari poſſe ſeu debere declarat. Quominus dicto ſalvo condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu non obſtante, liceat judici competenti &amp; Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtico inquirere, punire, &amp;c. Etiamſi de ſalvo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductis Confiſi ad locum venerint judicii, alias non
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170992:27"/>venturi. Nec ſic permittentem, cum fecerit quod in ipſo eſt ex hoc in aliquo remanſiſſe obligatum. Fides haereticis data ſervanda non eſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Becan. Inſt. tit. 46. S. 51.</note> 
                     <hi>ſicut nec tyrannis piratis, &amp; caeteris publicis praedonibus.</hi> And ſo I leave you to the tickling of your own fancy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, good Maſter, don't be gone yet, and don't be ſo angry, I'll rather not laugh at all than loſe your company. And the truth is, I could much ſooner weep when I think of the ſad Diviſions which are betwixt the hearts, as well as the judgments of Chriſtians. Though I have an averſion to ſome of your Doctrines, yet I aſſure you I have none for you, nor any others that diſſent from our Church. And would to God our different Opinions had not ſo utterly deſtroyed not only Chriſtian Charity, but even Humanity; ſuch bloudy and unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Doctrines and Practices as you now menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, had never been ſeen nor heard of. And for all your ſuddain paſſion, I am perſwaded you have ſo much of humane Nature in your breaſt, that if you conſult your heart upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts, you'll find in it ſome abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to thoſe cruelties as have often been uſed againſt diſſenting Chriſtians by thoſe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be better, if not the beſt of that name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly I confeſs that in cold bloud I ſhould be unwilling to uſe ſuch ſeverities againſt any body; and for my own ſelf, I would not perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute any man upon the account of Religion. But yet I cannot condemn the practice of our Church in this: for the Pope, out of the pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170992:27"/>of that power he hath over all the Chriſtian World, may well diſpoſe of the life of an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick that will not be reclaim'd: for he hath power to diſpoſe, for the good of Souls, and the advancement of the Catholick Faith, of the Kingdoms, and the very Lives of all Princes, if the aforeſaid exigencies require it. Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Stapleton</hi> after having diſputed againſt thoſe who granted too large a power to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> aſſerts this as the moſt moderate Opinion of the Doctors of the Church: <hi>That in caſe of mortal ſin, eſpecially Hereſie, when 'tis likely to be prejudiciable to the Church, the Roman Pontiff as being Supreme Paſtor of it, may for its preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion puniſh any Princes whatſoever; and if it ſhould be requiſite, deprive them of their Kingdoms, either by means of the Parliament, or Peers and Commons: or in caſe of neceſſity, (that is) if it can't be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that way, he may do it immediately by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by his own Authority, by giving his Kingdom to another Prince, or to any the firſt Catholick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror. For ſo</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>Pope</hi> Stephen <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd the Empire from the Greeks to the Germans, and Pope</hi> Innocent <hi>the Fourth took the Government of the Kingdom from the King of</hi> Portugal, <hi>and gave it to his Brother.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Stap. contr. 3. de pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mario ſubjecto poteſtatis Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticae quaeſt. 5. a. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>In caſu peccati mortalis &amp; maxime haereſis, potiſſimum quando in publicum aliquod &amp; magnum Eccleſiae detrimentum vergit, Romanus Pontifex tanquam ſupremus Eccleſiae Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, ad ejus conſervationem &amp; punire quoſvis prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes poteſt &amp; ſi rei neceſſitas exigat regno privare. —Romanus Pontifex in caſu haereſis principem aliquem dominio privare immediata authoritate po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt in caſu neceſſitatis; alioqui non niſi mediata,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170992:28"/>per populum aut ordines regni vel Senatum civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis: at ſi iſtud non ſuccedat (qui eſt ſtatus neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis) poteſt per ſe immediate procedere, dando il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius regnum alteri Orthodoxo principi, vel primo victori Orthodoxo illud aſſignando: ut Stephanus Papa tranſtulit imperium à Graecis ad Germanos. Innocentius quartus interdixit regni adminiſtratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Regi Portugaliae fratrem ejus ſubſtituens, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So likewiſe Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth teach, <hi>That though the Pope as Pope may not uſually, yet that as Supreme Spiritual Prince he may for the good of ſouls diſpoſe of Kingdoms as he thinks good, take them away from one, and give them to another. Non poteſt Papa ut Papa ordinarie, &amp;c. tamen po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt mutare regna &amp; uni auferre atque alteri con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, tanquam ſummus Princeps Spiritualis, ſi id neceſſarium ſit ad animarum ſalutem.</hi> For you muſt know, <hi>That in the Church the Eccleſiaſtick and the Civil Power are, as in Man, the Spirit and the Fleſh; and that Kingdoms and Governments are not immediately of God, but of Men; whereas the Power of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>comes immediately from God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bell. de Rom. Pont. l. 5. c. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſe habent in homine ſpiritus &amp; caro ſic ſe habent in Eccleſia poteſtas politica &amp; Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtica — regna non ſunt immediate à Deo inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, ſed ab hominibus, Pontificatus autem à Deo immediate eſt inſtitutus.</hi> And ſo, <hi>The Pope hath power to diſpoſe of all temporal things belonging to all Chriſtians in general. Pontifex Romanus in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine ad bonum ſpirituale habet ſummam poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem diſponendi de temporalibus rebus omnium Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum.</hi> And according to that unlimited Power in the Head, the Body of the Clergy
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170992:28"/>enjoys great Priviledges: <hi>They are above, or at leaſt equal to King and Princes; and therefore not bound to obey them, neither by Divine nor Humane right.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                     <hi>Reſpectu clericorum non ſunt principes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periores poteſtates ac proinde non tenentur clerici principibus parere neque jure divino neque humano, niſi quantum ad leges quaſdam directivas, i. e. non obligatione eoactiva.</hi> And ſo, <hi>The Goods and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of Clergy-men, as well Temporal as Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick, are and ought to be free from Taxes, and all duties to Princes; and they themſelves ought not to be judged by any Civil Magiſtrate, although they do not obſerve Civil Laws.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bell. de Clericis L. 1. c. 28.</note> 
                     <hi>Non poſſunt Clerici à ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice ſaeculari judicari, etiamſi leges civiles non ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent— Bona clericorum tam Eccleſiaſtica quam ſaecularia libera ſunt ac merito eſſe debent à tributis principum ſaecularium.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I ſee your Pope is a petty God upon Earth, his Power is not to be controul'd, and whatever he doth, his Almightineſs and Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility will bear him out, and make the thing good and juſt, though it ſeem never ſo much otherwiſe. But ſure in this he is none of <hi>Chriſts Vicar;</hi> the meek and humble <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> would not ſo much as divide the Inheritance betwixt two Brethren, much leſs diſpoſe of whole Kingdoms: he paid tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and acknowledged his Authority to be from above; and we read no where that ever he gave any ſuch power to his Apoſtles, or their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, as the Pope pretends to. He told them indeed that they ſhould be brought and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned before the Tribunals of Kings and Princes, but did no where tell them that ever
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170992:29"/>Kings and Princes ſhould be brought before their <hi>Pontifical Chairs</hi> to be judged and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them. We read but of one that ever pretended to have the power of diſpoſing of the Kingdoms of the World, he that ſaid, <hi>All theſe things will I give thee,</hi> Mat. 4.9. And ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Head of your Church will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge himſelf to be his Surrogate, he had beſt ſhew us how he came by the ſame Power. But this Doctrine is ſo contrary to the example and Religion of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that it will be its own antidote: you your ſelves are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to own it openly; and when it is known, it is confuted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſee we ſhall never agree as to particulars; as long as you believe to have the Scripture on your ſide, you'll never yield to the Authority of our Church, which you don't think to be infallible. But in general, by your own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ours is the beſt and the ſafeſt Church: for you yield that a man may be ſav'd in it, whereas we utterly deny the ſame priviledge to yours,
<note place="margin">Stapl. contr. 3. quaeſt. 9. &amp; 10.</note> 
                     <hi>the Communion of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abſolutely neceſſary to the Salvation of all men. Romanae Eccleſiae Communio omnibus eſt ad ſalutem neceſſaria.</hi> You alſo grant that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is St. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſor, which is a great point: And I believe you won't deny but that there is Miracles wrought in our Church, which are unanſwerable Arguments of the truth of its Doctrine. Theſe three are ſubſtantial points, and will abundantly outweigh all the petty Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections you can bring againſt ſome parts of our Religion. Pray conſider of them at your leiſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170992:29"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>To my thinking they require no great conſideration, and there is no ſuch weight in them as you fancy: though you make great uſe of ſuch woodden Arguments to ſeduce the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yet to thoſe that have but an ordinary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency of knowledge they ſeem very inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant.</p>
                  <p>The firſt is comon to you with our Fanaticks, they all confine Salvation every one to his own Sect, and you and they together take advantage of our charity, in that we don't exclude you out of Heaven, you believe that you only ſhall come in it. But, Mr. <hi>Novator,</hi> don't you truſt to our charitable Opinions, we may be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, for we pretend to no infallibility.</p>
                  <p>There was two Barques putting out to Sea, both of them bound for <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> one was rotten, leaky, and much out of order, but the Maſter of it was a bold Man, and of an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Spirit; he would perſwade the people that it was St. <hi>Peters</hi> own Barque, that it was impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Spirit; he would perſwade the people that it was St. <hi>Peters</hi> own Barque, that it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible it ſhould ſink, and that all as many as would not come into it ſhould certainly be drown'd, and never come to the Holy Land: The other Barque was ſound and ſtrong, and well fitted for the Voyage; the Paſſengers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in would tell thoſe in the leaky one of their great danger, and exhort them to ſtop the holes, and put things in better order, though they did not deſpair but that ſome of them might ſwim to ſhore upon ſome pieces of the Barque. Now, do you think this mans confidence would hold his ſinking Ship upon the Water? or that the compaſſionates hopes and wiſhes of the others
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170992:30"/>would make their own ſink? Certainly, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs is a very unfit mark to know Chriſtianity and the true Church by. But let me tell you, that we have no hopes of you as you are Papiſts. Thoſe Articles wherein you differ from us, ſhall greatly indanger, but in no wiſe advance your Salvation. What makes us admit of a poſſibility of your being ſav'd, is, becauſe you hold ſtill the ſame Creed with us, and becauſe though you have much ſhaken and weakned, yet ye have not quite overthrown the Foundation; that is, Jeſus Chriſt and his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving merits, which we hope will avail to thoſe of your Church that truſt in them, though they ignorantly believe thoſe things as would make them ineffectual if underſtood or relied on.</p>
                  <p>As for your ſo much cryed up Succeſſion, it ſignifies no more than this, that now the Pope is Biſhop of the ſame Town as St. <hi>Peter</hi> was, or at leaſt a Town of the ſame name: for old <hi>Rome</hi> hath been deſtroyed long agone. But pray, ſuppoſing that St. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſors were to be the Heads of the Church, who told you that he did not leave that priviledge at <hi>Antioch</hi> where his Sea was firſt? How many Ruptures and Schiſms hath there been in your Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? and how many hath there been of your Popes guilty of the greateſt Impieties and worſt of Hereſies? Your own Authors can inform you; as alſo, how good and bad, Orthodox and Heretick Biſhops have ſucceeded one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all Seas. But make the beſt of it as you can, what is it to the truth or untruth of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170992:30"/>thoſe points we differ about? Becauſe now <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> ſits in the ſame Chair as St. <hi>Peter</hi> did, therefore there is a Purgatory, and men ought to Worſhip Images, and the Pope is infallible, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A very Logical Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence! as good as that of the man who becauſe he ſate in <hi>Tullies</hi> Pew, would needs perſwade himſelf and others that he had <hi>Tullies</hi> Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
                  <p>But there is Miracles daily wrought in your Church by ſome Saint or other, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>! This is ſomething indeed! but 'tis common to all Religions. Monſieur <hi>Bernier,</hi> a man of your Church, will tell you as an eye-witneſs of it, that the Turks and Gentiles pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the ſame, and are more perſwaded of the truth of their Miracles, than (I believe) many in your Church are of the truth of yours. But let me tell you, that Miracles are for Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, not for Believers. St. <hi>Paul</hi> could not heal <hi>Trophimus,</hi> to him a beloved Chriſtian, though among the Unbelievers he could even raiſe up the dead. We believe the Religion Preached by the bleſſed Apoſtles upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of thoſe Miracles they wrought when they were yet alive; without their Reliques and Images work the ſame wonders, now, we are perſwaded of the truth of what they then delivered. And the truth is, you are ſo your ſelves. You don't pretend your new Miracles to confirm thoſe Eſſential Doctrines of the Chriſtian Religion which you and we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed about: Your greateſt Miracle-mongers have hardly reported any one Miracle wrought
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170992:31"/>theſe five or ſix hundred years in theſe parts of the World, to authorize Chriſtian Religion, or to prove the Doctrine of the bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or of the two Natures united in Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one perſon, (about which points were moſt of the ancient Hereſies) or any one Article of the Creed, they are all to confirm your new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Doctrines: The Cures as the Saints work upon thoſe that worſhip their Images, the appearing of dead Folks to beg for Maſſes and Prayers, the return of Souls out of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to tell how hot the fire is, and how well worth ones money Indulgences are, the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders done by your Fryars, or the Founders of their Orders, or of ſome one who is to be Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized, and moſt of them ſo ridiculous and ſo abſurd, that I believe the moſt ſerious Bigot amongſt you can hardly hold laughing at the reading of your Legends and Books of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. And ſo of thoſe three things you ſo much relied on, the firſt is againſt you, the ſecond ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies nothing, and the laſt expoſeth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt thoſe Doctrines it ſhould juſtifie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I did not think that you could ſay ſo much for your ſelves; and I aſſure you, I ſhall hereafter have a better opinion of you than ever I had: thus much at leaſt ſhall I be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited by our long Diſcourſe; and now Sir, fare you well, I thank—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, don't thank me, 'tis I ſhould thank you, for telling me ſo plainly thoſe Doctrines of your Church we diſagree about, and which uſually you ſo miſrepreſent to thoſe of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that they hardly ever know the truth of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170992:31"/>what your Church believes. But pray don't go away yet, I'll help you to that company as you will like much better than mine: I'll tell you whoſe 'tis, when firſt I have deſired theſe two things of you: Firſt, that you would conſider, how greatly ſuſpicious it is that your Church maintains thoſe Doctrines we call Errours, more for their profitableneſs to her than for any other reaſons, becauſe they all tend to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of her Riches or Authority. The Popes Infallibility, and his Power of diſpoſing of all the World for the good of Souls, the exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Clergy from the power of the Civil Magiſtrate, the requiſiteneſs of their intention in the adminiſtring of your Sacraments; how powerful, how honourable, and withal how dreadful muſt the belief of theſe make your Church and Church-men: The Doctrine of Purgatory, of Jubilees, Pardons, Indulgences, and worſhipping of Saints, (the beſt part whereof is the offering to them) what Eſtates, what Riches, what a world of profit doth it bring to the Head, and all the Members of your Clergy? In thoſe points of Chriſtian Religion that concern not her Intereſt, your Church is ſound and Orthodox, thoſe beggerly Hereſies of the <hi>Arians, Eutichian, Macedonians, &amp;c.</hi> are condemned and deteſted by her as much as ever they were by the firſt Councils: yours are Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Errours, if they are groſs and palpable, yet they are profitable and advantageous. The Pope is none of thoſe mean Souls that will hold erroneous Opinions meerly out of perverſeneſs and obſtinacy: <hi>Si Jus violandum, &amp;c. ſi Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170992:32"/>adulteranda, regnandi cauſa:</hi> if he errs, at leaſt he ſhall reign by it. And ſo now reciprocally, the Popes Greatneſs is the beſt argument to maintain thoſe Errours whereby he got it, the ſplendor of his own, and the intereſt he hath in the Courts of ſeveral Princes, the dependency all the Clergy hath upon him, the numerous Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of Souldiers he hath quartered in all Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beys and Monaſteries, and the influence they have upon the common people, his Inquiſitions, and his <hi>Ravilliacks,</hi> theſe be the beſt proofs to evidence the truth of thoſe Doctrines we have rejected, as well as to uphold his Pontifical Chair over the Throne of Chriſtian Princes.</p>
                  <p>The other is, that, remaining in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of your Church, you would think thoſe the moſt ſubſtantial Articles of your Faith which were delivered by the Apoſtles, confirm'd by the firſt Councils, and now believ'd by you and us together; and that upon them you would lay the greateſt ſtreſs of your future well-being. You cannot but ſee by what I have objected out of Gods Word againſt many of your Doctrines, and by what many learned men have written out of the beſt Records of Antiquity, (if you durſt read them) that thoſe things in debate betwixt us are at the beſt but doubtful; therefore 'twill be more ſure to relie chiefly on what is believ'd of both parties, our common Symbol or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Creed. You uſe to ſay, that yours is the ſafeſt Church, becauſe we believe as well as you that men may be ſav'd in it: And now I uſe the ſame reaſon and ſay, that 'tis better to believe as we do, becauſe you alſo acknowledge what we
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170992:32"/>believe to be ſound and Orthodox. That the Scripture is the Word of God, and therefore infallible; That God is the only Object of our Religious Adoration; That Jeſus Chriſt is in Heaven, and there to be worſhipped; That his Blood doth cleanſe us from all ſin, That he intercedes for us; and, That he will render to every man according to his works; the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is plain in all this, and you believe it as well as we: therefore 'tis much more certain and to be relied on, than the Popes Infallibility, the worſhipping Images, with the worſhip of <hi>Douleia</hi> as you ſpeak, the belief of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, the Doctrine of Purgatory, the relying on the Merits, Satisfactions and Interceſſions of the Saints, and the Pardons and Indulgences of the Church-treaſure.
<note place="margin">Bell. de Juſtif. l. 5. c. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Propter incertitudinem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priae juſtitiae &amp; periculum inanis Gloriae, tutiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum eſt fiduciam totam in ſola dei miſericordia &amp; benignitate reponere. Becauſe of the uncertainty of our own righteouſneſs, and the danger of ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedneſs, it is ſafeſt of all to put our whole truſt in the mercy of God.</hi> The like might be ſaid of all other points in queſtion. But why could not the learned Cardinal ſay ſo before, and ſpare himſelf the great labours he took about Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, Indulgences, and the Merits and Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of our ſelves and others? by ſaying plainly <hi>Tutiſſimum eſt,</hi> 'tis ſafeſt of all to relie upon Gods mercy: (Certainly in a thing of that moment we ſhould go the ſureſt way to work.) But pray learn that Leſſon of that great Champion of your Church, and mind what I have ſaid.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:170992:33"/>
                  <p>Now I'll tell you, if you ſtay a while longer, I expect Maſter <hi>V.</hi> a Presbyterian Miniſter, one that will tell you ſtoutly of the Beaſt and the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and many other things that will pleaſe you as well: I ſhould be very glad to hear you diſcourſe together, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps 'twill not be altogether unpleaſant to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Ho, Maſter <hi>V.?</hi> I know him of old, I would go many a mile to ſee him, and to talk with him: I have of late lookt over many of their Presbyterian Books as they printed in the time of the late War. I'll warrant you I'll make brave ſport with him, if you pleaſe but to ſtand Spectator or Auditor for a while: if you can be patient enough to hear us, I dare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you we'll find diſcourſe enough to entertain your attention.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>I will.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <div type="preface">
               <pb facs="tcp:170992:33"/>
               <head>The Preface.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Doctrines and Conſtitutions of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and oppoſed by the Presbyterians, have been ſo fully aſſerted againſt their Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Innovations, by the labours of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral learned men, that it had been</hi> actum agere, <hi>to thruſt my Sickle into other mens Harveſt, to ſay any thing in defence of them. I have therefore made it my only buſineſs, to diſcover their profeſt Religion, as it hath been ſolemnly taught by the Deeds and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of their greateſt Divines: becauſe I obſerve that they alſo draw people after them, chiefly by concealing or miſrepreſenting of it. I will not tell thee before hand, that they own the worſt of Popiſh Errours; thou ſhalt judge of it when thou haſt made an end of reading this Book. But for fear thou ſhouldſt think that thou knoweſt well enough already what their Doctrines are, I will aſſure thee that they diſguiſe them, and cunningly hide their real and worſt Opinions under fair and ſpecious pretences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I know I ſhall be told that I rake into the duſt of old ſtories, and open the grave of
<pb facs="tcp:170992:34"/>Oblivion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and be called a Lyar and a Calumniator, and what elſe they pleaſe.</hi> Veritas odium parit. <hi>But I ſay, that thoſe Authors I have cited, have never recanted their Errours, nor the Divines of that party ever cenſured or diſowned them or their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; but they ſtill perſiſt to impoſe upon the people, and draw them away from the Church, by the ſame arts and pretences as they did at firſt. And I proteſt that (though I might) I have not mentioned the failings of any one man, whom I knew to have repented of them by returning to his duty: neither have I falſified any of my Quotations in the leaſt, nor made ſuch ſevere reflections upon them as one might, but ſaid juſt as much as I thought would ſuffice to make them hang to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and let the Reader ſee the cheat. And as for their ill ſpeaking of me, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it not: for let it be never ſo bad, I am ſure they have ſaid worſe of better men than either I am, or pretend to be. If it be objected, That I have brought in a ſilly Presbyterian, who ſpeaks but two or three words at a time, and ſays nothing in his own defence: I deſire it may be conſidered, that the Papiſt having the Concluſion to prove, was therefore to be longeſt in his Diſcourſes, and that Replies and a full debate of the points
<pb facs="tcp:170992:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>in queſtion had been uſeleſs and inconſiſtent with my intended brevity. But the truth is, I knew not what my</hi> Veterator <hi>could have anſwered to thoſe proofs that were brought againſt him, I deſire the Reader to obſerve, whether they do admit of any pleas or evaſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And now before I ſuffer thee to hear the Diſcourſe of my</hi> Colloquutors, <hi>let me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire theſe two things of thee: Firſt, That whatſoever Religion thou art reſolved to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, thou wouldſt take heed, that by delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding arts and goodly pretences thou beeſt not made to follow thoſe Doctrines and practices which are hereafter mentioned, and the which if thou art a Chriſtian and a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, thou canſt not but condemn as being erroneous and criminal in the higheſt degree. And ſecondly, That thou would not draw poiſon out of my Antidote, be uncharitable to thoſe that are, becauſe I have made thee ſee their errours: ſuch foul Doctrines as thou ſhalt find in this Book, are never good but at ſecond hand; and they are mentioned by me with deſigns of charity, that thou mightſt avoid them, not to make thee hate or deſpiſe the Authors or Abettors of them. Remember that other mens faults ſhall not excuſe thine:</hi> Wherefore let him that
<pb facs="tcp:170992:35"/>thinketh he ſtands, take heed leſt he fall, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12. <hi>In ſtead of inſulting over them that are miſguided or fallen, do thou pray heartily with the Church,</hi> That God would bring into the way of truth all ſuch as have erred and are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170992:35"/>
               <head>Popery Manifeſted, AND THE <hi>Papiſt Incognito made known:</hi> By way of <hi>DIALOG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E</hi> between a Papiſt Prieſt, a Proteſtant Gentleman, and a Presbyterian Divine.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Second Part.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Servant, Sir, I come to ſee how you do, and to ſpend an hour with you according to my promiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, you are very wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, I am glad to ſee you, and I was very impatient of your coming, as much to enjoy your good company my ſelf, as to procure it to this old acquaintance of mine, who long'd for it as much as I did.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, I doubt you have too many ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintances: I know the man, and am ſorry to ſee you ſhould keep company with him, an Enemy to Chriſt and Chriſtian Religion. Take heed, Sir, Antichriſt is of a very ſeducing Spirit.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170992:36"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh how now, Maſter! you fall foul up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me already: that's a very coarſe Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſalute me with the odious name of Antichriſt. But I hope you are not in earneſt: for my part I am glad to ſee you, and deſire to ſhake hands with you, if it will not defile the holineſs of yours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>Avoid Satan! I would not have ſo much as your ſhadow to touch me; and I am ſorry to polute mine eyes with the ſight of ſuch a foul object as you are: no, there ought to be no communication betwixt light and darkneſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>That's true too: but I'll warrant you, you and I are much of a dye, and I am not of ſo dark a colour as you think. I dare ſay, for all your great averſion to me, your Religion and mine differ but a little; or at leaſt nothing ſo much as that of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which you think comes very near to ours. I can make it appear that we of <hi>Rome</hi> are agreed in many things with the Engliſh Presbyterians, wherein we greatly differ from other Proteſtants: come, my good Friend, let you and I diſpute the caſe a little, you ſhall find that I'll give you great ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe be impertinent brags and para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes: I need no ſatisfaction in the caſe, I am ſure enough of the contrary: There are no men under the Sun that hate and abhor Popery ſo much as we do; therefore you may ſpare your labour, and keep your breath for a better uſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray, Sir, don't ſhrink, or elſe you'll give him occaſion to inſult, and me to be doubtful. Sure after having been theſe twenty years ſet
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170992:36"/>about the extirpation of Popery, you are not afraid of being now prov'd a Papiſt. Come, make him repent of his bold challenge, and make it appear that your practice and opinions are as averſe to <hi>Rome</hi> as your words and clamors have been.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet ſtill I ſtand upon my firſt ground, you come very near to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in many things wherein you differ from the Church of <hi>England;</hi> even in thoſe things that are counted the worſt of our errours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall quickly confute your falſe and daring Aſſertion. And firſt, your Church doth greatly derogate from the Word of God, and makes it inferiour to her Traditions, and the Determinations of her Popes and Councils. Can you charge us with any ſuch thing?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, that I can. You do greatly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value the ſame Divine Word to ſet up your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons the higher: you perſwade your people that that is the only Preaching, and the true and only Word of God which you deliver out of your Pulpits; ſo that your own Diſcourſes are more attended and more regarded than the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it ſelf: And ſo prevalent is this opinion, that thoſe of your ſort that go to the Pariſh Churches defer to go in while the Pſalms, the Chapters, and the Epiſtle and Goſpel are read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as if theſe were not worth the hearing: But what is of the mans own making, they will liſten to attentively, and perhaps write it down, and repeat it with a great deal of Devotion. Gods Word is but a Woodden Dagger with you, it doth not reach the heart: but the worſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170992:37"/>Sermon in your Conventicles pierceth the very ſoul, and makes the people ſigh and groan, and take on moſt pitifully: the powerfulneſs of Preaching indangers the very heart-ſtrings! And ſo current 'tis amongſt you that your Preaching is the Word of God, that 'tis call'd by the name of <hi>The Goſpel,</hi> and to hear it is made a <hi>Mark of Election.</hi> So Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Burroughs</hi> told the Parliament:
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>rm. print. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>645. p. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>When I conſider this place</hi> [Weſtminſter,] <hi>the extraordinary hand of God in bringing the Goſpel to be preacht to you here in power, thoſe thoughts preſently ariſe, there is hope that there are many ſouls here belonging to Gods Election; ſurely many will come in and imbrace the Goſpel here.</hi> And by the tranſcribing thoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oracles, men were to judge of the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion their ſouls were in. <hi>Thomas Palmer</hi> in a Sermon of his tells the people,
<note place="margin">164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8.</note> That <hi>to hear Sermons, and not write them, is like taking water in a Sieve: You keep a Shop-Book,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>O be perſwaded to keep a Soul-Book, that you may know how your Spiritual Eſtate ſtands,</hi> (belike thoſe that had much written had very rich ſouls) <hi>what increaſe or decreaſe of Grace you make: this recording of revealed Truths and Soul-experiences from God, would be of admirable uſe in time of trouble.</hi> This is the difference in the caſe, we undervalue Scripture that we may heed the more the Decrees of our Pope; and you, that you may the better attend to the dictates of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of your Sermonizers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>I know all you can alledge will come ſhort of what you would prove, therefore I don't intend to trouble my ſelf with anſwering
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170992:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>your impertinencies; it would but make our Diſcourſe too tedious: let this Gentleman be judge betwixt you and I who are in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e right.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>That will be very well: I'll follow your example, and endeavour to ſhorten our Dialogue by pleading guilty t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> every Article: Charge our Religion with what you will, I'll deny nothing, but ſhew you your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wn face in that Mirrour you ſhall reach to me. Come, proceed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>In your publick Worſhip you uſe an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Tongue which the people doth not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and thereby you keep them in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that they may not be able to diſcern the errours of your Religion. I am ſure you can tax us with no ſuch thing, for we make all things plain to our hearers, and they are an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and a knowing people, who have more light in ſpiritual matters than any people whatſoever.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>You do but fancy ſo; they are as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant as any of us, and they underſtand as little what you ſay: though you ſpeak Engliſh, yet you ſpeak an unknown Language to the people: for you have ſo ſpiritualiz'd Religion, that you have made riddles and myſteries of the plaineſt of its Doctrines: it all conſiſts in new-coin'd phraſes, and ſpiritual notions, and fancies, and ſecrets. Pray hear what Mr. <hi>Francis Cheynell</hi> preacht before the Parliament:
<note place="margin">Serm. 1646. p. 2. and 3.</note> 
                     <hi>God doth commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate rare ſecrets to certain known and choſen men, to Prophets Prophecies, Chriſt to his Diſciples Goſpel-ſecrets, Doctrinal-ſecrets, God to men of publick ſpirits ſecrets of State; and we have ſeen ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable experiences of Gods mercy in this kind
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170992:38"/>within theſe five years, that our Poſterity will ſcarcely believe what we have ſeen. — God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts myſterious ſecrets to his choſen people, ſome ſecrets to make them his friends, other ſecrets after they are his friends, convincing ſecrets, humbling ſecrets, converting ſecrets.</hi> Don't you think that theſe ſecrets are as bad as Latine? Again, (if I may cite the words of one who was ſomewhat <hi>nearer to the Lord</hi> than you) <hi>Thomas Brooks</hi> in a Sermon of his:
<note place="margin">1648. p. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>O if God would raiſe up Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-men, and men in the Army and in the City, and round the Kingdom to more ſpiritual acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with himſelf, to more internal knowledge, we ſhould find that they would do abundantly more gloriouſly: for it is want of an internal ſpiritual knowledge of God that men are Newters, Apoſtates,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>As you would do glorious and honourable things, look to this, that ye have an internal know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſpiritual acquaintance with God, and this will enable you to do Exploits.— If you would do gloriouſly, keep your Evidences for Glory always bright and ſhining, ſoil not your Evidences for Glory.</hi> And p. 20. <hi>If Parliament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and men in all the Kingdom would believe more gloriouſly, they would do more gloriouſly for God.</hi> Spiritual internal knowledge and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, bright Evidences, believing gloriouſly! I ſhould think theſe as hard to be underſtood by ordinary people as an <hi>Ave Maria:</hi> yet doubtleſs your people muſt needs be very knowing, when you find them with Books whoſe very Titles if well underſtood would be able to open the ſeven Seals:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joſ. Caryl</hi> Preach. of Lincolns-Inn. 1644.</note> 
                     <hi>The Saints thankful acclamation at Chriſts Reſumption of his great power, and the Initials of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170992:38"/>his Kingdom:</hi> A Thankſgiving Sermon for one of your Victories at <hi>Selby</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire, The Thoughts of the Almighty.</hi> A Sermon preacht before the Mayor by a Divine of the Aſſembly, wherein 'tis like <hi>thoſe thoughts</hi> had been revealed to him.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>John Strickland</hi> 1644.</note> Such Books muſt needs give great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> people, and the light of this following Doctrine would queſtionleſs expel even an Egyptian darkneſs!
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>T. Palmer</hi> ibid.</note> 
                     <hi>Who would not now deſire to cloſe with Chriſt, and love Chriſt, and walk with Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>? yea, who would not be rouled up, and wholly incloſed in Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The many Sermons you printed twenty years agone, are for the moſt part full of ſuch inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant, canting and unintelligible myſteries. Now, I ſay, it matters not whether it be Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh or Latine, as long as the people doth not underſtand, both will keep them equally igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. I note only theſe two differences, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they make for us: Firſt, that our Prieſts underſtand their Latine, whereas your Rabbies themſelves cannot make ſenſe of many of their Engliſh Myſteries, And ſecondly, that if our people are ignorant, at leaſt they are conſcious of it, and therefore do follow the Church; whereas your Diſciples when they have got by heart your empty phraſes, are ſo ſelf-conceited of their great skill in diſcerning <hi>the things of the Spirit,</hi> that they judge all others blind that won't admire them, and will venture to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the hardeſt places in Scripture, and ſometimes leave you, and ſet up for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>The Canons and Injunctions of your
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170992:39"/>Church, and the numberleſs Ceremonies ſhe hath appointed, you obſerve with as much ſtrictneſs as if they were commanded by God himſelf; and ſo you make your own devices equal to Gods Ordinances. I am ſure we do quite contrary, for we allow nothing to be done in Gods ſervice, but what he hath appointed himſelf, and we will have Scripture for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Circumſtances of Divine Worſhip.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>I remember indeed that five of your Doctors told us in an Apology they preſented to the Parliament,
<note place="margin">Jer. Bur. Will. Bri. Ph. Nye. Syd. Sam. Th. Good.</note> pag. 10. <hi>That they were certain there was in Scripture Rules and ruled Caſes for all occaſions whatſoever, if we were able to diſcern them:</hi> But I never heard that they had found out only ſo much as enough to determine all the Circumſtances of Gods Worſhip. However, I am ſure you have by far out-done us in the magnifying and impoſing of your own inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. You told us that if your intended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation (which was doubtleſs a device of your own) did not take, Chriſtianity ſhould go near to be loſt. The Miniſter of <hi>Aſhford</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> in a Sermon before the Committee of that County,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joſ. Boden</hi> 1644. p. 30.</note> informs them of the preſent danger of looſing <hi>the Chriſtian Religion through all the Churches of the World, if they ſhould be careleſs and neglect the opportunity put into their hands: The Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath ſet this as a prize, but we muſt run for it; this is propoſed as a Crown to the Saints, but we muſt fight for it:</hi> yea, and reaſon good:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>George Gilleſpie,</hi> 1645. p. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>for that Reformation was according to the mind of Chriſt,</hi> ſaith a Miniſter of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> to the Commons at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170992:39"/>you have rejected the ancient Ceremonies of the Church, (all that was not of your devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) as Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> told the Parliament, <hi>We that live under the Goſpel, know that the worſhip of God the more ſpiritual the more beautiful it is in the eyes of God who is a Spirit, and that the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward pomp in Gods ſervice is an attire more fit for the Whore of</hi> Babylon <hi>than for the modeſt Spouſe of Chriſt, and that Muſick in Gods ſervice though it may pleaſe the ears of men, yet it is unpleaſing in the ears of God,</hi> (if you'll take his word for it.) But what was of your own inventing, O that is much made of! Your Presbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was ſaid <hi>to be of Chriſts own Inſtitution,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>F. Cheynel</hi> Serm. 1646. Ep. Dedic. <hi>Ch. Love</hi> at Uxb. p. 20.</note> ſo the Parliament was taught, and you grac'd it with glorious Epithets, as in theſe lines: <hi>God is feeling the pulſe of this Nation, looking how we are affected: me thinks I hear the Lord asking the Inhabitants of this Kingdom, Will you have your Biſhops, your Common-Prayer-Book?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or will ye have the Goſpel in power? a reformation in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity? your Aſsemblies refin'd? your pollutions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved? and the Government of my Son Eſtabliſht in the midſt of you?</hi> And ſo the ſetling of your Diſcipline was the ſetling Chriſt in his Throne, as Mr. <hi>White</hi> hath it in the Preface to his Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies 1643. <hi>Let us ſet hand and heart and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and all to advance the Lords Sion to a perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of beauty, and to ſet up Chriſt upon his Throne.</hi> And ſo another great One of yours:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>S. Marſhal</hi> Serm. to the Parl. 1643. p. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Did ever any Parliament in</hi> England <hi>lay the cauſe of Chriſt and Religion to heart as this hath done? — Did ever the City of</hi> London, <hi>the reſt of the Tribes, and the godly Party throughout the Land, ſo willingly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170992:40"/>themſelves that Chriſt might be ſet up?</hi> And pag. 20. <hi>Let all</hi> England <hi>cry, that our Bloud, our Poverty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are abundantly repaid in this, that there is ſuch a concurrence to ſet up the Lord Chriſt upon his Throne to be Lord and Chriſt over this our Iſrael.</hi> And the beſt of it is, that when you had nothing to ſay for the antiquity of your goodly Diſcipline and Directory, you would make it a <hi>Diopetes,</hi> a thing fallen from Heaven, or like the Heathen Legiſlators, receiv'd from God himſelf, that it might be reverenc'd according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<note place="margin">Ibid. p. 20</note> The ſame perſon told his Auditory: <hi>Here you have a reverend Aſſembly of grave and learned Divines, who daily wait upon the Angel in the Mount to receive from him the lively Oracles, and the pattern of Gods houſe to preſent to you.</hi> But that which you magnified moſt of all, and which was as much your own contrivance as your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd Directory, was the Covenant, the bleſſed Covenant! There is not a Text in Scripture that ſpeaks of the Covenants God hath made with men at any time, but it was applied to your own by your learned Preachers: Scripture, Sacraments, none of Gods Ordinances was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to it, it was ſo divine and ſo excellent: Proofs are almoſt needleſs in a thing ſo well known, yet I'll bring two or three out of Mr. <hi>Caſe</hi>'s Sermons on the Covenant, upon this Text,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Th. Caſe,</hi> p. 59.</note> 
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.25. <hi>A wonderful mercy, a high favour may we count it from our God, that yet ſuch a ſovereign means is left us for our recovery and reconciliation.</hi> And then ſaith he, pag. 61. <hi>How ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> Again, pag. 19. <hi>There are found amongſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170992:40"/>us ſo many profane Ephramitiſh and Zabulonitiſh ſpirits, that do contemptuouſly reject the Covenant of God.</hi> And pag. 31. <hi>It was no ſmall thing that poor Creatures ſhould be married to the living God,</hi> (by the Covenant) <hi>yea, be one with him, yea, perfect in one.</hi> What could you have ſaid more, except you had quite Deified it? Now therefore in this buſineſs, I ſee no more diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt you and us than this, that our Conſtitutions, our Devices, and our Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, are more in number, but acknowledged to be of Humane Inſtitution; whereas yours be fewer, but of a Divine Origine, as you ſay, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from Scripture or ſome latter revelation: but let the quality go for the quantity, and we are agreed: for 'tis well known that you were as ſevere to thoſe that would not conform and obey, as ever was the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>Now you put me in mind of it, have any ſuch thing as a Pope, who pretends to be choſen by Gods Spirit, and ſo acted by it, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſaith muſt be aſſented to as true, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altogether infallible? Don't we rather reach, That God only is free from all errour and ignorance, but that no man enjoys that priviledge?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>No, you have no ſuch thing as one only Pope, but you have a great many: for every Miniſter of yours pretends to the ſame Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and the ſame Priviledges; and I believe that's the reaſon you hate him of <hi>Rome</hi> ſo much, becauſe he will have no fellows, but reign all alone. I know not how 'tis amongſt you now, but heretofore <hi>the Reforming Parliament-men</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170992:41"/>themſelves were choſen by the Spirit, as Mr. <hi>Caſe</hi> told them in a Sermon:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tho. Caſe,</hi> 1644. p. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>Surely had not the Spirit of the Lord gone forth to a wonder of wiſdom and power in beſpeaking the Votes of the people for a major part of men, whoſe ſpirits were above fears and above flatteries,</hi> &amp;c. If Parliament-men, much more Miniſters: but I need no inference, the Spirit was poured upon you all in ſuch a meaſure, that all ranks of people were endued by it with Heroick, nay, even Angelick Vertues and Abilities, or elſe Mr. <hi>Caſe</hi> was miſtaken: for thus he ſaid,
<note place="margin">Ibid. p. 28</note> 
                     <hi>As the Spirit of the Lord came upon</hi> Sampſon, <hi>and</hi> Jephtah, <hi>and</hi> David, <hi>ſo hath it been in our conflicts, the Spirit of the Lord hath come upon our Noble General, and all our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, the Spirit of the Lord hath come upon our Gallants, Gentlemen, Young men, faithful Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men renowned Citizens: ſo that he that was weak among them is as</hi> David, <hi>and he that was as</hi> David, <hi>hath been as the Angel of the Lord.</hi> And you the teaching Elders, you pray by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and you preach by the Spirit, (wherefore it is I ſuppoſe that you call your Sermons <hi>the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and Gods Word</hi>) and if long Prayers and Sermons be a ſign of having much of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, any of you may vie it with all the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> put together. Nay, and to make the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel compleat, you pronounce <hi>Bulls</hi> and <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations</hi> by the Spirit too,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Wil Beech</hi> Serm. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenc'd by Mr. <hi>Cram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> 1645. p. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Tell them from the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Beech) from the Word of Truth, that their deſtruction ſhall be terrible, it ſhall be timely, it ſhall be total:</hi> And 'tis more than probable, you would have made Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Scripture ere now, had not the Kings Return
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170992:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſomewhat frighted away that Spirit you were ſo poſſeſt withal. But in this there is ſtill ſome difference betwixt our Opinions: for with us the Pope hath the greateſt part of the Spirit, if not all of it; whereas your Miniſters are all ſharers of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet ſtill, for ought you have ſaid, it doth not appear that we pretend to Infallibility, we don't arrogate to our ſelves the power of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting Scripture excluſively to all others; and before we have declar'd what the ſenſe of it is, we don't call it as you do, <hi>A Waxen Noſe,</hi> which may be turn'd all manner of ways, and never right till we fix it our ſelves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>One thing after another pray, we have done with the Spirit, which is the cauſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility; we ſhall now come to the expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Scripture, which is the effect of that cauſe. And to give you your due, I muſt needs ſay that you have done very much in this; and if you will but go on as you have begun, you'll go near to perſwade poſterity, that a body may expound Scripture out of a Scotch Pulpit, as well as out of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, and a great deal better: for beſides the Doctrinal part, beyond which Popes could never go, Presbyterians ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound Prophecies, and make Prophecies too. Pray hear ſome of them:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer. Bur.</hi> Serm. 1643. p. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>All the Saints in theſe days ſhould be full of the Spirit, ſtrong in the might of the Lord, becauſe Jeſus Chriſt is about to pull down that great Enemy of his, that Man of Sin, and in his Conqueſt is ſaid to come with Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments dipt in Bloud.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 19.</note> Do you think any man but he could, have ſeen that this Nation wallowing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170992:42"/>in Bloud was the fulfilling of that Prophecy? Mr. <hi>Th. Goodwin,</hi> who belike had ſeen <hi>the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern in the Mount,</hi> being one of the Aſſembly, made this remarkable diſcovery,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Th. Good.</hi> Serm. to the Parl. 1645. p 47. &amp; 48</note> 
                     <hi>That it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain we are now in the laſt times of thoſe ten King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of</hi> Europe, <hi>of which the Holy Ghoſt hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied,</hi> Rev. 17.14. <hi>Theſe ſhall make War with the Lamb,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And where you ſee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that Jeſus Chriſt hath took footing in any of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms by ſuch a way of conqueſt</hi> (reforming) <hi>as in ours it hath the ſecond time for greater ſecurity, ſtand that Kingdom ſhall till you ſee</hi> Rome <hi>down.</hi> And yet as miſchief would have it, the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſtor'd to his right, their ſecond Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was turn'd out of doors before <hi>Rome</hi> would down. But here is a Seer come from <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> who perchance will have better luck: In a Sermon before the Parliament, after having cited many Scriptures relating to the time of Chriſts coming, and particularly that <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.8. <hi>The Glory of this latter Houſe,</hi> &amp;c. he infers, <hi>There are very good grounds to make us think that this Temple is not far off,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Geo. Gill.</hi> 1644. p. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>and that Chriſt is to make a new face of a Church in this Kingdom, a fair and beautiful Temple for his Glory to dwell in; and he is even now about the work.</hi> So famous Mr. <hi>Bond</hi> in the ſame Auditory expounding the Image in the ſecond of <hi>Daniel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh. Bond,</hi> 1644. p. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>We are come</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to the toes of thoſe feet — the German Eagle is ſtript of her plumes, Papacy drops her Prelatical Feathers continually, ſo that both Scripture, Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology, and common ſence do evince, that the Image doth ſtand at beſt but on tip-toes, and the time is at hand, and I conceive is preſent in which it ſhall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170992:42"/>be thrown down, and utterly aboliſhed.</hi> Oh the mans modeſty, that he did not cry out <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>! What a pity it is that ſuch quick-ſighted Seers have never applied themſelves to writing of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks? I'll bring but one more, but have a care of it, for 'tis one that can bite and ſting, if Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> be to be believ'd,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>T. Coleman</hi> 1645. p. 33.</note> for he told the Houſe of Commons, <hi>There is a biting Prophecie,</hi> Joel <hi>hath ſaid it,</hi> chap. 3. v. 19. <hi>Egypt ſhall be a deſolation, and Edom ſhall be a deſolate wilderneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>how to ſhelter them</hi> (the Cavaliers) <hi>from the ſting thereof, I know not:</hi> Had not that man great skill in Prophecies, that could tell that <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Edom</hi> meant the Kings Party? So much for that.</p>
                  <p>Now 'tis to be conſidered, that we call Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture a Waxen Noſe, and ſo don't you: Well! But what matters it for calling, if you make it ſo <hi>de facto?</hi> Shall we wrangle about names, when we are agreed in the thing? I dare lay my Noſe againſt yours there was never a Waxen Noſe ſo diſtorted and contorted as Scripture was by you: I could produce ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proofs of it, that I am ſure you would be weary, if not convinc'd before I had done: but for your ſatisfaction here's a few of them. That place in <hi>Daniel, In the days of thoſe Kings ſhall the God of Heaven ſet up a Kingdom which ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be deſtroyed,</hi> &amp;c. and that of St. <hi>Matthew, I ſay unto thee, Thou art Peter, and upon,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe places were brought to prove, that the Presbyterians ſhould overcome all their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, in a Sermon called,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>T. Palmer</hi> 1644. p. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>The Saints Support in theſe ſad times: Let ſecret Enemies ſeek to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170992:43"/>let open Enemies plot, prepare, and watch, God will diſcover the one, diſappoint the other, and deſtroy them all,</hi> Dan. 2.44. Mat. 16.18. And pag. 19. <hi>Saints, cheer up your hearts, ply God with your prayers, you ſhall prevail, bleſſed be God your Enemies have been on the decaying loſing hand a pretty while; they have in</hi> Scotland, <hi>that you know, they have loſt in</hi> England, <hi>that you know, and they ſhall loſe and loſe till they have loſt all: as much as I have ſaid you ſhall find in the</hi> Revelations, <hi>in the</hi> 17 <hi>Chapter; you have a large deſcription of the Whore, and all her Glory; and Chapter</hi> 18. <hi>and the ſecond Verſe, there is her deſtruction.</hi> Was not that as pat as could be to prove what he intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? So Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> in a Sermon before the Houſe of Commons, ſpeaking of thoſe that would take Arms againſt the Parliament, rather than the Government and Worſhip they had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved under ſhould be deſtroyed,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Edw. Cal.</hi> 1645. p. 4.</note> tells them, <hi>My Text confutes this, The times of this ignorance God winked at, but now commands all men every where to repent,</hi> Act. 17.30. <hi>Former times were times of ignorance, and times wherein mens Conſciences were oppreſt: but now the times are times of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, God hath given greater liberty, and hath ſent a greater light in the Kingdom, and now God commands all men every where to repent:</hi> that is, as you ſee, to deſtroy that Worſhip and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment they lived under.</p>
                  <p>And in the forementioned Sermon of <hi>William Beech,</hi> pag. 9. the 136 Pſalm is applied to thoſe Encounters wherein they had worſted the Kings Forces: <hi>O give thanks unto the Lord, for he is gracious, and his mercy endureth for ever: who
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170992:43"/>remembred us at</hi> Knasby, <hi>for his mercy endureth for ever: who remembred us in</hi> Pembrock-ſhire, <hi>for his mercy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>who remembred us at</hi> Leiceſter, <hi>for his mercy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>who remembred us at</hi> Taunton, <hi>for his mercy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>who remembred us at</hi> Briſtol, <hi>for his mercy,</hi> &amp;c. but this by the way. I could tell you alſo how you uſed Scripture to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance your cruelty againſt the Loyal Party, but you ſhall hear of it another time: this is enough at preſent to ſhew how you have rack'd and abus'd it to make it countenance your wicked follies. We call Scripture a Waxen Noſe, and you make it ſo; (I ſuppoſe out of kindneſs to us, to make good what we ſay) our Church interprets the Doctrinal part of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and every one of you not only that, but even the hardeſt Prophecies of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, but as much Popes as you can make us, we don't deny but that we are ſubject to Kings and Princes, as not only your Pope, but even your meaneſt Clergy doth: we don't ſay that we can abſolve Subjects from their Oath of Allegiance: we don't pretend to have the right of diſpoſing of the Good of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and even of all the Kingdoms in the World in order to the good of ſouls, as your great Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop doth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Why? Do you think when the Pope was as yet weak and ſtruggling for that Power he hath now got into his hands, that he own'd any ſuch Doctrines? No, I'll warrant him: And to my thinking you have ſhewn more cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage than ever he did, for you have aſſum'd that high Authority you ſpeak of, even when you
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170992:44"/>were not altogether able to maintain it by force, though you ventured very fair for it: but there are three or four things in what you ſaid that muſt not be confounded. And firſt,</p>
                  <p>That not only your Miniſters, but even your People alſo are not ſubject to the Laws of the Civil Magiſtrate, except they approve of them, (which is as much as not at all) will too manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear by thoſe famous, or rather infamous Books of <hi>Rutherford</hi> and <hi>Prynne,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of M. <hi>Prynns Truths Triumph,</hi> 1645. p. 30. p. 25.</note> 
                     <hi>Lex Rex,</hi> and <hi>The Sovereignty of Parliament.</hi> Moreover, we have it in plain terms, That <hi>the general Aſſembly is ſubordinate to no Civil Judicature whatſoever,</hi> in a Book called, <hi>The readineſs of the Scots ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance into</hi> England. And Mr. <hi>Dury</hi> told the Parliament in a Sermon, <hi>Settle but the Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of particular Congregations, and let the Thrones of the whole Houſe of</hi> David <hi>be crected, and you ſhall find that the fruit of righteouſneſs, &amp;c.</hi> Iſai. 32.17. as much as to ſay, Inthronize a Pope in every Pariſh, and all will be well.</p>
                  <p>But ſecondly, you are ſo far from being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Laws of Princes, that you will have them to be ſubject to yours. This was one of the Propoſitions preſented to the Aſſembly at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Art. 8.</note> 1647. <hi>None that is within the Church ought to be without the reach of the Church Laws, and excepted from Eccleſiaſtical cenſures, but Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline is to be exerciſed on all the members of the Church, without reſpect or conſideration of thoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering qualities which uſe to commend a man to other men:</hi> All the Power the Pope claims over ſecular Princes, is included in this one Article. When once the Kirk hath decreed that any
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170992:44"/>thing is Antichriſtian, and muſt down, or that ſome new device is according <hi>to the Pattern in the Mount,</hi> and therefore muſt be eſtabliſht, if the Magiſtrate dares to oppoſe it, then cries the petty Pope, Help ye the Lord againſt the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as <hi>S. Marſhall</hi> in a Sermon:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>S. Marſhal</hi> 1641.</note> 
                     <hi>Curſe ye Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roz for not helping the Lord againſt the Mighty. Some Politicians</hi> (ſaith he, pag. 2.) <hi>look which ſide ſhall prevail, and ſtand Neuter: but as Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon ſaid to the men of</hi> Succoth, <hi>when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to give bread to the people,</hi> Judg. 8.7. — <hi>then will I tear your fleſh with the thorns of the wilderneſs: ſo I ſay to ſuch, if the Lord prevail, he will do them. — Is it ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that they are curſed that help not the Lord againſt the Mighty? Then, Brethren, as you deſire to be freed from this curſe, and to obtain a bleſſing, be exhorted to put forth your hand now to the help of the Lord. I pray look on me as one that comes among you this day to beat a Drum in your ears to ſee who will come out to follow the Lamb.</hi> Here was a Preſs-Maſter for the Synod!</p>
                  <p>Now here what <hi>Th.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tho. Good.</hi> 1645.</note> 
                     <hi>Goodwin</hi> ſaid to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, how that the Saints, <hi>(i. e.</hi> the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and their Adherents) muſt not be croſt in their humour, under pain of utter ruine; after a long canting to ſhew <hi>that the greateſt and higheſt Intereſt of Kings and Kingdoms on which their welfare or their ruine depends, was the dealing well or ill with the Saints,</hi> he gives theſe reaſons for it: 1. <hi>Their nearneſs and dearneſs to God.</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">p. 40.</note> 
                     <hi>The intereſt of the Saints in God the Governour, and the priviledges which they themſelves have vouchſafed them by God in ruling and governing this World,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">p 42.</note>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170992:45"/>
                     <hi>and Providences of God therein. And,</hi> 3. <hi>the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, — whoſe deſign and practiſe is and hath been to break all Kingdoms that do oppoſe him, and oppreſs his Saints.</hi> Here's the Dickins and all (I think) for Papal Power: But you muſt underſtand that all this was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of his Text, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.14. <hi>He ſuffered no man to do them wrong; yea, he reproved Kings for their ſakes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, Sir, that your moſt Godly Party would make a pretty good title to the Goods of the wicked, if they were in power, <hi>Th. Palmer</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to clear, when in the 15 and 16 pag. of his Sermon he made it his buſineſs to prove, <hi>that wicked men who are out of Chriſt,</hi> (i. e. out of their favour) <hi>have no proper right to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, neither to the Sacraments and Ordinances, nor to thoſe Creatures that ſuſtain life: And then</hi> (ſaith he, pag. 17.) <hi>when the Riches, and Honours, and Liberty given to the Saints, and Goſpel-times ſo long promiſed ſhall come, then the wicked miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the wicked begin, then ſhall their time of ſorrow and ſadneſs come in:</hi> whereby he inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, that ſhould once the <hi>Saints</hi> come to reign, the <hi>Wicked</hi> would go near to be dealt with as Uſurpers of what they poſſeſs, as indeed many of them were when the <hi>Saints</hi> had power to plunder and ſequeſter.</p>
                  <p>As for your abſolving from Oaths, I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther charitably believe that you can do that too, than judge you guilty of perjury; for either of the two muſt be, becauſe many of your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters acted contrary to what they had ſworn when they receiv'd Ordination or Inſtitution
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170992:45"/>from the Biſhop: that you won't deny. And again, they acted contrary to their Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, and made their people do ſo too, and take an Oath contradictory to that, your holy Covenant: for though you pretended that it was to make the King happy and glorious, yet 'twas againſt your Allegiance, being it was againſt his will and juſt Authority: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that goodly pretence it ſelf was an affron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Majeſty; for you would make him to deſtroy the Church, which by his Oath at leaſt he was bound to preſerve and maintain; and you would have wreſted his Regal Power out of his hand, and left him only his Scepter to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance you. This is called <hi>Proteſtatio contraria facto,</hi> when a man cuts anothers purſe, and ſwears that he doth him no wrong: but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you cut or untied the knot whereby you were bound to act otherwiſe than you did, I leave it to your choice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>By and by I ſhall ſhew that your Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations ſignifie nothing: but ſuppoſing they did, yet that cannot prove what you intend them for, becauſe the Quarrel betwixt the King and the Parliament, and the War that enſued thereon, was upon a Civil account: and if the people were in the wrong, it was the Lawyers that miſ-led them, and not we. But how many <hi>Holy Wars</hi> hath the Pope raiſed againſt Kings and Emperours, meerly to eſtabliſh or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that ſupreme Authority he claims over them? This alone doth overthrow all you have ſaid of your Papal Power.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170992:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, if you muſt have more proofs, I'll warrant you I can give you enough: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to confirm what I have ſaid of your claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Pope-like Power, I ſhall make it appear that it was you miſ-led the people, and made them rebel, and that your War was a <hi>Holy War upon the account of Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Leech</hi> tells his Auditors in a Sermon, pag.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer. Leech</hi> 1644.</note> 22. <hi>Who is on my ſide, let him caſt down</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabel <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>down with her Idolatries and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, down with her Altars and Images, down with her Rags and Reliques, they be but</hi> Jezabels <hi>fragments, let them be uſed as</hi> Jezabel <hi>was uſed: Help, Royal Sovereign, to throw her down; help to throw her down more and more, ye that are of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Court of Parliament: Every one that loves the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, help to throw her down, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver let us halt as we have done betwixt God and Baal.</hi> 'Tis probable that had <hi>Royal Sovereign helpt to pull down</hi> Jezabel, you had not pulled him down with her: being he proved refracto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Church, you judged it requiſite <hi>in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine ad ſpiritualia,</hi> to make him feel that Power of yours he would not acknowledge. Nay, when there were ſome hopes of an Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> who died a Martyr for your Kirk, was ſo afraid the Holy War ſhould be ended, <hi>and Chriſt not ſet upon his Throne,</hi> (you know what that means) that Preaching at <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>x<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> before the Commiſſioners, he made uſe of another mans words, as he ſaid, to exhort them to go on in fighting for God: <hi>'Tis the Sword</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>not Diſputes nor Treaties muſt end this Controverſie; therefore turn your Plowghſhears into
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170992:46"/>Swords to fight the Lords Battels, to avenge the Bloud of Saints which hath been ſpilt. Curſed is he that doth the work of the Lord negligently, and curſed is he that keepeth back his Sword from Bloud,</hi> Jer. 48.10. Some ſilly Cavaliers thought indeed that the War betwixt the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament was about matters of Priviledges, but <hi>S. Marſhall</hi> told them ſoundly of their ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, in a Sermon before the Parliament, and Mayor and Aldermen:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>S Marſhal</hi> 1643. p. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>Noble and reſolute Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, fight the Battels of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. — All Kingdoms except the Malignants in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>do now ſee that the queſtion here is, Whether Chriſt or Antichriſt ſhall be Lord or King.— Go on therefore couragiouſly, you can never venture your Bloud in ſuch a Quarrel: Chriſt ſhed his Bloud to ſave you from Hell, venture yours to ſet him up up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Throne.</hi> So <hi>Joſ. Boden</hi> told the Kentiſh Committee, pag. 11.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joſ. Boden</hi> 1644.</note> 
                     <hi>That they were fighting for the Lamb againſt the Beaſt.</hi> And at the 13 pag. <hi>Beſides their wondring after and worſhipping the Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 13.4. <hi>Have they not gathered together in Arms and Armies againſt the Lord, and againſt his Chriſt?</hi> (belike they did not give that name to their Parliament Priviledges:) <hi>Nay, are they not daily more and more mad and deſperate in their miſchief conceived againſt the Church? Do they not daily beat up their Alarms, and bid defiance to the people of the moſt High?— I would have every Chriſtian ſtand upon his reputation, and not diſcover puſillanimity after ſuch proud Challengings. What hath Antichriſt done for them, that they dare be ſo bold? And what hath not Chriſt done for us, that we ſhould now in theſe days of daring be da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardly,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170992:47"/>hen-hearted and effeminate?</hi> This Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon was called, <hi>An Alarm beat up in</hi> Sion, <hi>to War againſt</hi> Babylon; and it well deſerves to be tranſcribed, but that it is too long. In all theſe you ſee we hear of nothing but <hi>the Whore, the Beaſt,</hi> Babylon <hi>and Antichriſt,</hi> which were to be deſtroyed; not one word of any Civil mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or differences, if there was any it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, your Church-Champions were ſo intent upon <hi>the Lords Work,</hi> and it proſpered ſo well in their hands, that they could think of nothing elſe.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh. Bond,</hi> 1644. p. 59.</note> 
                     <hi>As</hi> Sampſon <hi>with the Philiſtines,</hi> (ſaith one of the Saints) <hi>ſo let us die with</hi> Babylon: <hi>if we cannot out-live Antichriſt, and the Enemies of Reformation, let us adventure our ſelves to death in the Cauſe; yea, let us take hold of the Pillars of the Church of</hi> Dagon, <hi>of the Temple of Antichriſt, and ſay, Now let me die with Antichriſt,</hi> Rome <hi>and</hi> Babylon. The War was ſo wholly and intirely upon Gods account, (as you ſaid) that though betwixt the Inhabitants of the ſame Kingdom, yet you would not have it to be a Civil War. <hi>It is not a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>J. Arrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith,</hi> 1643. p. 69.</note> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Arrowſmith</hi> to the Parliament) <hi>but one King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom againſt another, the Kingdom of Chriſt divided againſt that of Antichriſt; and this Antichriſtian Kingdom will rage as much as they can to their power to ſhed Bloud, but the Lord hath them in this Chain, and hath ſent forth his hoſt againſt them:</hi> They were not the Parliaments Forces, but the Hoſt of the Lord ſent againſt Antichriſt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were ſo earneſtly exhorted never to ſhrink, but joyfully to loſe their very lives in ſo <hi>good a cauſe.</hi> Mr. <hi>Midhope</hi> at the Funeral of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170992:47"/>Colonel <hi>Gold,</hi> exhorted the Militia thus:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>St. Midb.</hi> 1644. p. 24.</note> 
                     <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Commanders, be active for Chriſt, ye cannot do or ſuffer too much in his Cauſe.— Lay out your Time, Strength, Parts, your All for Chriſt; fear no loſs here, ye cannot drive a more gainful Trade.</hi> Could any thing more have been ſaid to the bleſſed Martyrs? Or did ever the Pope recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his <hi>Croiſadoes</hi> more highly?</p>
                  <p>What hath been ſaid, proves it to the full, that you valued your intended Reformation more than Chriſtianity it ſelf, (which 'tis no thanks to you if it was not quite deſtroyed by theſe moſt nefarious and unchriſtian actings.) Now two Witneſſes more will make it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unqueſtionable, that from the beginning to the end, that curſed War was raiſed and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented to maintain your new-faſhioned Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and to bring about your Reformation. Mr. <hi>Cheynell</hi> told the Parliament,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>F. Cheynel</hi> 1646. p. 32.</note> 
                     <hi>Conſider the cries and out-cries of the Godly Party of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for a Reformation, they ſpeak plain and tell you, that they have faſted, prayed, and wept for a Reformation, they have exhauſted their Treaſures, many of them ventured their Lives, loſt their Limbs, their Bloud, their Friends for a Reformation; you have promiſed us a Reformation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">N. B.</note> 
                     <hi>we have paid for a Reformation, you are therefore indebted to us of a Reformation, we are bound to challenge ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation as will quit coſt and anſwer the price we have paid, and the pains we have beſtowed,</hi> &amp;c. And Mr. <hi>Jeniſson</hi> a Scotch-man in a Sermon at <hi>New-caſtle,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rob. Jen.</hi> 1648. p. 29.</note> 
                     <hi>The late deſigns of the Popiſh and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Party tending to the utter ſubverſion of our Religion and of our Liberties, occaſioned the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170992:48"/>Covenant between</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland, <hi>and the joining in Arms for the defence of their Religion.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">N. B.</note> Now I hope it is clear enough that it was you chiefly (if not alone) that raiſed and fomented that execrably <hi>Holy War,</hi> to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh your projected Religion and Diſcipline: And if you dare ſay to the contrary, you muſt give the lye to your own Fellow-labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for you ſee I have it from them. So I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive that you and I have made it appear that you are not only not ſubject to Kings and Princes, but ever in ſome ſort their Superiours; and that when you judge Religion concerned, you will loſe the bonds of Allegiance, make Subjects to rebel againſt their Sovereign, and be as active for the <hi>Kirk,</hi> as ever the Pope was for the <hi>Church:</hi> ſo that in this, you wanted nothing of being right Catholicks, but that you did not fight to advance the holy <hi>See,</hi> but the holy <hi>Claſſis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis well you can make an end at laſt. I could find in my heart to let you talk alone, you are ſo infinitely tedious, eſpecially in your Citations.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I know that ſuch grave and ſerious men as you are, are gifted with a great deal of patience: but yet let me tell you, that I could be a great deal more tedious; you have made the ſubject in hand ſo copious, that one muſt write Volumes that would treat it in its full La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. But what have you to ſay next?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſay, (being we are diſcourſing of War) that you Papiſts are cruel and mercileſs to thoſe that differ from you in Religion; as appears by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170992:48"/>your Maſſacres and Inquiſitions abroad, and your Perſecutions and Plots here at home: and you make people believe, that in their bloudy cruelties againſt Proteſtants they do God great ſervice. I am ſure we are quite of another temper, for we preach meekneſs and forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of one another, and are for Liberty of Conſcience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I know you ſhall never lack com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation for want of ſpeaking well of your ſelves: your words then are all honey, honey-ſweet, but the miſchief is that your actions are in the other extream as bitter as gall. 'Tis true, you are now for forbearance and Liberty of Conſcience: but when you had the Power in your hands, no men ever more ſtrict and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere. You tied your ſelves by a ſolemn Oath, <hi>Faithfully to endeavour the diſcovery of all Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and evil Inſtruments that ſhould hinder the Reformation of Religion, that they might be brought to publick tryal, and receive condign puniſhment,</hi> in the fourth Article of your <hi>Solemn League and Covenant for the Reformation and defence of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> (as you call'd it:) and ſo whereas there are but few Inquiſitors in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> you had thouſands of them among you; every man that had taken the Covenant was bound to be one, bound to accuſe his own Brother if he were not of your party. And ſo 'tis ſaid of Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> that he performed this part of his Oath very conſcientiouſly: as indeed it was his Doctrine in his Sermons on the Covenant:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Caſe.</hi> p. 56</note> 
                     <hi>If any one perſiſt to hinder Reformation, be it the man of thine own houſe, the husband of thine youth, the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170992:49"/>wife of thy boſom,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>thou muſt with all faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs endeavour the diſcovery, thine eye muſt not pity nor ſpare,</hi> Deut. 13.6, 7, and 8. But I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you would ſpeak of cruelty, my laſt Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of your Authors being ſo full of it: It ſeems you would have me make it out that there is a perfect reſemblance betwixt your Church and ours in our Zeal for <hi>God and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> Well, you ſhall be ſatisfied.</p>
                  <p>You know the firſt thing we do to Hereticks is to Excommunicate them: ſo Mr. <hi>Cheynel</hi> would have thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſerv'd, in the Epiſtle Dedicatory of his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Sermon, he deſires the Parliament. <hi>That if bloudy Delinquents come to compound, their Compoſition may not authorize them to communicate at the Lords Table.</hi> And he tells them at the 44 pag. <hi>There are ſome ſly Malignants who are too wiſe to be ſcandalous, they do not roar like a Lion, but fret like a Moth; you will be importun'd that thoſe men may be ſpar'd, becauſe they are not ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous in their lives: have you not read of one, Qui ſobrius acceſſit ad perdendam rempublicam? Muſt men be ſpar'd becauſe they do not fiercely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault Church and State?</hi> It ſeems their honeſty would ſignifie nothing to excuſe them from your perſecution, as long as they were not of your party. Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> had found a way of puniſhing the Biſhops in caſe they ſhould eſcape with their lives, which I don't remember to have ever been uſed amongſt us:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>T. Coleman</hi> 1644. p. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>Look to all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,</hi> (ſaith he to the Parliament) <hi>and ſpare none; and amongſt the reſt the Prelates, whoſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences in caſe they ſhould not be found capital, that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170992:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>device of ſending them to</hi> New-England <hi>tranſcends all the inventions I ever met with:</hi> as good have caſt them with <hi>Daniel</hi> into the Lions Den. Nay, it was ſo much a duty to God to ſhew no mercy to any of the Kings Party, that he had told them before, pag. 15. <hi>That their ill ſucceſs in the Weſt was becauſe of their careleſneſs in keeping and deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Delinquents,</hi> and proves it by this Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.42. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt let go out of thy hand a man whom I appointed to utter deſtruction, therefore thy life ſhall go for his life, and thy people for his people.</hi> So Mr. <hi>Caſe</hi> in a Sermon to the Court-Martial at the 13 pag. <hi>There is no dealing with God now,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>T. Caſe,</hi> 1644.</note> 
                     <hi>God is angry, he ſeems to ask this once more, Will you ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>k? will you execute Judgment? or will you not? Tell me: for if you will not, I will; I will have the Enemies bloud and yours too, if you will not execute Vengeance upon Delinquents.</hi> At the 16 pag. he tells them, <hi>That God would have Judges to ſhew no mercy when the Quarrel is againſt Religion and the Government of Jeſus Chriſt. Thoſe men that would riſe up in curſed practices to bring in Idolatry and falſe Worſhip, to depoſe Chriſt from his Throne, and ſet up Antichriſt in his place,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſuch a Generation hath Chriſt doom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to execution,</hi> Luk. 19.27. <hi>Thoſe mine Enemies that would not have me to reign over them, bring hither, and ſlay them before me.</hi> And at 18 pag. <hi>What ſeverity will God expect from you in theſe caſes, who are call'd this day to judge for God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſons of</hi> Belial, <hi>bloudy Rebels, and an whole Chriſtian hurch and State now reſiſting unto Bloud for Reformation? Let me ſay to you as God
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170992:50"/>to</hi> Moſes <hi>concerning the Midianites, Vex theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianites and ſmite them, for they vex you with their wiles,</hi> Numb. 25.17, and 18. Behold how the Godly ſanctified their cruelty with pieces of Scriptures, and thereby preſt it as a moſt indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable duty! Mr. <hi>Joſeph Boden</hi> alſo in his forecited Sermon, pag. 16. and 18. exhorts the Committee to do the utmoſt as they could againſt the Malignants. <hi>God arms them</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with ſtrength againſt his people, becauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore and now alſo they have and do find too much favour at our hands.</hi> I am confident the next time the Devil gets into the Pulpit he'll preach as good Divinity upon this ſubject as this man, and many of his Brethren did. It was ſo eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial a part of your <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> and ſuch an acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable piece of ſervice to Chriſt, to ſhew no mercy to the Malignants, that it was the praiſe of a dead Saint,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>S. Midhope</hi> p. 22.</note> (Colonel <hi>Gould) That he had been impartially active in puniſhing Malignants againſt the cauſe of Chriſt, and therein another</hi> Moſes. And indeed who would have ſhewed any love to thoſe ugly Cavaliers, who were Gods Enemies? <hi>Remember</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Leech</hi> before he exhorted thoſe that were on Gods ſide to throw down <hi>Jezabel) that we cannot be rightly for God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer. Leech</hi> p. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>if we be not againſt thoſe that are againſt God: Gods Friends muſt be our Friends, and Gods Enemies muſt be our Enemies.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was (I ſuppoſe) that your minds were ſo imbittered againſt the Malignants, that you breathed cruelty againſt them in your very Prayers. Mr. <hi>Teſdale</hi> one of your holy Synod exhorting the Houſe of Commons to pray for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170992:50"/>the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which was the words of his Text, out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.6. <hi>Iſrael</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and</hi> Amalek <hi>join Battel daily: ſhould not therefore</hi> Moſes <hi>hands be lift up in prayer, and</hi> Aaron <hi>and</hi> Hur <hi>help to ſuſtain them, until the Lord hath avenged us of our Enemies, of pray for the peace of</hi> Jeruſalem? But for a concluſion, hear what Mr. <hi>J. W.</hi> Batchelor in Divinity, preacht upon a Thankſgiving-day for your Victory at <hi>Heſſammoor:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">p. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Moſt of them</hi> (Cavaliers) <hi>are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately wicked, whom Satan hath principled to make haſte for Hell: there is no deſign ſo deſperate as ſome of them will not attempt, though uſually they be bulletted and ſent out of this life for it, and ſent to meet with ſuch Matches as will keep fire for ever.</hi> It ſeems their ſouls found no more mercy at your hands than their bodies did, you ſent them ſtraight to Hell. Whence by the way it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, that your Power reacheth downward further than the Popes; for his as yet goeth that way no further than Purgatory. But what a pity 'tis that you were not of the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> VVhat brave Champions ſhould we have had? And what a loſs is it that ſuch <hi>fervent Zeal</hi> was ſpent upon a wrong Cauſe? But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, right or wrong, it appears that you made the people believe that cruelty to your Enemies was an excellent piece of Religion, and moſt acceptable to God: and ſo, dear Sir, in this we may alſo ſhake hands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>You are a lying Calumniator, and it is your cuſtom to load with reproaches, and the blackeſt of crimes, thoſe whom you are not able to encounter with Reaſon and Arguments:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170992:51"/>whoever will not dote upon your follies, you'll be ſure to defame and ſlander with your viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent tongues, and you make the vulgar abhor your adverſaries by repreſenting them as mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I aſſure you for all your anger, I had the very ſame thing to ſay to you; and if you ſpeak truth in this, we are really Brothers in iniquity: for you alſo clapt a moſt ugly Vizard on your Enemies face, and then brought them out to be worried by the people: Wicked, Accurſed, Popiſh, Babyloniſh, Antichriſtian, theſe were the colours you drew them in, as you may ſee in what follows. There was a Book printed 1643. by <hi>Thomas Watſon,</hi> call'd <hi>The Cavaliers Catechiſm,</hi> ſo foul, that I ſhould be aſham'd to mention it, but that you was not aſham'd to print it, or at leaſt to ſuffer it to be made publick: It was thus: <hi>What is your Name? Cavalier. Who gave you that Name? My Seducers and Deceivers in mine Innocency, wherein I was made a Member of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and conſequently a Limb of Antichriſt, an Enemy to all Godlineſs, the Child of the Devil, and an Inheritor of the Kingdom of Darkneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>What Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have you learned, and will you keep? Theſe following, To obſerve the Will of his Holineſs of</hi> Rome, <hi>To commit Treaſon againſt Kings that oppoſe him, and To commit Adultery, Rapine,</hi> &amp;c. But there was as bad as this ſpoken out of the Pulpit: <hi>Steph. Marſhal</hi> in a Sermon to the Mayor and Aldermen:
<note place="margin">S. <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſhal</hi> 1044.</note> 
                     <hi>Theſe are miſerable and accurſed men, theſe men are Factors for Hell, Satans Boutefeus, and as the true Zealots, are ſet on fire from Heaven,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170992:51"/>ſo theſe mens fire is kindled from Hell, whither alſo it carries them.</hi> So Mr.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>J. Vicars,</hi> p. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Vicars</hi> in his <hi>Jehovah-Jireh: I mean to make the godly Reader to ſee the diſtreſs and danger we were plunged in by the nefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Plots of Jeſuitical Prieſts and perfidious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, for I may moſt juſtly link them together like</hi> Simeon <hi>and</hi> Levi, <hi>brothers in iniquity, combining and complotting to reduce us to the accurſed Romiſh Religion:</hi> the whole Book is full of the ſame ſtuff. And there were <hi>Centuries of ſcandal us Malignant Prieſts,</hi> printed by the order of the Committee of the Houſe of Commons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Epiſcopal Clergy was charged with the moſt deteſtable crimes and abominations that could be invented. And Mr. <hi>White</hi> ſaith of them in the Preface, <hi>That they were dumb Dogs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jo White,</hi> 1643.</note> 
                     <hi>againſt whom God had proteſted for their ignorance, men ſwallowed up with Wine and ſtrong Drink, whoſe Tables were full of vomit and filthineſs, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers and Adulterers, who as fed-Horſes neigh'd after their Neighbours Wives, Buggerers, that chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the natural uſe in that which is againſt Nature, men unfit to live or to preach among Chriſtians.— Prieſts of</hi> Baal, <hi>of</hi> Bacchus, <hi>of</hi> Priapus. Pray what could you have ſaid worſe not only of us, but even of the lewdeſt Turks and Heathen? So Mr. <hi>Gill.</hi> at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in his Sermon to the Houſe of Commons on <hi>Ezck.</hi> 43.11. <hi>And if they be aſhamed of what they have done,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith at the 13 pag.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gilleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>The firſt Application ſhall be to the Malignants, enemies of the Cauſe and people of God at this time, who deſerve to have</hi> Jeremies <hi>black mark to be put upon them,</hi> Jer. 6.15. <hi>Were they aſhamed when they committed abomination?</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170992:52"/>Mr. <hi>Teſdale</hi> likewiſe in his fore-mentioned Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Teſd.</hi> p. 8.</note> Balaam <hi>may engroſs the Promotions of</hi> Moab, <hi>as the temporizing Clergy of late the Dignities of our Church; but upon ſawey terms they muſt come then and curſe Iſrael.</hi> And before at the 6 pag. he had joined together, <hi>the Atheiſts, Papiſt Prieſts, the Prelates, Iriſh Rebels, and the Engliſh Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, as</hi> Sampſons <hi>Foxes to deſtroy the Church and Commonwealth.</hi> Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> himſelf that man of moderation told the Commons,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>E Calamy,</hi> 1645. p. 26.</note> 
                     <hi>If there be any amongſt you that favour Malignants becauſe they are your Friends, though Enemies to God and his cauſe, this is a great ſin to be repented on greatly: I ſay to ſuch as the Prophet to</hi> Jehoſhaphat, 2 Chr. 19.2. <hi>Shouldeſt thou help the ungodly, and love them that hate the Lord?</hi> Any body whom you knew to be a Friend or an Helper to the King, was ſure to be a wicked man for his pains, and to have fine Epithets beſtowed upon him; as theſe:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Beech,</hi> 1645. p. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Have not our new</hi> Midianites, Aſſyrians, <hi>taking to their aſſiſtance the</hi> French Philiſtines, Welſh Egyptians, Corniſh Hungarians, <hi>the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate</hi> Iſhmaelites, <hi>and the Renegado</hi> Engliſh, <hi>have not theſe wreſted our lives?</hi> &amp;c. Nay, the Magiſtrates themſelves were not exempt from the ſting of your poiſonous tongues. Mr. <hi>Caſe</hi> told the Court-Martial,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Th. Caſe,</hi> 1644. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>That for many years Robbery, Violence, Murther and Treaſon, had ſate on the Bench, and not ſtood at the Bar,</hi> &amp;c. And your tongues were ſo inur'd to ſlander, that you could not ſo much as ſpare the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperours and Biſhops, who had been the great Propagators of Chriſtian Religion.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>T. Palmer,</hi> 1644. p. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>The wicked</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Palmer</hi>) <hi>and the Popes and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170992:52"/>Emperours, have agreed all along to perſecute Gods Saints, that hath gone on for above</hi> 600 <hi>years, they have been getting upon the Saints almoſt all this while, and therefore now 'tis no more but juſt with God to bring their time of loſing,</hi> &amp;c. Thus you ſee the conformity between you and us holds ſtill in this particular of ſlandering our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; or rather to give you your full due, you have out-done all Precedents by far, if not <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolos</hi> himſelf, the Father of Lyes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>I know not whether your Quotations be true: but this I am ſure of, that there is no men under the Sun ſo humble as the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, none acknowledge themſelves ſo vile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and make ſuch ſoul-humbling con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of ſin: whereas you magnifie your ſelves as the only people of God; you think there is no goodneſs to be found but only amongſt you, therefore you exclude all that are not of your Church out of Heaven: and ſo puft up you are with pride, that you dare talk of your merits, as though you were more than perfect.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Of Merits and Perfection another time if you pleaſe: for the preſent let us inquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you do not value your ſelves as highly as we do, and alſo ſhut out of Heaven thoſe that are not of your <hi>holy Sect.</hi> As for your long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of ſins, I confeſs that I have ſometimes admired how they could be conſiſtent with the good opinion you have of your ſelves. At firſt, I thought that you took a pride in profeſſing much humility, and poſſibly I was not much out, for you know you call him the Son of Pride, who calls himſelf <hi>Servus Servorum:</hi> But
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170992:53"/>I remember that heretofore you kept days of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation for the ſins of others. Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> in a Sermon to the Parliament, after he had told them how that ſins may be puniſhed long after their commiſſion,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>T. Coleman</hi> p. 14.</note> adds: <hi>This particular was taken to heart, when by an Ordinance you call'd upon the Kingdom to be humbled for the Bloud ſhed in the</hi> Marian <hi>perſecution: if ſuch an Ordinance was reprinted, with ſome additions concerning mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in Gods ſervice, and violence againſt Gods ſervants under the Prelatical Tyranny, it might poſſibly do much good:</hi> whereby it may ſeem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that in your long confeſſions you mean other mens ſins, and not your own. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it appears by what I have ſaid already, that you think your ſelves the beſt of men, or to ſpeak more properly, <hi>the holy ones, the elect and choſen people:</hi> you engroſs to your ſelves the names of <hi>precious, Saints and Godly,</hi> others go under the notion of <hi>vile,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Looking-Glaſs for Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,</hi> p. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>ungodly, reprobates. It grieves the Saints</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Vicars</hi>) <hi>to ſee thoſe miſerable Malignants to be ſo godleſs and graceleſs, ſo bitingly and bitterly to flout and affront the Lord Chriſt himſelf in his holy Members, and his moſt glorious Cauſe.</hi> And in his <hi>Jehovah-Jireb,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Baſtwick, Burton, &amp;c.</hi> brought out of priſon,
<note place="margin">p. 13.</note> he ſaith, <hi>Did not the Lord ſhew himſelf moſt ſtrangely in the Mount for the redemption of all theſe his beloved</hi> Iſaacs, <hi>and cauſe his wrath to lay hold on thoſe Romiſh Rams who were intangled in the buſhes of their Biſhoply abuſes to Gods children, and ſo by his admirable Providence to make them a prey to his juſt indignation, in ſtead of his innocent, his tenderly affected</hi> Iſaacs, <hi>his beloved Lambs.</hi> I
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170992:53"/>believe the Jews never put ſo many affronts and indignities upon the accurſed poſterity of <hi>Cham,</hi> as you did upon thoſe that were not enrol'd among your Saints.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer. Bur.</hi> 1643. p. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>The Lord hath raiſed up</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi>) <hi>the worſt, the vileſt upon the face of the earth, and they have poſſeſt the houſes of many of his Saints, the dearly beloved of Gods Soul.</hi> Is not this to the purpoſe? Nay, it ſeems, the bleſſed Apoſtles and firſt Chriſtians were inferiour in Saintſhip to your moſt incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable ſelves: ſaith Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>Look upon this Iſle wherein we live,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Th. Good.</hi> 1645. p 51.</note> 
                     <hi>as it is the richeſt Ship that hath the moſt of the precious Jewels of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt in it. — Let me uſe the ſame Expreſſion as I did in publick twenty years agone, That if we ſtood at Gods elbow when he bounded out the Nations and ſeaſons that men ſhould live in, we ſhould not have known (unleſs in Chriſts) in what Age or in what place we ſhould have choſen to have lived in, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the enjoyments of the Goſpel, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, more than in this Kingdom wherein we live.</hi> Now, my loving Friend, don't you think that we are alſo well agreed in this, in eſteeming our ſelves highly, and condemning others that ar not of our ſide as impious repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, fit only for Hell? All the difference lies in this, that we think well of our ſelves in that we obey our Church, and hold Communion with her; and you contrariwiſe make your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency to conſiſt in forſaking your Church, and endeavouring to deſtroy it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall repent by and by of the great pains you take for nothing: mean while I'll
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170992:54"/>give you leave to talk of what Maſter ſuch an one, and ſuch an one ſaith; and pray can you find by thoſe your Authors you have ſo ready at your fingers end, that we have merits of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity and merits of condignity, and that we can give Pardons and Indulgences, (if ſo be we can get money for them) Don't we teach that all our righteouſneſs is as a defiled Rag, and that our beſt works are rather ſinful, than merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>It may be ſo: but for all that, I can tell you of one thing that is hugely meritorious among you, and that is, the advancing <hi>of the Cauſe:</hi> the time was, when you exhorted the people to ſpend all upon ſo good a work;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>S. Marſhal</hi> 1644. p. 41.</note> 
                     <hi>Lay out your ſtrength, and hearts, and affections for the Lord, go on with all your might, with all your eſtates, with all your treaſure, whatever you have let God have it all in his Cauſe if he need it.</hi> And pag. 43. <hi>Who knows how far the Zeal of any one man may prevail? therefore go on in it to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, let Offices go, let Wife and Children go, let Eſtates go, be wholly for the Lord, and ſay, What may I do? wherein may I be imployed and laid out? what is there in my head or heart, in my ſoul or body, in my treaſury, ſhop or houſe, which may be of any uſe for the Lord?</hi> Mr. <hi>Teſdale</hi> in the ſame manner,
<note place="margin">P. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>Honourable Patriots, Chriſt is gone forth with his triumphing Army conquering and to conquer; and if you want Arms, or Money, or Horſe for their accommodation, God is the great Landlord of Heaven and Earth? Art thou then Gods Tenant? and doſt thou owe him Knight-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and Plough-ſervice, and doth he want thy
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170992:54"/>Horſe, and ſhall he not have it?</hi> &amp;c. Yea verily, it was ſo meritorious a thing to advance the intereſt of the <hi>holy Covenanteers,</hi> that that was call'd to help the Lord, and people were to do the utmoſt for it, and then an hundred-fold here, and eternal life beſides was the leaſt as they could have for a recompence. Mr. <hi>Bond</hi> after a long Exhortation <hi>to pull down Antichriſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh. Bond,</hi> 1644. p. 60.</note> 
                     <hi>and to do for the Lord,</hi> in the cloſe of all ſaith, <hi>I will recommend unto you theſe two eſpecial pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> Mat. 19.29. <hi>Every one that hath forſaken Houſes or Brethren,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and</hi> Mar. 8.35. <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall loſe his life for my ſake and the Goſpels, the ſame ſhall find it. O that they were written over the doors of the Houſes of Parliament! If theſe places do deceive an active Believer at laſt, then let it be written upon my Grave, Here lieth that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that was miſtaken in his God and Goſpel.</hi> Was not the acting for the Cauſe highly meritorious, when the greateſt of rewards were to be got by it? Wherein then lieth the difference? Only in this, That among you 'tis rebelling againſt the King and the Church, but with us 'tis good works only that merit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, but them good works conſiſt for the moſt part in being kind to the Fryars, thoſe good ſouls who have vowed forſooth to follow the counſels of perfection, poverty, chaſtity, and blind obedience, and yet preach themſelves more than Jeſus Chriſt; and in begging about, make people believe that the beſt ſervice they can do to God, is to do them good: whereas you ſee by your own Citations, that what our Miniſters did, was out of Zeal for Gods Cauſe,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170992:55"/>to advance his Honour, and not their own Profit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, that was a piece of deceit and craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs, whereby they out did the Fryars them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to call their own, Gods intereſt, to give ſpecious names to their own devices, as if God and Religion had been much concern'd in the eſtabliſhing of them, and to make the world believe, that to pull down the Church was to pull down <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and to ſet them up, was to ſet up <hi>Chriſt in his Throne:</hi> yet <hi>terminis termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natibus,</hi> they would ſpeak it out too, that they and their followers were to be uſed kindly, and that it was the duty and intereſt of the whole Nation to do good to the <hi>Saints,</hi> and to make as much of them as they could. I confeſs you never oblig'd your ſelves to obey the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick counſels, but you went as near to it as any bad Copy can reſemble a good Original: for you vow'd to <hi>ſpend your Lives and Eſtates</hi> upon the work in hand, that was poverty to the height. You vow'd to reform the Church <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the pattern of the beſt reformed Churches, to extirpate Superſtition and Hereſie, and to preſerve the Rights and Priviledges of the Parliament, and the Liberties of the Kingdoms.</hi> All which I am ſure was blind obedience, for not one of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred as took the Covenant underſtood what theſe things meant, and were therefore to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low you blindfold. And if in ſtead of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency you'll give me leave to put obſtinacy, we have found the three Monachal vows in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant: for you ſwore <hi>never to ſuffer your ſelves directly or indirectly, by whatſoever combination,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170992:55"/>perſwaſion or terrour, to be divided or withdrawn from your bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion or Conjunction,</hi> (as you call'd it) <hi>but zealouſly and conſtantly to continue therein all the days of your lives againſt all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition whatſoever.</hi> And accordingly that renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Champion of yours who died a Martyr for the Covenant, ſaid on the Scaffold,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> Caſe, 1651. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1</note> 
                     <hi>I did oppoſe in my place and calling the Forces of the late King, and were be alive again, and ſhould I live longer, the Cauſe being as then it was, I ſhould oppoſe him longer.</hi> The good man would rather venture Damnation, than break the Covenant by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting of his Rebellion againſt his Sovereign, ſo binding was that <hi>Holy League</hi> which oblig'd him to be thus oſtinate.</p>
                  <p>But perhaps you won't believe what I have ſaid, that you made the people believe it was a moſt meritorious thing to be kind to you, and that you preacht your ſelves as much as ever the Fryars did: if not, at leaſt believe theſe preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men. Mr. <hi>Dury</hi> having obſerv'd out of his Text, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 52.11. that God <hi>hath veſſels belonging to him,</hi> tells the Houſe of Commons,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dury,</hi> p. 14</note> 
                     <hi>God hath intruſted ſome with thoſe his Veſſels, and charged them with the care of them, to look to them, to bear them up, &amp;c.</hi> and then having extol'd the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant up to the Skies, he ſaith, pag. 24. <hi>This is a new thing in the Chriſtian Church, there is a ſpecial engagement lying upon us all more than upon other men to bear every one our own veſſels, to bear the veſſels of each other, and to bear jointly the Church and Cauſe of God in our hearts, hands and ſhoulders. In all the World there is not a Magiſtracy ſo eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entruſted with ſuch a charge over a people ſo nearly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170992:56"/>united unto God as you and the Parliament of</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>are.</hi> Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> likewiſe told the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer. Burr.</hi> 1645. p. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>It hath been the honour of ſome of you to receive and countenance godly Miniſters who ſuffered under the Tyranny of Prelates, this Chriſt hath ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you for, and we hope it ſhall be remembred for good to you and yours, let not your hearts be changed towards theſe men.</hi> And pag. 45. <hi>My Lords, you are advanced to high power and honour in a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom where Chriſt hath as many Saints, (I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid as in the World beſides) he expects you ſhould uſe them kindly.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Th. Good.</hi> 1645. p. 5. and 6.</note> And Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> to the Houſe of Commons obſerves out of his Text, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.14. <hi>Here is the nearneſs and dearneſs of the Saints to God, they are dearer to him than Kings and States ſimply conſidered, and here is the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Kings and States to deal with his Saints otherwiſe than well.</hi> And then towards the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end, pag. 52. and 53. <hi>It is not the having Saints, and multitudes of Saints, but the uſing them kindly, that is the intereſt of a Nation. The Saints of</hi> England <hi>are the intereſt of</hi> England, <hi>look to and keep this your intereſt, namely, maintain and preſerve the Saints among you, and make provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for them as you would preſerve this Kingdom.</hi> And then he repeats it again, p. 54. <hi>The Saints of</hi> England <hi>are the intereſt of</hi> England, <hi>write this upon your walls, and have it in your eyes in all your Conſultations, and have reſpect to the Saints the whole lump of them, if you will maintain your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt whole and intire, have regard to the Saints ſmall and great.</hi> More could not have been ſaid to perſwade the people to do you good, and in this you are in no wiſe inferiour to the moſt ſelf-preaching Monks.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170992:56"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſcorn your words, we are in nothing like your fooliſh Fryars: Presbyterians are a ſerious and conſidering people, who ſerve God according to his VVord in ſpirit and in truth; whereas they mind nothing but their fopperies, their ſuperſtitions and biggotteries, whereby they have made Religion ridiculous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, you would fain make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that your new-deviſed Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and every thing you ſpeak and do, is Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and according to the Spirit, and truth; and to hear you cry up your Orders and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward circumſtances of divine Service, one would think you had found Scriptural or ſpiritual Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies. But when all comes to all it is only this, that you make Religion and Godlineſs to conſiſt in rejecting that decent and inſtructing Order in Divine VVorſhip which the Primitive Church uſed, and tranſmitted to us, for to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your irreverent and unſeemly manner of worſhipping God according to your own minds. But that you alſo have done enough to make Religion ridiculous and fabulous too, is eaſie to be ſeen by what I have ſaid, and ſhall ſay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the many <hi>intolerabiles ineptias</hi> you preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your beſt-ſtudied Sermons before your Parliament, and printed afterwards as being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Diſcourſes, are ſufficient proofs that your grave out-ſides are inwardly full of emptineſs, or ſomething elſe: and I proteſt nothing can fully repreſent how ridiculous you have made the Publick Offices of Religion, as being an eye-witneſs of it in your Private Meetings. And had you not beſotted your people by making
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170992:57"/>them believe that what others do is all <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> but what you do your ſelves is <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Gods Ordinance in purity,</hi> they would hiſs you out of your Desks, or at leaſt leave you there alone to enjoy your extravagant humours. I leave it as a concluſion to be drawn from our whole Diſcourſe when it is ended, that you have made Religion ridiculous, or rather that yours is a mock-Religion, conſiſting alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as to the exterior of it in new-made Prayers and Sermons, ſpoken with a certain pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous tone, and ſome affected faces and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxiſms of Zeal, ſuch as Mr. <hi>Cheynel</hi> was in when he told the Parliament,
<note place="margin">1646. p. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>I arreſt you this day at the Suit of the great Jehovah, for a Debt of ten thouſand talents, nay, millions of millions, and over and above of High Treaſon againſt the three Perſons of the ever-bleſſed Trinity;</hi> and then he was in a Trance, pag. 24. <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I feel, I bleſs God I feel my ſelf tranſported even beyond my ſelf with raptures and extaſies of love: I could tell you of Chriſt-concerning-points, and Soul-concerning-points, of Parliament-repentance, and Sacrament-repentance, and Bed-repentance, and Shop-repentance,</hi> and many ſuch new-coined phraſes, which are none of the leaſt part of the <hi>powerfulneſs of preaching:</hi> And I could tell you of a receipt which is as the extract of a Book, called, <hi>Parliament-Phyſick for a ſick Nation,</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed by Mr. <hi>J. Cranford,</hi> which makes a mock-Phyſick or Divinity of all Evangelick and moral Vertues.
<note place="margin">1644. p. 112.</note> A great deal of fopperies and futili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as you charge us with, might be pickt out of the Sermons as you then printed; and I
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170992:57"/>doubt not but the Prayers were much after the ſame ſort, had they come out in print: and if my Notes deceive me not, what you preach now is not much better: but I will not ſay any thing except what I have under your hands. But this needs not be proſecuted directly any further.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>What of all this? Theſe be perſonal fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. I don't know how we are come inſenſibly to talk of things that are meerly practical, whereas we was to ſpeak of Doctrinal points. I'll give you but two or three inſtances more of the wide difference that is betwixt us, and then let all the world be judge how impertinent you have been in charging Popery upon us. And firſt, you make outward ſplendor and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to be a mark of the true Church, whereas we teach according to Divine and Humane Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, that the Church hath her wanes as well as her fulneſs, that ſometimes ſhe is fain to flee into the wilderneſs, and that her Glory may be eclipſed without ſhe doth ceaſe to be the true and only Spouſe of Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I hope you love us never the worſe for that agreement as you ſee is betwixt us in practical points, for thoſe be the moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. But as for what you mentioned laſt, I muſt confeſs that after the Kings and the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches return to their right, you taught,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>E. Calamy,</hi> 1662. p. 10. &amp; 14</note> 
                     <hi>That the Ark of God was in great danger, and very near to be loſt, gray hairs</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Calamy) are upon the Goſpel: I ſay not that the Goſpel is dying, but that it hath gray hairs. I dare challenge any Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to ſhew me an example of any Nation that hath enjoyed the Goſpel for an hundred years together,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170992:58"/>now that gray hairs is to an hundred years, is no wonder. Well, gray hairs are here and there, and yet no man lays it to heart.</hi> But then 'tis to be obſerved, that your Principles and Doctrines do change according to your condition,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Th. Good. Ph. Nye, Sy. Symp. Jer. Bur. W. Bridge</hi> p. 10.</note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as five of your Brethren told us in their Apology to the Parliament, <hi>This principle we carried along with us, not to make our preſent judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice a binding Law to our ſelves for the future.</hi> For in the days of your Power, you then followed God and Providence, every proſperous ſucceſs of yours was a mark that yours was Gods Cauſe, and you his beloved ones. <hi>Behold God in the Mount,</hi> cries Mr. <hi>Vicars</hi> at every advantage you had over the Kings party, in his <hi>Jehovah-Jireh,</hi> yea and your proſperity was a mark that you were deſtroying Antichriſt. <hi>Tho. Palmer</hi> in that Sermon 1644. dedicated to the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epiſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat.</note> hath theſe brave expreſſions: <hi>God hath put you in his own place, God hath grac'd you with his own Name, Lord of Hoſts, General of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, God hath committed to your care what is moſt precious to himſelf, precious Goſpel, precious Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, a precious Parliament, a precious people, God hath called forth your Excellency as a choice Worthy, to be his General, and the Champion of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to fight the great and laſt battel with Antichriſt in this your native Kingdom.</hi> So Mr. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryl</hi> in a Thankſgiving Sermon for a Victory of yours,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joſ Caryl,</hi> 1644.</note> 
                     <hi>Divine Providence is a leading Cloud to this day, it is ill to out-run Providence, and it is as bad not to follow it.</hi> Many things that I have ſaid before, will clear it enough that you made your good ſucceſs and proſperity an argument
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170992:58"/>of your being Gods Church and people, and I ſhall ſay more to it anon. I only add now, that as it is obſerv'd, that where Religion hath been looſeſt, there Fortune hath been moſt worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: ſo when you had broken all natural and religious bonds, you made uſe of the proſperous events of your enterprizes to juſtifie the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I ſee you'll make hard ſhift but you'll have ſomething to ſay. But can you find that we attribute to the Sacraments the vertue of working by their own efficacy the grace they ſignifie? (which you call <hi>opus operatum:</hi>) don't we rather teach, that nothing but Gods Grace can work any good in us, and that outward means are uſeleſs without it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I do ſuppoſe the Sacraments are of no great account amongſt you: whatever is not of your own appointment, is of little uſe or profitableneſs, though ordained by the firſt Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the Chriſtian Church, or by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But I could tell you of two or three things of your own deviſing, of as great force and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy as any of our Sacraments; that is, your Covenant, your powerful Preaching, and your extemporary Prayers; of the firſt, I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken enough already, how you made it <hi>a moſt precious and ſoul-ſaving Ordinance,</hi> and equalled it at leaſt to the Covenants God hath been pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make with Mankind; wherefore it was to be taken ſtanding uncovered, and one hand bare and lifted up, which is more of honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence than you afford to the bleſſed Sacrament of the Body and Bloud of Chriſt, which you
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170992:59"/>receive fitting upon your tails, or to any other part of Divine Worſhip. If any one will ſee more of it, let him read <hi>Thomas Mokett</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons on that ſubject, printed 1642. That your Preaching is likewiſe very powerful, I have evinc'd before, in that you call it <hi>the Goſpel,</hi> the Word of God, and make it in a manner equal to Scripture, as proceeding from the ſame Spirit, as Mr. <hi>Marſhal</hi> told the Parliament at a Thankſgiving-Sermon for ſome good ſucceſs of yours:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>S. Marſhal</hi> 1643. p. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>I ſhould ſend you home preſently, and command all of you not to weep to day, but to eat the fat, and drink the ſweet, but that I have firſt ſome banquetting ſtuff for your ſouls, ſuch as God hath brought to my hand:</hi> ſure they might make a very ſoul-refreſhing meal on what God himſelf had prepared! Mr. <hi>Palmer</hi> alſo pag. 27. <hi>How few come prepared to the Ordinances?</hi> (your preaching and Praying:) <hi>Who is it that conſiders the weightineſs of the buſineſs he is about? that he is now about a ſoul-ſaving or a ſoul-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying work?</hi> And accordingly in your Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing your Converts, if they be aged, the grand queſtion is, When, and at what time they were converted? for your Preaching works Converſion, even as Strong-drink works Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. When you have taught malicious or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people to rail at the Church, and to hate it, and thoſe that ſide with it, then the <hi>powerful Ordinance</hi> of Preaching hath done the feat! and the man is converted even as the weak-brain fellow that hath loſt his reaſon by too much drinking, As for your Praying, being it is by the Spirit, no wonder if it works ſtrangely.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170992:59"/>Mr. <hi>Vavaſor Powel,</hi> a holy man,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Life,</hi> 1671. p. 16.</note> and well worth to be credited, (though ſomewhat more Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick than you) for having a moſt authentick Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony and Approbation of fourteen of the chiefeſt Divines in the Aſſembly, did by his Prayers <hi>cure one Mrs.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">p 18.</note> Watkins <hi>of the Pariſh of</hi> Laningg <hi>in the County of</hi> Brecknock, <hi>who for two years together had kept her bed; and one</hi> Elizabeth Morris <hi>of</hi> New Radnorth, <hi>who was troubled with the Falling-ſickneſs and Convulſion-Fits;</hi> and did once in a wet Harveſt ſtop a moſt fierce rain,
<note place="margin">p. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>in ſeeking the Lord, and begging for fair weather.</hi> This will not ſeem ſtrange, if we conſider what one of you ſaid, That God had kindled the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent fire of Supplication in your hearts.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jehovah-Jireh,</hi> p. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>Oh how did the Lord-before and ever ſince this Parliament began, ſtir up and inflame the fire of ſupplicating faith, or faithful ſupplication and fervent zeal in private humiliation, to ſeek the Lord in the face of Chriſt for mercy and reconcilement to our poor Land!</hi> And then how could that fire that came from the Lord, do leſs than conſume and devour eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that ſtood in its way? As Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> ſaid to the Houſe of Commons,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh. Owen</hi> 1659. p. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>The Adverſaries openly confeſt, That there was nothing left for them to overcome, or to overcome them, but the Prayers of the Fanatick Crew.</hi> And as Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> ſaid to the ſame Auditory, <hi>We prayed at</hi> Nazeby,
<note place="margin">1645. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. &amp; 17</note> 
                     <hi>they plotted; ſee what end the Lord hath made, come and behold the works of the Lord. And at</hi> Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port <hi>and</hi> Bridgewater <hi>they could not ſtand, for God was againſt them: We prayed, we fought,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Th. Good.</hi> 1645. p. 42.</note> 
                     <hi>we conquered: certainly the power of Prayers is deſtructive.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Goodwin: God hath given
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170992:60"/>to thoſe his Saints</hi> (the Rebels) <hi>a Commiſſion to ſet up and pull down by their Prayers and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions.</hi> Whence by the way might be gathered, that you have ſome kindneſs for us, being you pull'd none down but the Church of <hi>England:</hi> But poſſibly the efficacy of your Prayers did not ſo much as the reach of your Piques and Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets. However, you ſee here is <hi>opus operatum</hi> with a vengeance, all the difference is that our Sacraments are of Chriſts Inſtitution, and work Grace only; whereas your powerful Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are of your own deviſing, and beſides Grace can work deſtruction.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>And can you find this one thing more about the Sacraments, that we take the Cup away from the people, as is the order of your Church, poſitively againſt an expreſs Command of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>Drink ye all of this?</hi> Sure you won't ſay we are guilty of diſpenſing with ſuch an expreſs Injunction of Chriſt as you do in this caſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>No, you never took the bleſſed Cup from the people, but you went very near to take away from them the ſacred Bread and all. You know how ſeldom and in how few places that holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament was adminiſtred in your reforming times; and you know how little regarded ſtill by many of your party, ſince you could preach and pray by the Spirit. And yet we are in good hopes that you'll comply with us in this too, for that in another caſe you can diſpenſe with as abſolute a command of Chriſt, that is, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lords Prayer, of which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>When you pray, ſay, Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170992:60"/>
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.2. But your wiſdom hath found it out that 'twas enough to ſay the ſenſe of that Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, without repeating the very words; and then if you ſhould uſe it, the people might be brought to believe that a ſet Form of Prayers is lawful according to ſo great an example, which might be a great prejudice to your more ſpiritual way of praying. And ſo you know our Church hath alſo <hi>many</hi> wiſe reaſons for not obeying <hi>Chriſt</hi> in this particular. Hereby it appears that you can as well as we make bold with an expreſs Law and Ordinance of Chriſt in what concerns the Worſhip of God; and what matters it though it be not in the ſame matter? they that can in one, can in all when they ſhall think good.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhould laugh if you could make it out too that we have amongſt us Miracles and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends, as I am ſure you have a great many to prove your new Religion by. Come, try your skill: I don't deſpair but one day you'll find out the Quadrature of the Circle, or the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual motion, you are ſo ingenious and ſo good at making diſcoveries.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>I can't tell what I ſhall do for the firſt, but I am ſure for perpetual motion the world is beholding to you for the finding of it out: for when you taught the people that nothing muſt be done in Divine Worſhip but what is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in Scripture, and that therefore the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy was to be put away: they finding that the order appointed in the Directory was no more to be found in Scripture than the other, took it away too; and ſo your Thorough-Reforming by ſuch an unlimited Principle, ſet a Wheel a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170992:61"/>going, whoſe motion 'tis likely will be perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual. You reformed the firſt Reformation, others reformed yours, and others that, and ſo on it went, and I believe will go as long as there is any brains in Schiſmatick-heads to keep on the Circulation.</p>
                  <p>But 'tis a thing ſo plain that you alſo have Legends and Miracles to perſwade the people of the Divineſs of your new-contrived way of Worſhip and Diſcipline, that my making of it appear will deſerve none of your commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I could tell you of a ſecret way of whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering Legends, fine well-made ſtories of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Prieſts, when <hi>the Brethren</hi> meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but poſſibly thoſe that don't know you ſo well as I do, would not believe me, therefore I'll inſtance in a few of a great many that are upon record.
<note place="margin">p. 8.</note> Mr. <hi>Vavaſor Powel ſaw ſeveral times the Devil appearing to him, ſometimes ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping upon the Chamber-floor, and ſometimes blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſtrong cold wind upon him, and ſeveral other ways: once it was revealed to him that he and two of his friends ſhould be wounded in the Iſland of</hi> Angleſſy.
<note place="margin">p. 17.</note> And another time, <hi>he being in his bed,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">p. 130.</note> 
                     <hi>there appear'd to him a bright ſhining light, and in the light a ſpeckled Bird, which bad him read</hi> Mat. 3.2. Mr. <hi>Cook</hi> likewiſe (no Divine I confeſs, but yet a man that well deſerves to be credited for being an holy Covenanteer) go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and meeting with a great and fearful ſtorm, which frighted him to ſome purpoſe, <hi>God</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>put in his mind the chief places in Scripture concerning the Seas;</hi> and then it follows, <hi>I preſt my dear Chriſt not to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170992:61"/>drown us, for, ſaid I, we fight for thy Kingly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: throw the Egyptians and all thine implacable Enemies in the midſt of the Sea, but let us be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</hi> Yet for all his fear and danger, he fell aſleep, and then, as he ſaith pag. 6. <hi>he ſaw a large Room, in the midſt whereof was a long Table, and upon that Table an ordinary Carpet, two Candles, two Trenchers of Tobacco, &amp; ſome Pipes: in the Room there was a man of a middle ſtature, his hairs were white and curling at the end, but the hair of his upper lip was brown, his cloaths were of a ſad colour, and upon his head was a Cloth-broad-brim Hat, and he told him he waited upon Jeſus Chriſt, and carried him to his Maſter, who told</hi> Cook <hi>that he ſhould not be drowned, hearing that he belonged to the Protector,</hi> (Traytor) <hi>and other ſtrange things which yet proved true in the event.</hi> Here be as you ſee moſt miraculous Viſions, the particulars whereof are related with ſuch exactitude, that I believe none but Malignants ever doubted of the truth of them. But I muſt not relate parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, my Book it ſelf ſhould be a miracle in bigneſs: if you pleaſe to read the <hi>Mirabilis An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> that was printed in 1662. there you ſhall find as the Author ſaith, <hi>many ſignal and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous judgments and accidents befallen thoſe that have moleſted the Godly for Nonconformity.</hi> And alſo Mr. <hi>Vicars Looking-Glaſs for Malignants,</hi> will furniſh you with many wondrous ſtories of the <hi>terrible and moſt dreadful judgments that befel the Malignants from</hi> 1640. <hi>to</hi> 1643. when the Book was printed. Theſe Books for Miracles and fine Tales may deſervedly be ranked among the moſt fabulous Legends that ever were
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170992:62"/>printed: and though 'tis likely the Authors did not believe them, yet they ſerved your turn: Thoſe <hi>pious frauds</hi> won more Proſelytes to your ſide than any thing elſe next to your Weapons: all the difference is this, that our Miracles are wrought <hi>by the Saints,</hi> and yours <hi>for the Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>And ſo you cunningly inſinuate that we have Saints as well as you: What, don't you know we will not ſo much as call <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> Saints, we are ſo far from praying to them, or keeping days in their honour? Prove it if you can that in this particular your Doctrine and ours hath the leaſt reſemblance, and then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inſtancing any more, I'll make it appear that you have taken a great deal of labour to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>What! I have mentioned your Saints forty or fifty times out of thoſe of your Authors whoſe words I have cited, and now you ſpeak as if you had none at all. Why man, there is no people under the Sun that owns ſo many as you: 'tis true, you won't call the bleſſed Apoſtles and Martyrs by the name of Saints, that would be Popery and Superſtition: but you'll call your ſelves ſo very freely and humbly, and without any ſcruple, for it ſeems that is your due, and not theirs: any one that would throw a ſtone againſt the woman ſurprized in Adultery was <hi>ipſo facto</hi> made a Saint, contrary to what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the Goſpel; I mean, that every one that would help to throw down <hi>the Whore and Jezabel,</hi> (as you call'd the Church) were thereby immediately <hi>Canonized:</hi> ſo that the worſt of Fanaticks who help'd to do the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170992:62"/>work, have ſtill retained the Saintſhip you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd upon them, though ſince they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from you. As <hi>Thomas Brooks</hi> in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon dedicated to Sir <hi>Tho. Fairfax,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1648. p. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>To do glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly is to appear for the Saints, and ſide with the Saints, let the iſſue be what it will: O it is a baſe thing in thoſe that have appeared and ſided with the Saints, now to prove treacherous, and let the poor Saints ſhift for themſelves.</hi> And ſo before that in 1646. Mr. <hi>Cheynel</hi> inſtructed the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament concerning the Saints in this manner: <hi>I am ſo far from endeavouring to perſecute Saints,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">p. 37.38. &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>that I humbly deſire that we would all ſtudy how to make more Saints: Oh it will be a comfortable work to gather and order Saints of our own making.</hi> Nay, though ſome of the Saints were froward, and perchance unruly, yet becauſe they helpt to do the <hi>work of the Lord,</hi> they were not to be blotted out of the Calendar, for he ſaith a little before, <hi>Saints muſt not be perſecuted though they be peeviſh, nay deſperate. — I muſt not out of a ſullen humour deny a peeviſh Saint the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand of fellowſhip.</hi> But enough of this you ſhall find ſcattered up and down this Book.</p>
                  <p>Now as for your keeping of days for the old Saints, I confeſs you are not for that, neither do you keep any for Chriſt, that would be you know what. But you know alſo that when the deſigns of the <hi>new Saints</hi> were bleſt with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, there was by Authority a day kept in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of it with much ſolemnity. So it ſeems the deſtroying of the Kings Forces was a mercy great enough to make a Holy-day of it: but it would be Idolatry to do the ſame in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170992:63"/>of thoſe precious mercies the Church receives from what Chriſt did and ſuffered for her, and his holy Apoſtles after him. As for praying to the ancient and deſpiſed Saints, it would be to no purpoſe, your new ones having got their place, and belike their power too: we have ſeen already that your prayers are effectual beyond what their interceſſions could be, which is the reaſon I ſuppoſe that when any amongſt you is going a Journey, or hath ſome other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in hand, or feels the want of any temporal or ſpiritual thing, he deſires the prayers of the Saints in your Conventicles. So there appears to me no other difference in the caſe, but that our Saints are dead, and Canonized by the Pope, whereas yours for the moſt part are alive, and of your own making.</p>
                  <p>Now I hope I have ſatisfied you, and made it appear that you come much nearer to Popery than the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which by your own confeſſion hath nothing common with us that's bad but a few Ceremonies, and this of order, which don't much concern Religion, and which (according to your Chronology) were in the Chriſtian Church long before Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: whereas you own both in belief and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice many of the Popiſh Doctrines which are counted the worſt of our errours, only you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe them a little, and put them in a Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Garb.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>Worthy Sir! you might have ſpar'd your great pains, for all you have ſaid will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade any one man that we have any good will for the Papiſts, 'tis too well known that there is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170992:63"/>an irreconcileable antipathy betwixt them and us. No, we deteſt thoſe opinions and practices of yours which you would perſwade the world we approve and imitate, and we agree with you in nothing that other Proteſtants diſagree in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, we do, we both hate the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I am ſure we are agreed in that, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you have gone beyond us; as I remember Mr. <hi>Love</hi> ſaid when there was an overture for peace, pag. 42.
<note place="margin">At <hi>Ux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Is it likely to have peace with ſuch men as theſe?—We can as ſoon make fire and water to agree, I had almoſt ſaid reconcile Heaven and Earth.</hi> But there is enough ſaid already to prove that. As for your diſclaiming friendſhip with us, it only perſwades me that you are of thoſe generous Friends who oblige people behind their backs, without deſiring that any notice ſhould be taken of it: for to uſe Mr. <hi>Loves</hi> words, pag. 22. <hi>When <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou had put down the Peſts and Plague-ſores of the Kingdom, Epiſcopacy and Common-Prayer Books,</hi> you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by advanced our intereſt greatly, and did us a notable piece of ſervice; for then you left no viſible Church, no known Rules of Doctrines, no ſet form of Government and Diſcipline: ſo that whilſt your tedious Rabbies were hammer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their brains the new form of a future Church, according to their ſeveral fancies, or according to <hi>the Pattern in the Mount,</hi> the people were fain to betake themſelves, ſome to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of our Church, as not a few did, and other ſome to Madneſs and Enthuſiaſm, as did a great many more. And beſides, the ſcandal which you brought upon the firſt Reformation
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170992:64"/>by your <hi>fine doings</hi> was ſo great, that (thanks be to you) it hath perſwaded a great many that there is no ſafety but in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> where there is a conſtant union and order. So we find a Book printed in 1652. call'd, <hi>A Beacon ſet on fire, or an Information of the Stationers to the Parliament concerning the great advancement the Papiſts made, and the many Books they printed, as alſo the many blaſphemous Books which others put out.</hi> And in <hi>the ſeaſonable Exhortation of the</hi> London-<hi>Miniſters</hi> 1660. they tell us pag. 10. That <hi>all manner of blaſphemous and horrid Opinions were openly written and publiſhed, that there was in many Atheiſm and contempt of Religion, in others Scepticiſm and Irreſolution in many, and that ſome were grown to that heigth of wickedneſs as to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Devil himſelf.</hi> And there they complain alſo, <hi>That ſome by their back-ſliding and apoſtacy fell from the truth to Popery, as being the only Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion wherein unity and order was retained.</hi> All which how naturally they iſſued from your late doings, and how much the Pope and Devil were beholding to you for, I leave to your own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienciouſneſs to conſider. And one thing more that makes me believe that you have more kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for us than you own by words, is, that you deſtroy'd the King and the Church of <hi>England</hi> by the ſame means that were appointed by <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panella</hi> a cunning Politician, and a great Enemy to Proteſtants, pag. 160. <hi>The Engliſh Biſhops</hi> (it ſhould have been Puritans) <hi>are to be exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and put into fears and jealouſies, by telling them that the King of</hi> Scotland (King James) <hi>turned Proteſtant out of hope, but that he will quickly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170992:64"/>return to the former Religion when he is eſtabliſht in the Engliſh Throne.</hi> (The ſame advice is alſo lately given by the Marquiſs <hi>de C. in his Politique de France,</hi> in that Chapter that treats of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>) That counſel was followed by you, and prov'd ſucceſsful; the outcry whereby you rais'd the people againſt our late martyr'd Sovereign was Popery, <hi>Rome, Babylon:</hi> therefore after all this, judge you whether we muſt not be very ungrateful if we did not ingenuouſly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that we are highly beholding to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>All that ſignifies nothing: for we differ from the Church of <hi>England</hi> only in ſome few Ceremonies, being agreed as to the Eſſentials both of Doctrine and Diſcipline. We honour the firſt Reformators of this Church, and we are perfectly agreed with the reformed Churches beyond Sea, which we love and reverence, and deſire to imitate: and when you have ſaid all you can, this will be truth ſtill, and I am ſure will be believ'd ſo to be by all rational men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>I know that one of your Brethren, an ancient Sophiſter, in his laſt ſcribbling againſt Doctor <hi>Durell,</hi> ſpeaks as if there was hardly any difference betwixt you and the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bonaſius Vapul.</hi> 1672. p. 80.</note> 
                     <hi>It may be worth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe who are in Authority whether they may not enjoy Eccleſiaſtical Preferments who differ from their Brethren only in ſome few points of Diſcipline; for as to the Eſſentials of Diſcipline, I am not ſo quick-ſighted as to find that we diſagree,</hi> &amp;c. But if it be ſo, the more wicked you, who have made crimes and enormities of a few indifferent points of Diſcipline. What, was it the tenderneſs of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170992:65"/>your Conſciences that made a few Ceremonies to be <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtianiſm?</hi> ſo that upon their account you muſt <hi>call upon the people in</hi> Sion <hi>to war againſt</hi> Babylon. Either you are the greateſt Cheats in the World, or elſe you differ from your Church at leaſt in thoſe points wherein (as I have ſhewn) you come ſo near to us: chuſe you which you pleaſe. As for your loving and honouring the reformed Churches beyond Sea, and the firſt Reformators of this, I find no ſuch thing in your Books, but rather that you lov'd and honour'd your ſelves far beyond them all. Mr. <hi>Dury</hi> in his Sermon to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament upon theſe words, <hi>Depart ye, &amp;c. Iſai.</hi> 52.11.
<note place="margin">p. 5.</note> is pretty plain in it: <hi>I choſe theſe words</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>becauſe the deſtruction of</hi> Babylon <hi>and the deliverance of the Church out of it, is the great work which God intends to accompliſh by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel in theſe latter times, and becauſe of the relation wherein we do ſtand to it, for I conceive that God is not only working out our deliverance to bring us out of</hi> Babylon <hi>at this time,</hi> &amp;c. Where could you have been worſe than in <hi>Babylon</hi> before the good men in King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth's time had done any thing towards a Reformation? So you may hear him ſay at the 25 pag. <hi>None of all the Magiſtrates or Miniſters of other Nations have ever given ſuch an anſwer to this Call</hi> (to come out of <hi>Babylon) as you and we of the Miniſtry and this people have done, for we have undertaken the Cauſe in the full extent thereof, therefore we are in this employment nearer unto God than any others, and he is more intereſt in us and in</hi> Scotland <hi>than in any other Nation whatſoever.</hi> Two Witneſſes
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170992:65"/>more I hope will make the thing credible. Mr. <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> in his Sermon <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.6. <hi>Reward her as,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">p. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſaith, <hi>'Tis no wonder that our forefathers did little or nothing againſt the Beaſt and the Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, for their eyes were blinded they could not ſee to work, much leſs to fight; but that we having clear viſions and full diſcoveries made of the Beaſt and her abominations, ſhould ſit ſtill and be careleſs, and ſuffer her for ever to play her beaſtly pranks, is a moſt deadly ſhame and ſtain unto us.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Tho. Goodwin</hi> in his foreſaid Sermon, <hi>Others had had the honour in the firſt Age of reforming,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">p. 52.</note> 
                     <hi>and we had been like blear-eyed</hi> Leah; <hi>yet ſince, we have been abundantly the more fruitful of Saints, faithful and choſen.</hi> And indeed the truth is, you went ſo far beyond all other Reformers, that you might well deſpiſe them, as having done their work very imperfectly to what you did.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                  <p>I took you to be but a Prieſt, but I doubt you are a Jeſuite too, for you can turn other mens words to what ſenſe you pleaſe: I believe thoſe good men meant no ſuch thing as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation you give to their words. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they did or no, 'tis nothing to us, we pin our faith upon no mans ſleeve; if they have ſaid or done any thing amiſs, we utterly diſclaim it. We own the Kings Supreme Authority and we own the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and to prove the contrary by particular mens words, (as you have endeavoured to do) is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together loſt labour, becauſe their Opinions is not the Rule we follow. So that all your Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations evince nothing of what you intended,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170992:66"/>and you well deſerve to be laugh'd at for having taken ſuch a huge deal of bootleſs pains in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating other mens words.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well! 'tis but making up your mouth, and wiping of it, and looking very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, and then you have done nothing; and ſo you think you can abuſe the world everlaſtingly. But ſtay, Sir, dear-bought experience hath taught us, that your goodly words are little to be truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and you have approved your ſelves ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Jugglers, that we will ſee what you tell us before we believe it. In the higheſt of your Rebellion you were for the King forſooth! much more now he reigns: <hi>Th. Palmer</hi> was <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Army raiſed for King and Parliament,</hi> as he ſtiles himſelf in the Title of his Sermon 1644. Mr. <hi>Peech</hi> at the Siege of <hi>Baſing</hi> was fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the King, pag. 24. <hi>We honour the King, we fight for him, we reſolve though it coſt us our lives we will have his love and his preſence again:</hi> And <hi>John Arrowſmith</hi> before the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons calls him his Dear Sovereign:
<note place="margin">1643. p. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>They</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that brought our King into this Civil War, are a Generation of ſcornful men that laugh at our Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as</hi> Sanballat <hi>and his Complices did at</hi> Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, <hi>What is this thing as ye do? will ye rebel againſt the King? a Generation which can neither find in their hearts to afford a good word of advice to our Dread and Dear Sovereign,</hi> &amp;c. But 'tis more than probable that by a worſe than Jeſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Equivocation, you meant only a notional King, the workmanſhip of your deceitful Brains: for ſo we find a cunning diſtinction between the King and the Kings Perſon. <hi>Tho. Caſe</hi> in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170992:66"/>to the Court-Martial on 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.6, &amp; 7. <hi>And Jehoſhaphat ſaid unto the Judges, Take heed what ye do,</hi> &amp;c <hi>Tell them, That though they had not a</hi> Jehoſhaphat <hi>to give them that charge in his perſonal capacity, yet they had him in his political capacity.</hi> So <hi>Robert Auſtin</hi> D. D. printed a Book intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to prove,
<note place="margin">1644.</note> 
                     <hi>That by the Oath of Allegiance the Parliament was bound to take up Arms, though againſt the Kings perſonal command, for the juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Kings Perſon, Crown and Dignity.</hi> So you might be ſure by ſuch means ever to be for him, and have him of your ſide whatever you did: for ſo Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> prov'd by the ſame art, pag. 27. That his <hi>moſt Loyal Party was not fighting againſt the King, but for the King, for the preſervation of true Regal Power in the King and his Poſterity, and to reſcue him from the hands of evil men, who were his greateſt Enemies.</hi> And he ſaid pag. 57. <hi>That the Saints and moſt Religious had ventured their Lives, Fortunes, Children, and all for the ſafety of the King.</hi> One would have taken him then for a great Royaliſt, but that there was an unlucky Equivocation in the caſe, <hi>The Scripture</hi> (ſaith he pag. 28.) <hi>bids us to be ſubject to the Higher Powers, it doth not bid us to be ſubject to the will of thoſe who are in higheſt places.</hi> But two or three ſpecious words ſerv'd the turn, this was chiefly to ſeduce the Kings own Friends if it were poſſible: Thoſe that had a Loyal Soul, here was a bait for them, <hi>you were fighting for to make the King great and glorious, though 'twas againſt his will, and for his Authority againſt his Perſon, and he was on your ſide in his Pelitical, though not in his Perſonal capacity;</hi> and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170992:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo if they lov'd the King; they might join with you; and no doubt but thoſe goodly pretences deluded then many a well-meaning Soul. But then if people were not for the King, to be ſure they would be for the Lord, and upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they might and they muſt join with you, for you <hi>were fighting the Lords Battels, warring for</hi> Sion <hi>againſt</hi> Babylon: this was the grand cheat whereby the Nation was deluded. Had the Parliament-Officers gone about and told the people that the King encroacht upon their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and acted againſt the Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom, the generality of men was not ſo well read in the ancient Statutes and Charters of this Realm as to know whether it was ſo or no; and ſo 'tis likely they had been very ſlack in engaging in a doubtful general. But you knew well enough that the people would right for God, therefore you made him a party in the caſe, and then called upon them <hi>to help the Lord againſt the Mighty, to help to throw down Antichriſt, and to ſet up Chriſt;</hi> and thoſe that came to your call, were rewarded (beſides the holy Plunder) with good words, flatteries, high and lofty titles; they were <hi>the Saints, the Godly, the Choſen, the Lambs Followers, and the precious Ones,</hi> and ſo you made them active in their wickedneſs by making their deluded Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to warrant their accurſed doings. Though the way was beſprinkled with bloud, yet that the people might not be deterred from doing <hi>Gods work,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Palmer,</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3.</note> they were told <hi>that God had ſeen it good to bring Chriſt into the Kingdom that bloudy way;</hi> and then who would be afraid of bloud-ſhedding
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170992:67"/>upon ſuch an account? But this hath been ſufficiently proved, when I ſpoke of your cruelties, and made it appear that the War was Religious and not Civil, and that for the good of Souls you may do what you lift as well as the Pope.</p>
                  <p>Now I deſire only to mention a few more of your juggling tricks, and then I ſhall endeavour to ſay ſomewhat in defence of thoſe Authorities I have cited out of your Books. Mr.
<note place="margin">p. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. &amp; 13</note> 
                     <hi>Palmer</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves that grand Query, How ſhall I know that the Parliaments Cauſe is Gods Cauſe, and thoſe that join with them more Gods people than on the other ſide? in this manner: <hi>Alas, it is the plaineſt thing in the world, look to the words of Chriſt,</hi> John 10.5, and 44. <hi>My Sheep know my Voice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now do but conſider which of the new-raiſed Forces come neareſt to this Rule; who is it that ſubmits to the Word and Rule of God? who ſet up the work of Reformation? who is deſirous to preſerve the people of God?</hi> Was not he an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Caſuiſt to make your pretences and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings an argument to prove that your War againſt the King was juſt? Much like him that ſaid <hi>it is and hath been the deſign and practice of Jeſus Chriſt to break all Kingdoms that oppoſe him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Th. Good.</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. p. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>and oppreſs his Saints:</hi> As much as to ſay, that God pulled down the King, becauſe he oppreſt Chriſt, and did not favour the Saints: by which Rule the beſt cauſe is condemned if it be unſucceſsful, and well-fare the Turk and all the wicked as long as they proſper: according to this we have ſeen before that <hi>Providence was your Guid and Captain,</hi> it led you, and did all things for you,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170992:68"/>and ſo it came to paſs that the worſt of your doings were charged upon God. <hi>Jehovah-Jireh,</hi> pag. 65. <hi>The Prentices and Porters were ſtimulated and ſtirr'd up by Gods Providence thouſands of them to petition the Parliament for ſpeedy redreſs.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Will. Jenkins</hi> in <hi>his Conſcientious Queries and Submiſſion to the then preſent Power</hi> 1651. uſeth only the Turkiſh Argument of good ſucceſs to prove that the proſperous Rebels were to be obeyed as lawful Superiours, and that by charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that had been done upon God and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, pag. 2. <hi>Whether the ſtupendious Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of God manifeſted among us in the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the late King and his Adherents in ſo many pitcht Battels, and in this Nations univerſal for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking of</hi> Charles Stuart, <hi>and the total overthrow of him and his Army; whether by theſe Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces God hath not plainly removed the Government from</hi> Charles Stuart, <hi>and beſtowed it upon others, as ever he removed and beſtowed any Government by any Providence in any Age? Whether a refuſal to yield Obedience and Subjection to this preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, be not a refuſal to acquieſce in the wiſe and righteous pleaſure of God, and a flat breach of the fifth Commandment?</hi> Therefore he ſaith in his Humble Petition, That <hi>he looks upon it as his duty to the then Authority to yield all active and cheerful Obedience in the Lord, even for conſcience ſake:</hi> as though their proſperous wickedneſs could give them a juſt title to their Uſurpation. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would have it believed that the <hi>Saints</hi> were victorious,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh. Owen</hi> 1659. p. 22.</note> becauſe of Chriſt being with them, and their having a Commiſſion from him to act as they did, ſaying, <hi>That the Saints and the ſecret ones
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170992:68"/>ſhall work deſtruction, and that this feeble Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be as a Lion from the preſence of Chriſt amongſt them. Chriſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>aſſigns that to them which is his own proper work: let men take heed how they provoke this Lion, for then he will not lie down until he eat of the prey, and drink of the bloud of the ſlain.</hi> As though it had been by the order and power of Chriſt that the <hi>Lion</hi> or the wild Beaſts had filled all the Nation with bloud and ſlaughter. Then in ſtead of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the people to obey the Precepts of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, Charity, Humility, Meekneſs, Obedience to the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you would have them mind the ſecret intentions of God, and ſet forward that work which his Providence had begun, as you ſaid, which was called Generation-work, a phraſe and a Doctrine ſtill in uſe amongſt you. <hi>It is the duty of the Saints</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>to obſerve what the way of God is in the time of their Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer. Burr.</hi> 1643. p. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>to ſee what Name of God is moſt conſpicuous in his adminiſtration, and accordingly to ſanctifie that Name of his.</hi> Nothing can be more pregnant with deluſions and evil conſequences than this. Afterwards when in the carrying on of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns in hand the Kingdom was filled with bloud and confuſion, that the people might not ſee how they were gull'd, you fell to prophecying, promiſing them much happineſs, with many ſecret and glorious things after all their trouble, ſo ſaith the ſame Author, <hi>ibid.</hi> pag. 6. <hi>We ſhall ſee at laſt that the mercy God intended for us was worth all the troubles and bloud,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>God hath many Promiſes to his Church to accompliſh, many Prophecies to fulfil, many glorious things to declare,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170992:69"/>many Mercies for his Saints to beſtow; and theſe ſtirs among us will make way for all.</hi> And ſo Mr.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh. Bond,</hi> 1644.</note> 
                     <hi>Bond</hi> tells the Parliament, That <hi>the preſent work of Salvation and Reformation they had in hand, was carried on in a myſtery, was a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed maſter-piece, altogether made up of ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, paradoxes, and wonders, and ſo the comfort is, it ſhall be a great Salvation, a Salvation from Babylon.</hi> But this will ſuffice at preſent to ſhew that the people was deluded more ways than one; and to give a warning to the following Generation, that ſo they never be drawn into Rebellion by the ſame arts and pretences as their Fathers were.</p>
                  <p>It would be endleſs to rehearſe all the equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, jugglings, and deceits as were uſed to ſeduce the people: next time we meet perchance you ſhall hear more of them. What I have ſaid now is enough to prove that your words ſignifie nothing but what you pleaſe, that your diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations are deep and ſpecious, and that you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver want arts and evaſions to plead innocency, and ſalve your credit after the fouleſt doings and miſcarriages. Now you differ but a very little from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and you are for Obedience to the King, whatever ſome of you may have ſaid or done heretofore. Very good! That's as much as to ſay, That do you what you will, you are reſolved ever to be in the right, and never to acknowledge your ſelves faulty in the leaſt, for fear of loſing the repute of Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. But let it be conſidered,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That I have proved what I charged upon you, not by the words of the obſcure and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170992:69"/>but of the moſt famous men of your Party, who muſt needs have known the Tenets and Doctrines of your Sect, and who were then and are ſtill now cryed up and followed by your Diſciples and Admirers.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That thoſe words of theirs I have cited, were not taken out of Libels or prophane Books, nor were ſpoken heedleſly in the heat of diſpute, but are to be found in their Sermons, and were delivered out of their Pulpits in the powerfulneſs of Preaching, as being the Word of God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That thoſe Sermons were not preached in Country-Towns, or to ordinary Congregations, (where any ſtuff preached after the tone and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in uſe among you had been as good as the beſt) but almoſt all of them before the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where none but great men were admitted to preach, and where, to be ſure, they preached none but their beſt Sermons: and moreover, that thoſe Sermons were printed with the names of the Authors, and with Licenſe and Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That 'tis more likely they would then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver their true Opinions, and ſpeak out what was in their hearts, when they had the power in their hands, and were free to ſpeak what they pleaſed, than now they are under fear and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and are fain to conceal or diſſemble what they would then openly preach and proclaim.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That they not only preached Sermons, but they and their Diſciples lived Sermons alſo; your practice and Doctrine agreed excellently well, what was preach'd was acted, there was none of their good Inſtructions loſt, you appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170992:70"/>what they ſaid by doing accordingly, and you generally own'd by a practical belief thoſe Doctrines I have ſet down as yours out of your moſt approved Authors.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, It is manifeſt by my Quotations, that your Miniſters rendred the laſt King odious to his people, and preacht him out of his Throne and Kingdom: but 'tis no where to be ſeen that they ever preach'd this King into the favour of his people again, or uſed their powerful elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to have him reſtor'd to his Right. And ſince his return, though you have given over printing, yet moſt of you have kept up the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and in ſtead of crying <hi>peccavi,</hi> have ſtill endeavour'd to weaken the Church, and draw Diſciples after you; and your Synods have never diſclaimed thoſe men who by their Preaching had kindled up the late Rebellion, and the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers have never recanted their former Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but either juſtified or diſguiſed them: nay, many of them own ſtill the Obligation of that infamous Oath call'd the <hi>Covenant,</hi> whereby they acted and warranted all their wickedneſs. Therefore though the people may be excuſed ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been deluded and impoſed upon, yet you the Miniſters and Heads of the Faction can never (with all the wit you have) plead any thing that can juſtifie you from owning the worſt of Popiſh Errours.</p>
                  <p>Now let our Judge ſpeak if he pleaſeth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>G.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſs I am ſomewhat amazed at what I have heard: I never thought ſo much could be ſaid for proving a Conformity betwixt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170992:70"/>and Presbyterians in ſo many points: but yet I will decide nothing, nor make any reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon what you have ſaid: I'll rather tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe and print your diſcourſe, and leave the Reader to think and to judge as his own diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall adviſe him. Only ſeeing that you are moſt chiefly agreed in denying the King that Supreme Authority which God hath given him, and pretending a certain Power and Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over him, <hi>in ordine ad ſpiritualia,</hi> for the good of ſouls, or to phraſe it aright, <hi>for to advance Gods Cauſe, and to ſet up Chriſt:</hi> I ſhall ſet down ſome Texts of Scripture which plainly evince the contrary, and then deſire all Chriſtians to yield a chearful and loyal Obedience, until they have been told from Heaven that the Pope or Claſſis are impowered from God to act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Word in this particular.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, For the Authority of the Supreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate over all that live in his Dominions, read <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, and 2. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers, for there is no power but of God; the powers that be are ordained of God: whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation.</hi> — v. 5. <hi>Wherefore ye muſt be ſubject, not only for wrath, but alſo for conſcience ſake.</hi> Here you ſee that neither Pope nor Puritan is except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but <hi>every ſoul is to be ſubject:</hi> this was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten when the Higher Powers were Heathen, bloudy Perſecutors of Chriſtianity, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to deſtroy the Goſpel; and yet for all that, they muſt not be rebelled againſt, and their Authority muſt not be reſiſted: <hi>Whoſoever reſiſteth
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170992:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>the power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation:</hi> and therefore we muſt be ſubject to them, not only for fear of their anger, but alſo for fear of Gods, <hi>not only for wrath, but alſo for conſcience ſake.</hi> In Tit. 3.1. <hi>Put them in mind</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>to be ſubject to principalities and powers, to obey magiſtrates, to be ſubject to every good work.</hi> You ſee that good works and obedience to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates are joined together, and appointed to be equally preſt upon the people by the Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Chriſts Miniſters. In the 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, &amp;c. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of men for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as Supreme, or unto Governours as unto them that are ſent by him: — for ſo is the will of God, that with well-doing ye may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men; as free, but not uſing your liberty for a cloak of maliciouſneſs, but as the ſervants of God. — Fear God, honour the King.</hi> You ſee it is the will of God that with well-doing, (that is) <hi>by obeying the King and his Governours,</hi> we ſhould put to ſilence the <hi>ignorance of fooliſh men,</hi> who thought that Religion freed them from the yoke of ſubjection: and that we <hi>ſhould not make Chriſtian liberty a cloak of maliciouſneſs,</hi> a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Diſobedience and Rebellion; but as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to God, honour the King, and ſubmit our ſelves to him <hi>for the Lords ſake.</hi> Therefore it is a great impiety and hypocriſie to pretend Gods cauſe and intereſt for rebelling and diſobeying, when he bids us for his ſake to obey and to be ſubject.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That none muſt preſume upon any account
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170992:71"/>whatſoever to rebel againſt the Sovereign or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governour, read <hi>Num.</hi> 16. at the 3. v. you ſhall find that <hi>Korah</hi> and his rebellious crew pleaded that <hi>the people was the Lords people, and that they were holy every one of them; and therefore</hi> (ſay they) <hi>to</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron, <hi>Why lift ye up your ſelves above the Congregation of the Lord?</hi> But at the 32. v. <hi>The earth opened her mouth and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them up, and their houſes, and all that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to them.</hi> And by that dreadful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard-of judgment, God manifeſted how much he deteſts Rebellion, that following Ages might beware of the heinouſneſs of that crime. So in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.5, and 6. <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſmote him becauſe he had cut off <hi>Sauls</hi> skirt, and he ſaid to his men, <hi>The Lord forbid that I ſhould do this thing unto my Maſter, the Lords Anointed, to ſtretch forth mine hand againſt him, ſeeing he is the Lords Anointed.</hi> And c. 26. v. 9. <hi>David</hi> ſaith unto <hi>Abiſhai, Deſtroy him not, for who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords Anointed, and be guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs? David</hi> was then Anointed King, he was perſecuted wrongfully by <hi>Saul, Saul</hi> was reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God, and he had moſt barbarouſly put to death the Prieſts of God, and their whole fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; and yet becauſe he was King over the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords Anointed and be guiltleſs?</hi> God as you ſee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows no pretence at all for Rebellion, for that as I have ſhewn you Kings have their Authority from him, <hi>By me Kings reign,</hi> ſaith the Divine Wiſdom, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15. and therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> joins God and the King together, as the objects of our reſpect and obedience, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21. <hi>My ſon, fear
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170992:72"/>thou the Lord and the King,</hi> and ſo <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.2. <hi>I counſel thee to keep the Kings Commandment, and that in regard of the Oath of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. We are not to ſpeak evil of the King, but rather to pray for him: in 22. <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods,</hi> (that is, Supreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates) <hi>nor curſe the Ruler of thy people.</hi> Job 34.18. <hi>Is it fit to ſay to a King, Thou art wicked? and to Princes, Ye are are ungodly?</hi> So it was witneſſed againſt <hi>Naboth</hi> by his falſe accuſers, <hi>That he blaſphemed God and the King,</hi> 1 King. 21.13. and then he was ſtoned to death. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appears, that in Iſrael it was one of the greateſt impieties to ſpeak ill of the King. As alſo it is commanded by <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thoughts,</hi> &amp;c. And you may ſee what a black character the Apoſtles ſet upon thoſe <hi>that deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> in the Epiſtle of Saint <hi>Jude</hi> and in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. Now that it is our duty to pray for the King, we have theſe examples, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.24. when <hi>Saul</hi> was anointed, the people cryed, <hi>God ſave the King;</hi> and ſo likewiſe when <hi>Solomon</hi> was anointed, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 1.39. But what need any more than this precept of St. <hi>Paul?</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, and 2. <hi>I exhort therefore that firſt of all ſupplications, prayers, interceſſions, and giving of thanks be made for all men, for Kings, and for all that are in Authority: — for it is good and acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable in the ſight of God our Saviour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, That we are to pay Tribute to Kings and Sovereign Princes, read <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.6, and 7. <hi>For this cauſe pay you Tribute alſo, for they are Gods Miniſters, attending continually upon this very thing.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170992:72"/>Render therefore to all their dues, tribute to whom tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute is due, cuſtom to whom cuſtom, fear to whom fear, honour to whom honour.</hi> If the Heathen Emperours were Gods Miniſters, and therefore to receive Tributes and Cuſtoms, much more the Chriſtian Kings that now reign over us. Moreover, we have the example of Chriſt himſelf, who when he had not wherewithal to pay that Tribute which the Roman Kings had impoſed upon the Jews, was pleaſed to work a miracle for to get money to pay it withal, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He that was and is King of Kings and Lord of Lords, the God of Heaven and Earth, pleaded no exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from paying Taxes, but bound this duty up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all his followers by his own example, and thereby confirmed alſo that precept which he gave us, (when the Jews asked him whether it was lawful to pay Tribute to <hi>Caeſar, Mat.</hi> 22.21.) <hi>of rendring to</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſars, <hi>as well as to God the things that are Gods.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now therefore let no Chriſtian dare to go againſt theſe ſo many and ſo plain and expreſs Scriptures in diſobeying or reſiſting his King and Sovereign under pretence of Religion, or of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving evil Councellors, or of fighting for the Kings Authority againſt his Perſon, or becauſe the Pope or the Presbyterian Synod enjoin him ſo to do, <hi>for the good of ſouls, for the cauſe and intereſt of Chriſt and the Goſpel:</hi> for you ſee that God makes no reſervations, and allows of no diſtinctions or equivocations, but bids <hi>every ſoul to be ſubject,</hi> and threatens <hi>damnation</hi> to any that ſhall not. And now, Sirs, I leave you to meditate upon what you have heard, and I heartily wiſh it may do you good.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
